Gewát him ðá se hearda mid his hondscole
Then the hardy man went with his hand-picked retinue
XXVIIII
sylf æfter sande saéwong tredan
himself along the sand treading the sea-plain,
wíde waroðas· woruldcandel scán
the wide strand; the world-candle shone,
sigel súðan fús· hí síð drugon·
the sun eagerly from the south; they had survived the journey,
elne geéodon, tó ðæs ðe eorla hléo
strode quickly, to where the Shield of Heroes,
bonan Ongenþéoes burgum in innan,
the bane of Ongentheow  inside his citadel,
geongne gúðcyning gódne gefrúnon
the young war-king, they heard (that there) the good man
hringas daélan. Higeláce wæs
alloted rings. To Hygelac was
síð Béowulfes snúde gecýðed·
Beowulf's journey promptly reported,
þæt ðaér on worðig wígendra hléo
that there in enclosed homestead, the defender of warriors,
lindgestealla lifigende cwóm
shield-companion (still) living came,
heaðoláces hál tó hofe gongan·
from the war-play unharmed going to to the court;
hraðe wæs gerýmed swá se ríca bebéad
quickly was cleared, as the king bade,
féðegestum flet innanweard·
for the visitors on foot the floor within;
gesæt þá wið sylfne sé ðá sæcce genæs,
then he sat down with the same man, he who had survived the fight,
maég wið maége syððan mandryhten
kinsman with kinsman, after the liege-lord
þurh hléoðorcwyde holdne gegrétte
through ceremonious speech his loyal subject had greeted,
méaglum wordum meoduscencum
in emphatic words, mead-draughts
hwearf geond þæt síde reced Hæreðes dohtor
passed round through that spacious room Haereth's daughter,
lufode ðá léode· liðwaége bær
she loved the people  bore goblets
haéum tó handa. Higelác ongan
to the hands of the illustrious ones. Hygelac began
sínne geseldan in sele þám héan
his hall-companion in that high hall
fægre fricgcean· hyne fyrwet bræc
to question courteously, his curiosity burst forth,
hwylce Saé-Géata síðas waéron:
whatever the Sea-Geats' adventures were:
'Hú lomp éow on láde, léofa Bíowulf,
'How fared you on the way, dear Beowulf,
þá ðú faéringa feorr gehogodest
when you suddenly resolved far away
sæcce sécean ofer sealt wæter
to seek conflict over the salt water,
hilde tó Hiorote? Ac ðú Hróðgáre
combat in Heorot? Moreover, did you Hrothgar's
wídcúðne wéan wihte gebéttest
widely known woes at all ameliorate,
maérum ðéodne? Ic ðæs módceare
for the famed chieftain? I of this with anxious care of the heart
sorhwylmum séað· síðe ne trúwode
seethed with wellings of sorrow, I did not trust the venture
léofes mannes· ic ðé lange bæd
of my dear man; I begged you at length,
þæt ðú þone wælgaést wihte ne grétte·
that you the slaughter-ghast would not challenge at all,
léte Súð-Dene sylfe geweorðan
let the South-Danes settle themselves
gúðe wið Grendel· gode ic þanc secge
the war with Grendel; to God I speak thanks,
þæs ðe ic ðé gesundne geséon móste.'
for that I you sound am permitted to see.'
Bíowulf maðelode bearn Ecgðíoes:
Beowulf spoke, the son of Edgetheow:
'Þæt is undyrne, dryhten Higelác,
'It is not secret, lord Hygelac,
micel geméting monegum fíra·
that great meeting, to many men,
hwylc orleghwíl uncer Grendles
what a time of struggle between the two of us, me and Grendel,
wearð on ðám wange þaér hé worna fela
occurred in that place where he great multitudes
Sige-Scyldingum sorge gefremede
for the Victory-Scyldings brought about sorrows,
yrmðe tó aldre· ic ðæt eall gewræc
lifelong misery; I avenged it all,
swá begylpan þearf Grendeles mága
thus there is need to boast  of Grendel's kinsmen,
yfel ofer eorðan úhthlem þone
evil upon the earth  of that clash at dawn,
sé ðe lengest leofað láðan cynnes
he who lives the longest of that hateful race,
fáecne bifongen. Ic ðaér furðum cwóm
enveloped in malice. I first came there
tó ðám hringsele Hróðgár grétan·
to that ring-hall to greet Hrothgar;
sóna mé se maéra mago Healfdenes
straightaway to me the famed kinsman of Half-Dane,
syððan hé módsefan mínne cúðe
after he the purpose of the heart of mine knew,
wið his sylfes sunu setl getaéhte·
with his own sons he appointed a seat;
weorod wæs on wynne· ne seah ic wídan feorh
The troop was joyful; I have not seen in my whole life
under heofones hwealf healsittendra
under heaven's vault a hall-sitters'
medudréam máran. Hwílum maéru cwén
mead-revelry greater. At times the renowned queen,
friðusibb folca flet eall geondhwearf·
the peace-pledge of peoples, passed over all of the floor,
bædde byre geonge· oft hío béahwriðan
urged on the young boys; often twisted-rings she
secge sealde aér híe tó setle géong·
gave to the warriors, before she went to her seat;
hwílum for duguðe dohtor Hróðgáres
from time to time before the band of experienced warriors Hrothgar's daughter
eorlum on ende ealuwaége bær
to nobles continuously to the end bore the ale-flagon,
þá ic Fréaware fletsittende
those I Freawaru the ones on the floor
nemnan hýrde þaér hío nægled sinc
I heard name her, when she the studded cup
hæleðum sealde Sío geháten is
gave to heroes, she is promised,
geong goldhroden, gladum suna Fródan·
young, gold-adorned, to gracious son of Froda;
hafað þæs geworden wine Scyldinga
this has arranged the Friend of the Scyldings,
ríces hyrde ond þæt raéd talað
the kingdom's shepherd, and counsel reckons it
þæt hé mid ðý wífe wælfaéhða daél
that he with this woman a great part of the slaughter-feuds,
sæcca gesette. Oft seldan hwaér
conflicts will settle. Very seldom anywhere
æfter léodhryre lýtle hwíle
after the fall of a leader (even) a little while
bongár búgeð þéah séo brýd duge.
the murderous spear bends down, though the bride be good.
Mæg þæs þonne ofþyncan ðéoden Heaðo-Beardna
This then may displease the chief of the Heatho-Bards'
ond þegna gehwám þára léoda
and every thane of that people,
þonne hé mid faémnan on flett gaëð:
when he with the maiden walks on the floor:
dryhtbearn Dena duguða biwenede,
that the noble sons of the Danes, her veteran troop, are entertained,
on him gladiað gomelra láfe
on them glisten ancient heirlooms,
heard ond hringmaél Heaða-Bearna gestréon
hard and ring-adorned, the Heatho-Bards' treasure,
þenden híe ðám waépnum wealdan móston.
so long as they those weapons were able to wield.