Gewiton him ðá wígend wíca néosian
The warriors returned then to seek their houses,
XVII
fréondum befeallen, Frýsland geséon,
bereft of friends, to see Frisia,
hámas ond héaburh· Hengest ðá gýt
their homes and high fort; yet Hengest
wælfágne winter wunode mid Finn
the death-stained winter spent with Finn,
eal unhlitine· eard gemunde
in a place with no fellowship at all; he remembered his land,
þéah þe ne meahte on mere drífan
though he could not drive on the sea
hringedstefnan: holm storme wéol·
the ring-prowed ship: the sea welled in storm,
won wið winde· winter ýþe beléac
fought against the wind; the winter locked the waves
ísgebinde oþ ðæt óþer cóm
in icy bonds, until came another
géar in geardas swá nú gýt déëð·
year to the courtyards, as it still does now,
þá ðe syngáles séle bewitiað
those which continuously carry out their seasons,
wuldortorhtan weder. Ðá wæs winter scacen,
gloriously bright weathers. Then winter was gone,
fæger foldan bearm· fundode wrecca
fair was the Earth's breast; the exile was anxious to go,
gist of geardum· hé tó gyrnwræce
the guest of the dwellings; he of vengeance for grief
swíðor þóhte þonne tó saéláde·
sooner thought than of sea-path,
gif hé torngemót þurhtéon mihte
and whether he a bitter encounter could bring about,
þæt hé eotena bearn inne gemunde·
for that he of the Eotens' sons inwardly remembered;
swá hé ne forwyrnde woroldraédenne
so he did not refuse the worldly practice,
þonne him Húnláfing, hildeléoman
when to him Hunlafing the battle-light,
billa sélest on bearm dyde·
the finest blade he placed on (Hnaef's) lap;
þæs waéron mid eotenum ecge cúðe.
among the Eotens its edges were known.
Swylce ferhðfrecan Fin eft begeat
So too his mortal enemy's  Finn in turn received
sweordbealo slíðen æt his selfes hám
dire sword-onslaught in his own home,
siþðan grimne gripe Gúðláf ond Ósláf
when concerning the fierce attack Guthlaf and Oslaf,
æfter saésíðe sorge maéndon·
following their sea-journey, declared their grief,
ætwiton wéana daél· ne meahte waéfre mód
blamed for their share of woes; he could not his restless spirit
forhabban in hreþre· ðá wæs heal hroden
contain in his breast; then the hall were decorated
féonda féorum· swilce Fin slægen
with the foes' lives, so too Finn was slain,
cyning on corþre ond séo cwén numen·
the king amid his troop, and the queen was seized;
scéotend Scyldinga tó scypon feredon
Scylding shooters ferried to the ships
eal ingesteald eorðcyninges·
all of the house-goods of the nation's king,
swylce híe æt Finnes hám findan meahton
which they at Finn's estate could find:
sigla searogimma· híe on saéláde
shining jewels and well-cut gems; they on the sea-path
drihtlíce wíf tó Denum feredon·
the noble lady ferried to the Danes,
laéddon tó léodum. Léoð wæs ásungen
led to the people. The lay was sung,
gléomannes gyd· gamen eft ástáh·
the gleeman's tale; joy again sprang up,
beorhtode bencswég· byrelas sealdon
music rang out from the bench, cup-bearers served
wín of wunderfatum. Þá cwóm Wealhþéo forð
wine from wondrous vessels. Then Wealhtheow came forth,
gán under gyldnum béage þaér þá gódan twégen
walking in a golden neck-ring to where the good pair
sæton suhtergefæderan þá gýt wæs hiera sib ætgædere,
sat, uncle and nephew; then their kinship was still together,
aéghwylc óðrum trýwe· swylce þaér Hunferþ þyle
each to the other true; Unferth the þyle was also there
æt fótum sæt fréan Scyldinga· gehwylc hiora his ferhþe tréowde
sitting at the feet of the Scylding lord; each of them trusted his spirit,
þæt hé hæfde mód micel þéah þe hé his mágum naére
and that he had great courage, though he to his kin was not
árfæst æt ecga gelácum· spræc ðá ides Scyldinga:
honourable in clash of blades; the Scylding lady then spoke:
'Onfóh þissum fulle, fréodrihten mín,
'Receive this full cup, my noble lord,
sinces brytta· þú on saélum wes,
dispenser of treasure; you be joyful,
goldwine gumena, ond tó Géatum spræc
gold-friend of men, and to the Geats speak
mildum wordum swá sceal man dóön·
with gentle words so ought a man to do;
béo wið Géatas glæd, geofena gemyndig
be gracious with the Geats, mindful of gifts
néan ond feorran þú nú hafast·
which from near and far you now have;
mé man sægde þæt þú ðé for sunu wolde
it has been said to me that you wish for a son,
hereric habban· Heorot is gefaélsod
to have this leader of armies; Heorot is cleansed,
béahsele beorhta· brúc þenden þú móte
the bright ring-hall; enjoy, while you may,
manigra médo ond þínum mágum laéf
many rewards, and leave to your kinsmen
folc ond ríce þonne ðú forð scyle
folk and kingdom when you must go forth
metodsceaft séön· ic mínne can
to meet what is fated; I know my
glædne Hróþulf· þæt hé þá geogoðe wile
gracious Hrothulf, that he the youths wishes
árum healdan gyf þú aér þonne hé,
to hold in honour, if you earlier than he,
wine Scildinga, worold oflaétest
friend of the Scyldings, leave behind the world,
wéne ic þæt hé mid góde gyldan wille
I think that he with good will repay
uncran eaferan gif hé þæt eal gemon·
our children, if he that at all remembers,
hwæt wit tó willan ond tó worðmyndum
what we for his sake and for his worldly renown,
umborwesendum aér árna gefremedon.'
before, in his youth, bestowed our favours.'
Hwearf þá bí bence þaér hyre byre waéron
She turned then by the bench, where her boys were,
Hréðríc ond Hróðmund ond hæleþa bearn
Hrethric and Hrothmund,
giogoð æt gædere· þaér se góda sæt
the young company all together; there sat the good
Béowulf Géata be þaém gebróðrum twaém.
Beowulf of the Geats by the two brothers.