Béowulf maþelode             bearn Ecgþéowes:
Beowulf spoke,             the son of Edgetheow:
XXI
'Ne sorga, snotor guma·             sélre bið aéghwaém
'Do not sorrow, wise man·             it is better for everyone
þæt hé his fréond wrece             þonne hé fela murne·
that he his friend avenge,             than he mourn over-much;
úre aéghwylc sceal             ende gebídan
each of us must             await the end
worolde lífes:             wyrce sé þe móte
in the world of life:             gain he who may
dómes aér déaþe·             þæt bið drihtguman,
glory before death;             that is for the warrior,
unlifgendum             æfter sélest.
unliving,             afterwards the best.
Árís, ríces weard,             uton hraþe féran
Arise, O guardian of the kingdom,             let us go quickly,
Grendles mágan             gang scéawigan·
Grendel's kin's             trail survey;
ic hit þé geháte:             nó hé on helm losaþ
I swear it to thee:             she will not be lost in the cover,
né on foldan fæþm             né on fyrgenholt
nor in the embrace of the earth,             nor in the mountain wood,
né on gyfenes grund·             gá þaér hé wille·
nor in the ocean's depth,             go where she will;
ðýs dógor þú             geþyld hafa
this day you             must have patience
wéana gehwylces             swá ic þé wéne tó.'
in each of the woes,             as I expect you to.'
Áhléop ðá se gomela,             gode þancode
The        agèd one leapt up,      thanked God,
mihtigan drihtne             þæs se man gespræc·
mighty Lord,             for what the man spoke;
þá wæs Hróðgáre             hors gebaéted
then was for Hrothgar             a horse was bridled,
wicg wundenfeax·             wísa fengel
a mount with braided mane;             the wise ruler
geatolíc gende·             gumféþa stóp
rode well-equipped;             the foot-soldiers marched
lindhæbbendra·             lástas waéron
linden-wood bearers;       tracks were
æfter waldswaþum             wíde gesýne,
along the forest-track             widely seen,
gang ofer grundas             gegnum for
the trail over the grounds,             went straight-forward
ofer myrcan mór             magoþegna bær
over the murky moor,             she carried of the kin-thanes
þone sélestan             sáwolléasne
the finest              without his soul
þára þe mid Hróðgáre               hám eahtode.
of those who with Hrothgar             had defended their home.
Oferéode þá             æþelinga bearn
Traversed then             the nobles' son
stéap stánhliðo             stíge nearwe
the steep stone slopes,             the narrow ways,
enge ánpaðas             uncúð gelád
the tight single-file paths,             the unknown, uncertain water-crossings,
neowle næssas             nicorhúsa fela·
the precipitous headlands,             the many homes of nicors;
hé féara sum             beforan gengde
he with a few             went ahead
wísra monna             wong scéawian
wise men             surveying the field,
oþ þæt hé faéringa             fyrgenbéamas
until he by chance             mountain-trees
ofer hárne stán             hleonian funde
over a silvery-grey stone             found hanging,
wynléasne wudu·             wæter under stód
the joyless forest;             water stood below,
dréorig ond gedréfed·             Denum eallum wæs
bloody and stirred-up;             for all of the Danes was,
winum Scyldinga             wærce on móde
for the friends of the        Scyldings,     suffering in the heart
tó geþolianne,             ðegne monegum
to endure,      for        many thanes,
oncýð eorla gehwaém             syðþan Æscheres
awakening grief in each of the nobles,             when Æschere's
on þám holmclife             hafelan métton.
on the sea-cliff              head encountered.
Flód blóde wéol              folc tó saégon
The flood welled bloody              the folk stared at it
hátan heolfre·             horn stundum song
with flaming gore;             rapidly the horn sang,
fúslíc forðléoð·             féþa eal gesæt·
urgent song of departure;      the troop all        sat down;
gesáwon ðá æfter wætere             wyrmcynnes fela
they saw then through the water             many of the race of serpents,
sellice saédracan             sund cunnian,
strange sea-dragon             exploring the lake,
swylce on næshleoðum             nicras licgean
also on the cape-slopes             were lounging nicors,
ðá on undernmaél             oft bewitigað
they in mid-morning             often carry out
sorhfulne síð             on seglráde,
grievous sorties             on the sail-road,
wyrmas ond wildéor·             híe on weg hruron
serpents and wild beasts;             they rushed away
bitere ond gebolgne·             bearhtm ongéaton
bitter and swollen with rage;             they perceived the clear note,
gúðhorn galan·             sumne Géata léod
war-horn wailing;             one of the Geats' men
of flánbogan             féores getwaéfde
with a shaft and bow             separated it from life,
ýðgewinnes      þæt        him on aldre stód
of wave-struggle      that        in its heart stood,
herestraél hearda·             hé on holme wæs
a strong war-arrow;             it in the water was
sundes þé saénra             ðé hyne swylt fornam·
swimming the slower,             when Death seized it;
hræþe wearð on ýðum             mid eoferspréotum
fast it was in the waves             against boar-pikes
heorohócyhtum             hearde genearwod,
savagely-hooked             hard pressed,
níða genaéged             ond on næs togen
viciously attacked,             and from the cape dragged out,
wundorlíc waégbora·             weras scéawedon
wondrous spawn of the waves;             men stared at
gryrelícne gist.             Gyrede hine Béowulf
the gruesome guest.             Beowulf armed himself
eorlgewaédum·             nalles for ealdre mearn·
in noble garments,             feared not at all for his life;
scolde herebyrne             hondum gebróden
it was necessary that his army-byrnie,             braided by hands,
síd ond searofáh             sund cunnian
broad and cunningly adorned,             explore the lake,
séo ðe báncofan             beorgan cúþe
it the bone-chamber      could        protect,
þæt him hildegráp             hreþre ne mihte
that him the battle-grip             could not his heart,
eorres inwitfeng             aldre gesceþðan
nor angry grasp of malice             his life scathe,
ac se hwíta helm             hafelan werede
moreover the shining helm             warded his head,
sé þe meregrundas             mengan scolde,
that which the mere-depths             must stir up,
sécan sundgebland             since geweorðad
seek the mingling of waters             adorned with riches,
befongen fréawrásnum             swá hine fyrndagum
encircled with lordly-bands             as in far-days it
worhte waépna smið             wundrum téode·
was wrought by weapons' smith,             wonderfully lengthened,
besette swínlícum             þæt hine syðþan nó
beset with swine-forms,             so that it then no
brond né beadomécas             bítan ne meahton.
brond-blade nor battle-maiches      to bite were not able.
Næs þæt þonne maétost             mægenfultuma
Not the least then of             his mighty supports,
þæt him on ðearfe láh             ðyle Hróðgáres
that him in need lent             Hrothgar's þyle
wæs þaém hæftméce             Hrunting nama
was the long-hilted maiche-sword's             name Hrunting
þæt wæs án foran             ealdgestréona·
it was one above             of ancient treasures;
ecg wæs íren             átertánum fáh
edge was iron,             with poison-twigs patterned,
áhyrded heaþoswáte·             naéfre hit æt hilde ne swác
hardened with battle-blood;             never had it in a fight failed
manna aéngum             þára þe hit mid mundum bewand
any man,      who        it in hands brandished,
sé ðe gryresíðas             gegán dorste
he who terrifying journeys             dared to enter upon,
folcstede fára·             næs þæt forma síð
the domain of foes;             it was not the first time
þæt hit ellenweorc             æfnan scolde.
that it courage-work             had been obliged to perform.
Húru ne gemunde             mago Ecgláfes
Indeed he could not have recalled,             the kin of Ecgelaf,
eafoþes cræftig             þæt hé aér gespræc
mighty in strength,             that which he had said before,
wíne druncen             þá hé þæs waépnes onláh
drunk on wine,             when he lent that the weapon
sélran sweordfrecan             selfa ne dorste
to a better swordsman,             he himself did not dare
under ýða gewin             aldre genéþan,
under the waves' turmoil             to risk his life,
drihtscype dréogan·             þaér hé dóme forléas
to carry out bravery;             there he forfeited glory,
ellenmaérðum·             ne wæs þaém óðrum swá
fame from valour;             it was not so for the        other,
syðþan hé hine tó gúðe             gegyred hæfde.
when he himself for war             had equipped.