Ðá wæs háten hreþe Heort innanweard
Then the order was promptly given the interior of Heorot
XV
folmum gefrætwod· fela þaéra wæs
to furnish by hands; many there were,
wera ond wífa þe þæt wínreced
of men and women, who the wine-hall,
gestsele gyredon· goldfág scinon
the guest-hall prepared; gold-glittering shone
web æfter wágum wundorsíona fela
woven tapestries along the walls, many wondrous sights
secga gehwylcum þára þe on swylc starað·
for each of the men, who on such stared;
wæs þæt beorhte bold tóbrocen swíðe
that bright building was badly broken up
eal inneweard írenbendum fæst,
all inside secure with iron-bands,
heorras tóhlidene· hróf ána genæs
hinges sprung open; the roof alone remained
ealles ansund þé se áglaéca
entirely sound, when the ogre,
fyrendaédum fág on fléam gewand
guilty of wicked deeds turned in flight,
aldres orwéna. Nó þæt ýðe byð
despairing of life. That is not easy
to befléönne  fremme sé þe wille
to flee from  try he who will
ac gesacan sceal sáwlberendra
but he must gain by strife, those who have souls,
nýde genýdde, niþða bearna
compelled by necessity, the mens' sons',
grundbúendra gearwe stówe
the ground-dwellers' ready place,
þaér his líchoma legerbedde fæst
there his body, fast in his death-bed,
swefeþ æfter symle. Þá wæs saél ond maél
sleeps after feasting. Then it was the time and occasion
þæt tó healle gang Healfdenes sunu·
that to the hall went Half-Dane's son;
wolde self cyning symbel þicgan·
the king himself wished to partake of the feast;
ne gefrægen ic þá maégþe máran weorode
I have not heard when a tribe in a greater force
ymb hyra sincgyfan sél gebaéran·
around their treasure-giver comported themselves better;
bugon þá tó bence blaédágande
they then sank down on the bench, the fame-bearers,
fylle gefaégon· fægere geþaégon
rejoicing at the feast; they graciously received
medoful manig mágas þára
many full goblets of mead, their kinsmen,
swíðhicgende on sele þám héan
stout-hearted, in the high hall
Hróðgár ond Hróþulf· Heorot innan wæs
Hrothgar and Hrothulf· the interior of Heorot was
fréondum áfylled· nalles fácenstafas
filled with friends; no treacherous-strokes
Þéod-Scyldingas þenden fremedon.
the Folk-Scyldings made as yet.
Forgeaf þá Béowulfe brand Healfdenes
Then Beowulf was given the brand of Half-Dane,
segen gyldenne sigores tó léane
the golden banner in reward of victory,
hroden hiltecumbor, helm ond byrnan·
the adorned standard, helm and byrnie;
maére máðþumsweord manige gesáwon
the renowned treasure-sword many saw
beforan beorn beran· Béowulf geþah
brought before the hero; Beowulf took
ful on flette· nó hé þaére feohgyfte
the full flagon from the floor; of the reward-gift he did not,
for scótenum scamigan ðorfte·
as payment, need to be ashamed;
ne gefrægn ic fréondlícor féower mádmas
I have not heard that more graciously four treasures,
golde gegyrede gummanna fela
adorned with gold, many men
in ealobence óðrum gesellan·
on ale-bench have given to others;
ymb þæs helmes hróf héafodbeorge
around the helmet's roof  the head-guard
wírum bewunden walan útan héold
was wound with wires the re-inforced crest guarded from without,
þæt him féla láf frécne ne meahton
that him what the files have left could not savagely,
scúrheard sceþðan þonne scyldfreca
(could not) harm the wondrously-tempered (helm), when the shield-fighter
ongéan gramum gangan scolde.
against enemies had to go.
Heht ðá eorla hléo eahta méaras
The defender of earls then ordered eight horses,
faétedhléore on flet téön
with decorated head-gear, led onto the hall-floor
in under eoderas· þára ánum stód
in under the ramparts; one of them stood,
sadol searwum fáh since gewurþad·
saddle skilfully adorned, ennobled with jewels;
þæt wæs hildesetl héahcyninges
that was the battle-seat of the high king,
ðonne sweorda gelác sunu Healfdenes
when in sword-play the son of Half-Dane
efnan wolde· naéfre on óre læg
wished to engage; in the vanguard it never failed
wídcúþes wíg ðonne walu féollon·
his warskill well-known, when the slain were falling;
ond ðá Béowulfe béga gehwæþres
and then to Beowulf both of the treasures
eodor Ingwina onweald getéah
the protector of the Friends of Ing bestowed possession,
wicga ond waépna· hét hine wél brúcan·
horses and weapons; he ordered him to make good use of (them);
swá manlíce maére þéoden
so in a manly manner the famed chieftain,
hordweard hæleþa heaþoraésas geald
the hoard-ward of heroes, paid for war-clashes
méarum ond mádmum swá hý naéfre man lyhð
in horses and treasures; thus, one can never find fault in them
sé þe secgan wile sóð æfter rihte.
he who wishes to tell the truth according to what is right.