Béowulf        maþelode    bearn Ecgþéowes:
Beowulf        spoke,    the son of Edgetheow:
XXV
'Hwæt, wé þé þás        saélác,    sunu Healfdenes
'Listen, we you these        sea-spoils,    son of Half-Dane,
léod        Scyldinga,    lustum bróhton
lord of the        Scyldings,    gladly brought
tíres tó        tácne    þé þú hér tó lócast.
as token of        glory,    which you look at here.
Ic þæt        unsófte    ealdre gedígde
I it not        easily    survived with my life,
wigge under        wætere·    weorc genéþde
war under        water,    work risked
earfoðlíce·     ætrihte wæs
with trouble;    at        once was
gúð        getwaéfed    nymðe mec god scylde·
the warfare at an        end,    unless God shielded me;
ne meahte ic æt        hilde    mid Hruntinge
I could not in the        battle    with Hrunting
wiht        gewyrcan    þéah þæt waépen duge
bring about        anything,    though that weapon is excellent
ac mé geúðe    ylda        waldend
but to me        granted    men's Ruler
þæt ic on wáge        geseah    wlitig hangian
that I saw on the        wall    hanging fair
ealdsweord        éacen     oftost wísode
a mighty ancient        sword     most often He has guided
winigea        léasum     þæt ic ðý waépne gebraéd·
the one deprived of        friend     that I the weapon drew,
ofslóh ðá æt þaére        sæcce     þá mé saél ageald
slew then in the        strife,    when an opportunity was yielded to        me,
húses        hyrdas·    þá þæt hildebil
the house's        guardians;    then that battle-bill
forbarn        brogdenmaél    swá þæt blód gesprang
burned up, wavy-patterned,     as the blood        leapt out,
hátost        heaþoswáta·    ic þæt hilt þanan
the hottest sweat of        war;    I that hilt thence
féondum        ætferede·    fyrendaéda wræc
carried back from the        fiends,    foul-deeds avenged,
déaðcwealm        Denigea    swá hit gedéfe wæs.
deadly slaughter of        Danes,    as it was fitting.
Ic hit þé þonne        geháte    þæt þú on Heorote móst
I promise it to you        then,    that you in Heorot may
sorhléas        swefan    mid þínra secga gedryht
sleep without        sorrow    with your company of soldiers,
ond þegna        gehwylc    þínra léoda
and each        thane    of your nation,
duguðe ond iogoþe·             þæt þú him ondraédan ne þearft,
veterans and        youths,    that you for them need not dread,
þéoden        Scyldinga,    on þá healfe
chieftain of the        Scyldings,    on that side,
aldorbealu        eorlum    swá þú aér dydest.'
life-bale for        earls,    as you did before.'
Ðá wæs        gyldenhilt    gamelum rince
Then was the golden        hilt    to the old king
hárum        hildfruman    on hand gyfen
to the grey        battle-leader,    given into his hand,
enta        aérgeweorc·    hit on aéht gehwearf
the ancient work of        giants;    it had passed into the possession
æfter déofla        hryre    Denigea fréän
after the devils'        fall    of the lord of the Danes,
wundorsmiþa        geweorc    ond þá þás worold ofgeaf
the work of        wondersmiths,    and then this world gave up
gromheort        guma    godes andsaca
the angry-hearted        creature,    God's adversary
morðres        scyldig    ond his módor éac
guilty of        murder,    and his mother also;
on geweald        gehwearf    woroldcyninga
it passed into the        power    of the earthly kings
ðaém sélestan              be saém twéonum
the finest        ones    between the two seas,
ðára þe on        Scedenigge    sceattas daélde.
of those who in Scandinavia     dealt out        riches.
Hróðgár        maðelode·    hylt scéawode
Hrothgor spoke;    he              examined the hilt,
ealde        lafe·    on ðaém wæs ór writen
the old        heirloom,    on which was engraved the origin
fyrngewinnes    syðþan flód ofslóh
of ancient        strife,    when the flood slew
gifen        géotende    gíganta cyn
the pouring        ocean,    the race of giants
frécne        geférdon·    þæt wæs fremde þéod
they fared        terribly;    that was a tribe foreign
écean        dryhtne·    him þæs endeléan
to the eternal        Lord;    them the end-reward
þurh wæteres        wylm    waldend sealde
through the surging of        waters    the Ruler granted
swá wæs on ðaém        scennum    scíran goldes
also was on the sword-hilt    of shining gold
þurh        rúnstafas    rihte gemearcod
in        rune-staves    rightly marked,
geseted ond        gesaéd    hwám þæt sweord geworht
it was set down and        said,    for        whom the sword wrought,
írena        cyst    aérest waére
choicest of irons             had been first,
wreoþenhilt ond        wyrmfáh·    ðá se wísa spræc
with a twisted-hilt and        serpent-patterned;    then the wise man        spoke,
sunu Healfdenes            swígedon ealle:
the son of Half-Dane            all fell silent:
'Þæt, lá, mæg        secgan     sé þe sóð ond riht
'That, indeed, may        say    he who truth and right
fremeð on        folce·    feor eal gemon,
performs among the        folk,    remembers all from far-back,
eald éðel        weard·    þæt ðes eorl waére
old warden of the        homeland;    that this hero was
geboren        betera·    blaéd is áraéred
born a greater        man;    the fame is established
geond        wídwegas,    wine mín Béowulf,
throughout the distant        regions,    Beowulf my friend,
ðín ofer þéoda        gehwylce·    eal þú hit geþyldum healdest,
over each of the nations, of        you;    all you it with patience hold,
mægen mid módes snyttrum·      ic þé sceal míne gelaéstan
strength with the wisdom of the heart;    to you I shall continue to give my
fréoðe swá wit furðum spraécon·    ðú scealt tó frófre weorþan
protection, as we spoke of before;    you must be as a comfort
eal        langtwídig    léodum þínum
all        long-lasting    to your people,
hæleðum tó        helpe.    Ne wearð Heremód swá
to heroes a        support.    Heremod was not so
eaforum        Ecgwelan    Ár-Scyldingum·
to the sons of Edgewela,    to the        Honour-Scyldings;
ne gewéox hé him tó        willan    ac tó wælfealle
he grew not to their        pleasure,    but for slaughter
ond tó        déaðcwalum    Deniga léodum·
and for        annihilation    of the people of the Danes;
bréat        bolgenmód    béodgenéatas
he felled in a furious        spirit    his companions at table,
eaxlgesteallan    oþ þæt hé ána hwearf
shoulder-comrades,    until he alone        passed,
maére        þéoden    mondréamum from
famous        king,    from the joys of man
ðéah þe hine mihtig        god    mægenes wynnum
though him mighty        God    with joys of strength
eafeþum        stépte    ofer ealle men
powerfully        exalted    over all men,
forð        gefremede    hwæþere him on ferhþe gréow
further        advanced    yet in his heart grew to him
bréosthord        blódréow·    nallas béagas geaf
the treasure of the breast eager for blood;     not at all did he give rings
Denum æfter        dóme·    dréamléas gebád
to Danes for        glory;    he lived joylessly,
þæt hé þæs        gewinnes    wærc þrówade
so that he the        strife's    pain suffered,
léodbealo        longsum.    Ðú þé laér be þon·
a great evil to the people for a long        time.    You learn by this,
gumcyste        ongit·    ic þis gid be þé
understand human        virtue;    I this tale for you
áwræc wintrum        fród.    Wundor is tó secganne
recited, old and wise in        winters.    Wonder is to say
hú mihtig        god    manna cynne
how mighty God    to        mankind
þurh sídne        sefan    snyttru bryttað
according to deep understanding            dispenses wisdom,
eard ond        eorlscipe·    hé áh ealra        geweald·
land and noble        qualities;    he has control of all;
hwílum hé on        lufan    laéteð hworfan
at times He in        delight    lets go
monnes        módgeþonc    maéran cynnes
the heart's thought of some        man    of glorious kin
seleð him on        éþle    eorþan wynne
gives to him in his own        homeland    earthly bliss
tó        healdanne    hléoburh wera·
to command    a        stronghold of men,
gedéð him swá gewealdene            worolde daélas
makes subject to        him    from the world's portions,
síde ríce    þæt hé        his selfa ne mæg
a wide        kingdom,    that he himself can not
for his        unsnyttrum    ende geþencean·
in his        ignorance    conceive the end (of his rule);
wunað hé on        wiste·    nó hine wiht dweleð
he lives on in        abundance;    they hinder him not a bit,
ádl né yldo    né        him inwitsorh
sickness nor        age,    nor him evil sorrow
on sefan        sweorceð    né gesacu óhwaér
darkens in his        soul,    nor strife anywhere
ecghete éoweð    ac        him eal worold
sharp-hate        appears,    but to him all the world
wendeð on        willan·    hé þæt wyrse ne con.
turns on his        pleasure;    he does not know it worse.