Hwæt! Wé Gárdena in géardagum
(nor) heroes under heaven, who received that cargo.
Prologue
þéodcyninga þrym gefrúnon·
of those clan-kings  heard of their glory.
hú ðá æþelingas ellen fremedon.
how those nobles performed courageous deeds.
Oft Scyld Scéfing sceaþena þréatum
Often Scyld, Scef's son, from enemy hosts
monegum maégþum meodosetla oftéah·
from many peoples seized mead-benches;
egsode Eorle syððan aérest wearð
and terrorised the fearsome Heruli after first he was
féasceaft funden hé þæs frófre gebád·
found helpless and destitute, he then knew recompense for that:-
wéox under wolcnum· weorðmyndum þáh
he waxed under the clouds, throve in honours,
oð þæt him aéghwylc þára ymbsittendra
until to him each of the bordering tribes
ofer hronráde hýran scolde,
beyond the whale-road had to submit,
gomban gyldan· þæt wæs gód cyning.
and yield tribute:- that was a good king!
Ðaém eafera wæs æfter cenned
To him an heir was born then
geong in geardum þone god sende
young in the yards, God sent him
folce tó frófre· fyrenðearfe ongeat·
to comfort the people; He had seen the dire distress
þæt híe aér drugon aldorléase
that they suffered before, leader-less
lange hwíle· him þæs líffréä
a long while; them for that the Life-Lord,
wuldres wealdend woroldáre forgeaf:
Ruler of Glory, granted honour on earth:
Béowulf wæs bréme  blaéd wíde sprang
Beowulf (Beaw) was famed  his renown spread wide
Scyldes eafera Scedelandum in.
Scyld's heir, in Northern lands.
Swá sceal geong guma góde gewyrcean
So ought a young man by good deeds deserve,
fromum feohgiftum on fæder bearme
(and) by fine treasure-gifts, while in his father's keeping,
þæt hine on ylde eft gewunigen
that him in old age shall again stand by,
wilgesíþas þonne wíg cume·
willing companions, when war comes,
léode gelaésten: lofdaédum sceal
people serve him: by glorious deeds must,
in maégþa gehwaére man geþéön.
amongst his people, everywhere, one prosper.
Him ðá Scyld gewát tó gescæphwíle
Then Scyld departed at the destined time,
felahrór féran on fréan waére·
still in his full-strength, to fare in the protection of the Lord Frea;
hí hyne þá ætbaéron tó brimes faroðe
he they carried to the sea's surf,
swaése gesíþas swá hé selfa bæd
his dear comrades, as he himself had bid,
þenden wordum wéold wine Scyldinga
when he yet wielded words, that friend of the Scyldings,
léof landfruma lange áhte·
beloved ruler of the land, had ruled for a long time;
þaér æt hýðe stód hringedstefna
there at the harbour stood with a ringed-prow,
ísig ond útfús æþelinges fær·
icy and keen to sail, a hero's vessel;
álédon þá léofne þéoden
they then laid down the beloved prince,
béaga bryttan on bearm scipes
the giver of rings and treasure, in the bosom of the boat,
maérne be mæste· þaér wæs mádma fela
the mighty by the mast; many riches were there,
of feorwegum frætwa gelaéded·
from far-off lands ornate armour and baubles were brought;
ne hýrde ic cýmlícor céol gegyrwan
I have not heard of a comelier keel adorned
hildewaépnum ond heaðowaédum
with weapons of battle and war-dress,
billum ond byrnum· him on bearme læg
bill-blades and byrnies; there lay on his breast
mádma mænigo þá him mid scoldon
many treasures, which with him must,
on flódes aéht feor gewítan·
in the power of the waves, drift far off;
nalæs hí hine laéssan lácum téodan
in no way had they upon him fewer gifts bestowed
þéodgestréonum þonne þá dydon
with the wealth of a nation, than those did
þe hine æt frumsceafte forð onsendon
who him in the beginning had sent forth
aénne ofer ýðe umborwesende·
alone upon the waves being but a child;
þá gýt híe him ásetton segen gyldenne
yet then they set up the standard of gold,
héah ofer héafod· léton holm beran·
high over head; they let the sea bear,
géafon on gársecg· him wæs geómor sefa
gave to the ocean, in them were troubled hearts,
murnende mód· men ne cunnon
mourning minds; men cannot
secgan tó sóðe seleraédenne
say for certain, (neither) court-counsellors
hæleð under heofenum hwá þaém hlæste onféng.
(nor) heroes under heaven, who received that cargo.