Swá se        ðéodkyning    þéawum lyfde·
So the king of the        people    lived according to proper custom;
XXXI
nealles ic ðám        léanum    forloren hæfde
I by no means the        gifts     had lost,
mægnes méde    ac        hé mé maðma geaf
strength's        reward,     but he gave me treasures,
sunu        Healfdenes    on mínne sylfes dóm
the son of        Half-Dane,    according to my own glory,
ðá ic ðé,        beorncyning,    bringan wylle,
these I to thee,        warrior-king,    wish to bring,
éstum        geýwan·    gén is eall æt ðé
graciously to        offer;    still is all in thee
lissa        gelong·    ic lýt hafo
dependent upon your        favour;    I have few
héafodmága            nefne, Hygelác, ðec.'
near        kinsmen    except you Hygelac.'
Hét ðá in        beran    eafor héafodsegn
Then he commanded to be brought        in    the boar-crested standard,
heaðostéapne        helm    háre byrnan
the battle-steep        helm,    hoar-silver byrnie,
gúðsweord        geatolíc·    gyd æfter wræc:
the beautiful        war-sword;    the tale thereafter uttered:
'Mé ðis        hildesceorp     Hróðgár sealde
'To me this        battle-equipment    Hrothgar gave,
snotra        fengel·    sume worde hét
the clever        ruler;    with some words he ordered,
þæt ic his aérest        ðé     ést gesægde·
that I first you        its    legacy relate;
cwæð þæt hyt        hæfde     Hiorogár cyning
he said it        owned    King Heorogar,
léod        Scyldunga    lange hwíle·
the leader of the        Scyldings    a long time;
nó ðý aér suna        sínum    syllan wolde
no sooner for that to his        son    did he wish to give,
hwatum        Heorowearde    þéah hé him hold waére
to bold Heoroweard,    though he was loyal to him,
bréostgewaédu.     Brúc ealles        well.'
the        breast-armour.    Use it all        well.'
Hýrde ic þæt þám        frætwum    féower méaras
I heard that with the        treasure    four mares
lungre        gelíce    lást weardode
swift, all        alike,    followed behind,
æppelfealuwe·    hé him ést        getéah
apple-yellow;            he to him offered the gifts,
méara ond        máðma.    Swá sceal maég dön:
horses and        riches.    So should a kinsman act:
nealles        inwitnet    óðrum bregdon
not at all        malice-nets    weave for others,
dyrnum        cræfte    déað rénian
with hidden        arts    contrive death
hondgesteallan.     Hygeláce        wæs
of hand-companions.    To Hygelac        was
níða        heardum    nefa swýðe hold
in fierce        strife    his        nephew very loyal,
ond gehwæðer        óðrum    hróþra gemyndig·
and each the        other's    benefit remembered;
hýrde ic þæt hé ðone        healsbéah    Hygde gesealde
I heard that he the        neck-ring    gave to Hygd,
wraétlicne        wundurmáððum    ðone þe him Wealhðéo        geaf
the exquisite        marvel-jewel,    which Wealhtheow gave him,
ðéodnes        dohtor    þrío wicg somod
chieftain's        daughter,
swancor ond        sadolbeorht·    hyre syððan wæs
supple and bright with        saddles;    then was her,
æfter        béahðege    bréost geweorðod.
after receiving the        ring,    breast adorned.
Swá        bealdode    bearn Ecgðéowes
Thus he was        bold,    the son of Edgetheow,
guma gúðum        cúð    gódum daédum·
man famed in        war,    for good deeds;
dréah æfter        dóme·    nealles druncne slóg
he led his life for        glory,    never, having drunk, slew
heorðgenéatas·     næs him hréoh        sefa
his        hearth-companions;    a troubled heart was not in        him,
ac hé        mancynnes    maéste cræfte
but he        mankind's    greatest strength,
ginfæstan        gife    þé him god sealde
that ample        gift,    which God gave him
héold        hildedéor.    Héan wæs lange
he held,        battle-daring.    Long had he been        abject
swá hyne Géata        bearn    gódne ne tealdon
so the sons of the        Geats    did not reckon him good,
né hyne on        medobence    micles wyrðne
nor to him on the        mead-bench    much honour
drihten        wereda    gedón wolde·
the commander of the        troops    would grant;
swýðe sægdon    þæt        hé sléac waére
they especially        said,    that he was slack,
æðeling        unfrom·    edwenden cwóm
no bold noble;    a        turn-around came
tíréadigum        menn    torna gehwylces.
to the glory-blessed        man    for each of these miseries.
Hét ðá eorla        hléo    in gefetian,
Then the protector of heroes        ordered    to be fetched in,
heaðoróf        cyning,    Hréðles láfe
the war-noble        king,    Hrethel's heirloom,
golde        gegyrede·    næs mid Géatum ðá
fitted out in        gold;    there was not among the Geats then
sincmáðþum        sélra    on sweordes hád·
a better precious        treasure    in the manner of a sword;
þæt hé on        Bíowulfes    bearm álegde
that he in        Beowulf's    lap layed,
ond him        gesealde    seofan þúsendo,
and gave him    seven thousand hides of land,
bold ond        bregostól.    Him wæs bám samod
residence and ruler's seat.    Theirs was both together
on ðám        léodscipe    lond gecynde
in that        nation    inherited land,
eard        éðelriht,    óðrum swíðor
earth by ancestral        privelege,    to the second more
síde ríce    þám        ðaér sélra wæs.
of that broad        kingdom    to him who was higher.
Eft þæt        geíode    ufaran dógrum
After that it came to        pass    in later days
hildehlæmmum·     syððan Hygelác        læg
in        battle-clashes,    when Hygelac lay dead,
ond        Heardréde    hildeméceas
and for Heardred     battle-maiches,
under        bordhréoðan    tó bonan wurdon
under the cover of his        shield,    became the instruments of his death,
ðá hyne        gesóhtan    on sigeþéode
when they sought him        out    in the victory-tribe,
hearde        hildefrecan    Heaðo-Scilfingas·
the fierce battle-ready        warriors,    the Battle-Scilfings,
níða        genaégdan    nefan Hereríces·
with enmity they        attacked    the nephew of Hereric;
syððan        Béowulfe    braéde ríce
thereupon to        Beowulf    the broad kingdom
on hand        gehwearf·    hé gehéold tela
passed into his        hands;    he ruled well
fiftig        wintra     wæs ðá fród cyning
for fifty        winters     then he was a wise king,
eald        éþelweard     oð ðæt ón ongan
an old warden of the        fatherland     until one began
deorcum        nihtum    draca rícsian
in the dark        nights,    a        dragon to rule,
sé ðe on héaum        hofe    hord beweotode
he        who in a high house    watched over a        hoard,
stánbeorh        stéarcne·    stíg under læg
a stark stone        barrow;    the path below lay
eldum        uncúð.    Þaér on innan gíong
unknown to        men.    There went inside
niða        náthwylc    ond néah geféng
a man, I know not        which,    and he groped near
haéðnum        horde·    hond gewríþenne
the heathen        hoard,    his hands wrapped round
since fáhne    hé        þæt syððan beget
an ornamented        bauble,    he got that afterwards;
þéah ðe hé        slaépende     besyred hæfde
though he who sleeping    had been        tricked
þéofes        cræfte·    þæt síe ðíod onfand
by thief's        cunning;    the people discovered that,
búfolc        beorna    þæt hé gebolgen wæs.
the neighbouring folk of        men,    that he was enraged.