Hróðgár maþelode helm Scyldinga:
Hrothgar spoke, the helm of the Scyldings:
VII
'Fére fyhtum, þú, wine mín Béowulf,
'Fit to fight, you, my friend Beowulf,
ond for árstafum úsic sóhtest.
and for honour us have sought.
Geslóh þín fæder faéhðe maéste:
Your father by striking began the greatest feud:
wearþ hé Heaþoláfe tó handbonan
he was Heatholaf's slayer by his own hand
mid Wilfingum· ðá hine gára cyn
of the Wylfings; then him his spear-kin
for herebrógan habban ne mihte·
for dread of troops could not shelter;
þanon hé gesóhte Súð-Dena folc
thence he sought the South-Danes' folk
ofer ýða gewealc, Ár-Scyldinga·
over the welling of the waves, the Honour-Scyldings;
ðá ic furþum wéold folce Deninga
at that time I had just begun to rule the Danish folk
ond on geogoðe héold gimmeríce
and in my youth held the precious kingdom,
hordburh hæleþa· ðá wæs Heregár déad
the treasure-keep of heroes; then was Heregar dead,
mín yldra maég unlifigende
my elder brother unliving,
bearn Healfdenes· sé wæs betera ðonne ic.
the son of Half-Dane; he was better than I.
Siððan þá faéhðe féo þingode·
Then the feud I settled with fees;
sende ic Wylfingum ofer wæteres hrycg
I sent the Wylfings across the water's ridge
ealde mádmas· hé mé áþas swór.
ancient treasures; he swore oaths to me.
Sorh is mé tó secganne on sefan mínum
It sorrows me to say in my heart
gumena aéngum hwæt mé Grendel hafað
to any man Grendel has caused me what
hýnðo on Heorote mid his heteþancum
humiliations in Heorot with his thoughts of hatred,
faérníða gefremed· is mín fletwerod
carried out lightning-quick attacks; my hall-troop is
wíghéap gewanod· híe wyrd forswéop
waned, that war-band; they have been swept aside by Fate
on Grendles gryre· god éaþe mæg
in Grendel's horrid violence; God can easily
þone dolsceaðan daéda getwaéfan.
the rash ravager's deeds put an end to.
Ful oft gebéotedon béore druncne
Full oft have vowed, having drunk beer,
ofer ealowaége óretmecgas
over ale-flagons, battle-men,
þæt híe in béorsele bídan woldon
that they in the beer-hall would await
Grendles gúþe mid gryrum ecga.
Grendel's onslaught with vicious edges.
Ðonne wæs þéos medoheal on morgentíd
Then, this mead-hall was in the morning
drihtsele dréorfáh þonne dæg lixte,
this noble hall stained with gore when the day lightened,
eal bencþelu blóde bestýmed
all of the benches smeared with blood
heall heoru-dréore· áhte ic holdra þý laés,
the hall battle-gory; I had friends the fewer,
déorre duguðe þé þá déað fornam.
cherished old battle-retinue, for these Death took them away.
Site nú tó symle ond onsaél meoto
Sit now to feast and untie your thoughts
sigehréð secgum swá þín sefa hwette.'
of your glorious victories to the soldiers, as your heart urges.'
Þá wæs Géatmæcgum geador ætsomne
Then the Geatish men were gathered together
on béorsele benc gerýmed
in the beer-hall, room was made on a bench,
þaér swíðferhþe sittan éodon
there the strong-souled went to sit down,
þrýðum dealle þegn nytte behéold
proud in prowess a thane performed his office,
sé þe on handa bær hroden ealowaége
he who in his hands bore an ornate ale-cup,
scencte scír wered· scop hwílum sang
decanted pure sweet mead; a bard sang from time to time
hádor on Heorote· þaér wæs hæleða dréam,
clear in Heorot; there was joy of heroes,
duguð unlýtel Dena ond Wedera.
no small host of Danes and Wederas.