Cwóm þá tó flóde fela módigra
They came than to the flood full of spirit
XXVIII
hægstealdra· hringnet baéron
of the young warriors; ring-mail they wore
locene leoðosyrcan· landweard onfand
interlocked limb-shirts; the land-guard perceived
eftsíð eorla, swá hé aér dyde·
the return of heroes, as he did before;
nó hé mid hearme of hliðes nósan
he did not with insult from the cliff's promontory
gæstas grétte ac him tógéanes rád·
greet the guests, but rode towards them,
cwæð þæt wilcuman Wedera léodum
said that welcome to the people of the Wederas
scaþan scírhame tó scipe fóron·
the fighters with bright covering he went to the ship;
þá wæs on sande saégéap naca
then was on sand the sea-curved boat
hladen herewaédum hringedstefna
laden with war-garments the ringed-prow
méarum ond máðmum· mæst hlífade
with horses and treasure; the mast towered
ofer Hróðgáres hordgestréonum·
over Hrothgar's hoard-wealth;
hé þaém bátwearde bunden golde
he to the boat-guard a bound gold
swurd gesealde þæt hé syðþan wæs
sword gave, so that he afterwards was
on meodubence máþma þý weorþre
on the mead-bench by the treasure the worthier,
yrfeláfe. Gewát him on nacan
by the inherited relic. Departed him on the ship
dréfan déop wæter· Dena land ofgeaf·
to trouble deep water; he left the Danes' land;
þá wæs be mæste merehrægla sum
then was by the mast a mighty sea-garment,
segl sále fæst· sundwudu þunede·
sail fastened by rope; the sea-beam thundered;
nó þaér wégflotan wind ofer ýðum
there the wave-floater was not (by) wind over the waves
síðes getwaéfde· saégenga fór·
hindered in its venture; the sea-goers went,
fléat fámigheals forð ofer ýðe
the foamy-necked floated forth over the waves,
bundenstefna ofer brimstréamas
bound prow over the ocean-streams,
þæt híe Géata clifu ongitan meahton
until they the Geatish cliffs could perceive,
cúþe næssas· céol úp geþrang
the well-known headlands; the keel rushed up
lyftgeswenced· on lande stód.
weather-beaten, rested on the land.
Hraþe wæs æt holme hýðweard geara
Quickly was at the water the ready harbour-guard,
sé þe aér lange tíd léofra manna
he who already for a long time for the beloved men
fús æt faroðe feor wlátode·
eager at the current gazed far;
saélde tó sande sídfæþme scip
moored in the sand the broad-bosomed ship
oncearbendum fæst þý laés hym ýþa ðrym
firm with anchor-bounds, lest the force of the waves
wudu wynsuman forwrecan meahte·
the winsome timbers might carry away;
hét þá úp beran æþelinga gestréon
he ordered then to carry up the nobles' treasure,
frætwe ond faétgold· næs him feor þanon
trappings and gold ornaments; it was not far thence for them
tó gesécanne sinces bryttan
to seek the giver of treasures
Higelác Hréþling þaér æt hám wunað
Hygelac son of Hrethel, where he dwelt at home
selfa mid gesíðum saéwealle néah.
himself with his companions near the sea-wall.
Bold wæs betlíc, bregoróf cyning
The building was splendid, the king of princely valour,
héähealle, Hygd swíðe geong
the high hall, Hygd very young,
wís wélþungen þéah ðe wintra lýt
wise, well-thriving, through few winters
under burhlocan gebiden hæbbe
in the walled town had lived,
Hæreþes dohtor næs hío hnáh swá þéah
Haereth's daughter was not mean though
né tó gnéað gifa Géata léodum
nor too grudging of gifts to the people of the Geats,
máþmgestréona. Mód þrýðo wæg
of treasure-wealth. She showed violent arrogance,
fremu folces cwén, firen' ondrysne·
the lusty queen of the folk, terrible crimes;
naénig þæt dorste déor genéþan
dared not any of the bold to risk,
swaésra gesíða, nefne sinfréä·
of the dear companions, except her great lord,
þæt hire an dæges éagum starede
that on her by day stared with his eyes
ac him wælbende weotode tealde
but for him slaughter-bonds he might consider prescribed,
handgewriþene· hraþe seoþðan wæs
woven by hands; quickly then was
æfter mundgripe méce geþinged
after seizure a maiche was appointed,
þæt hit sceádenmaél scýran móste,
that it, shadow-marked, was obliged to settle,
cwealmbealu cýðan· ne bið swylc cwénlic þéaw
make known the evil of the death; such queenly manner is not
idese tó efnanne þéah ðe hío aénlicu sý·
for a lady to perform, though she be matchless,
þætte freoðuwebbe féores onsaéce
that peace-weaver deprives life,
æfter ligetorne léofne mannan.
owing to a false injury, of beloved man.
Húru þæt on hóh snod Hemninges maég·
However, it was cut off at the heel by Hemming's kinsman;
ealodrincende óðer saédan·
the ale-drinkers further told
þæt hío léodbealewa laés gefremede
that evil for the people she practised less,
inwitníða syððan aérest wearð
malice and enmity, since she first was
gyfen goldhroden geongum cempan
given, gold-adorned, to the young champion,
æðelum díore syððan hío Offan flet
of noble ancestry, when she to Offa's hall
ofer fealone flód be fæder láre
over the dusky flood by her father's wisdom
síðe gesóhte ðaér hío syððan well
sought in her journey where she afterwards fully
in gumstóle góde maére
on the throne, for goodness famed,
lífgesceafta lifigende bréac·
the fated span of her life her living she used well,
híold héahlufan wið hæleþa brego,
held high-love for the heroes' lord,
ealles moncynnes míne gefraége
of all mankind, I have heard,
þæs sélestan bí saém twéonum
the finest between the seas,
eormencynnes· Forðám Offa wæs
of the mighty race. Because Offa was
geofum ond gúðum gárcéne man
in gifts and in war, a spear-keen man;
wíde geweorðod· wísdóme héold
widely honoured, ruled in wisdom
éðel sínne· þonon ongéomor wóc
his homeland; then, exceedingly sad, he arose
hæleðum tó helpe Heminges maég
a help to heroes, the kinsman of Hemming,
nefa Gármundes níða cræftig.
grandson of Garmund, powerful over strife.