Swá ðá maélceare maga Healfdenes
So then over the sorrow of the time the son of Half-Dane
III
singála séað· ne mihte snotor hæleð
continually brooded; the wise hero could not
wéan onwendan· wæs þæt gewin tó swýð
turn away woe; that strife was too strong,
láþ ond longsum þe on ðá léode becóm,
hateful and enduring, that on the people came
nýdwracu níþgrim nihtbealwa maést.
fearfully cruel, violent trouble, the greatest night-evil.
Þæt fram hám gefrægn Higeláces þegn
That from home heard Hygelac's thane,
gód mid Géatum, Grendles daéda·
a good man of the Geats, of Grendel's deeds;
sé wæs moncynnes mægenes strengest
he was of mankind of the greatest strength,
on þaém dæge þysses lífes
on that day in this life,
æþele ond éacen· hét him ýðlidan
noble and mighty; he ordered them a wave-crosser
gódne gegyrwan· cwæð: hé gúðcyning
a good one  prepare; he said: the war-king
ofer swanráde sécean wolde
over swan-road he wished to seek,
maérne þéoden þá him wæs manna þearf·
that mighty clan-chief, since he was in need of men;
ðone síðfæt him snotere ceorlas
that adventure him, the clear-headed chaps,
lýt hwón lógon þéah hé him léof waére
very little begrudged though he was dear to them,
hwetton higerófne· haél scéawedon.
they urged on the valiant-hearted one, and observed the omens.
Hæfde se góda Géata léoda
The worthy one had, from the Geatish peoples,
cempan gecorone þára þe hé cénoste
chosen champions, those who were the boldest he
findan mihte· fíftýna sum
could find; fifteen together,
sundwudu sóhte· secg wísade
they sought the sea-wood, he led the warriors,
lagucræftig mon landgemyrcu.
that sea-skilled man, to the boundary of the shore.
Fyrst forð gewát· flota wæs on ýðum
Time passed by; the ship was on the waves,
bát under beorge· beornas gearwe
the boat under the cliffs; the ready warriors
on stefn stigon  stréamas wundon,
stepped up into the prow  the currents curled round,
sund wið sande  secgas baéron
sea against sand  the men bore
on bearm nacan beorhte frætwe
into the bosom of boat bright arms and armour,
gúðsearo geatolíc· guman út scufon
noble war-gear; the fellows shoved off,
weras on wilsíð wudu bundenne.
men on a welcome voyage, in a well-braced ship.
Gewát þá ofer waégholm winde gefýsed
Then they went over the water-waves urged by the wind,
flota fámíheals fugle gelícost
the foamy-necked floater, remarkably bird-like
oð þæt ymb ántid óþres dógores
until in due time, on the second day,
wundenstefna gewaden hæfde
the curved-prow had made the journey,
þæt ða líðende land gesáwon,
so that the sailors sighted land,
brimclifu blícan, beorgas stéape
bright sea-cliffs, towering shores,
side saénæssas· þá wæs sund liden
wide headlands; then was the sea traversed,
éoletes æt ende. Þanon up hraðe
their sea-voyage at an end. Thence up quickly
Wedera léode on wang stigon·
the Wederas-warriors stepped onto land;
saéwudu saéldon· syrcan hrysedon
moored their vessel; their mail-shirts clanked
gúðgewaédo· gode þancedon
those war-garments; they thanked God
þæs þe him ýþláde éaðe wurdon.
that for them the wave-paths had been smooth.
Þá of wealle geseah weard Scildinga
Then from the wall saw the ward of the Scyldings,
sé þe holmclifu healdan scolde·
he who the sea-cliffs had the duty to guard,
beran ofer bolcan beorhte randas
borne over the gang-plank, bright bossed-shields,
fyrdsearu fúslicu· hine fyrwyt bræc
eager war-devices; in him curiosity broke
módgehygdum hwæt þá men waéron·
the thoughts of his heart: what these men were;
gewát him þá tó waroðe wicge rídan
then he went to the shore riding his horse,
þegn Hróðgáres· þrymmum cwehte
the thane of Hrothgar; he forcefully shook
mægenwudu mundum· meþelwordum frægn:
his mighty wooden shaft, and with formal words asked:
'Hwæt syndon gé searohæbbendra
'What are you armour-wearers
byrnum werede þe þus brontne céol
bound in byrnies, who thus your tall keel
ofer lagustraéte laédan cwómon
over the sea-street leading came,
hider ofer holmas?'
hither over the waters?'
Hé wæs endesaéta· aégwearde héold
He was the coast-guardian, he held the sea-watch,
þé on land Dena láðra naénig
so that on Danish land no enemies at all
mid scipherge sceðþan ne meahte·
with a navy would not be able to ravage.
'Nó hér cúðlícor cuman ongunnon
'Not here more openly began to come
lindhæbbende né gé léafnesword
lindenwood shield-bearers, nor you the leave-word
gúðfremmendra gearwe ne wisson
of our war-makers certainly don't know
mága gemédu· naéfre ic máran geseah
our kinsmen's consent; never have I seen greater
eorla ofer eorþan ðonne is éower sum,
noble on earth than the one that you are,
secg on searwum· nis þæt seldguma
warrior in armour; this is no mere retainer
waépnum geweorðad· næfne him his wlite léoge,
made worthy by weapons; unless he is belied by his looks,
aénlic ansýn! Nú ic éower sceal
a unique appearance! Now I must your
frumcyn witan aér gé fyr heonan
lineage learn, ere you far hence,
léasscéaweras on land Dena
deceiving spies in the land of the Danes
furþur féran· Nú gé feorbúend
further fare; now you far-dwellers
merelíðende mínne gehýrað
you sea-sailors, hear my
ánfealdne geþóht: ofost is sélest
one-fold thought: speed is best
tó gecýðanne hwanan éowre cyme syndon.'
for reporting, whence your comings are.'