Nealles næs        geweoldum    wyrmhordan cræft
He was not at all in              control     of the skill of the              worm-hoard,
XXXII
sylfes willum    sé        ðe him sáre gesceód
of his own        desire,    he who sorely injured him,
ac for        þréanédlan    þéof náthwylces
because of        dire-distress    a thief of I know not which
hæleða        bearna    heteswengeas fléoh
sons of men            fled hostile blows,
ærnesþearfe    ond        ðaér inne weall
in need of a        hall    and there within raged,
secg        synbysig    sóna onwacade·
a man haunted by        guilt,    immediately watched over;
þæt géan ðám        gyste    gryrebróga stód·
then against the        stranger    stood horror and terror;
hwæðre        fyrensceapen
nevertheless upon the wicked        one
se faér begeat·
poured peril.
sincfæt        sóhte·    þaér wæs swylcra fela
He sought        treasure-gold,    there was many such,
in ðám eorðsele            aérgestréona
in that        earth-hall,    ancient treasures,
swá hý on        géardagum    gumena náthwylc
as they in former        days    some man,
eormenláfe            æþelan cynnes
this great        legacy    of a noble kind,
þanchycgende            þaér gehýdde
full of        thought,    had hid there
déore        máðmas·    ealle híe déað fornam
these dear        treasures;    all of them Death took
aérran        maélum    ond sí án ðá gén
in earlier        times,    and then were yet one
léoda duguðe    sé        ðaér lengest hwearf
of the old warriors of that        people,    the one who moved about there        longest,
weard        winegeómor    wénde þæs yldan·
the friend-grieving        warden,    he        hoped to delay that much,
þæt hé lýtel        fæc     longgestréona
so        that he for a little while     the long-kept treasure
brúcan        móste.    Beorh eallgearo
would be able to        enjoy.    The barrow all-ready
wunode on        wonge    wæterýðum néah
occupied the        plain    near the water-waves,
níwe be        næsse    nearocræftum fæst·
new on the        headland,    made secure by difficult-craft;
þaér on innan        bær     eorlgestréona
there inside        bore    of the treasure of earls
hringa hyrde              handwyrðne daél
a hoard of        rings    a hand-fashioned share
faéttan        goldes·    féa worda cwæð:
of plated        gold;    some words he spoke:
'Heald þú nú,        hrúse,    nú hæleð ne móstan
'Now hold you, Earth,    now the heroes        cannot
eorla        aéhte.    Hwæt, hyt aér on ðé
earls'        possessions.    Listen, it formerly from        you
góde        begéaton·    gúðdéað fornam
was obtained by good        men;    war-death has taken away,
feorhbeale        frécne    fyrena gehwylcne
terrible murder of        life,    of crimes each one,
léoda mínra    þá        mé ðe þis ofgeaf:
my belovèd        people,    they gave this up to me:
gesáwon        seledréam·    hé náh hwá sweord wege
they had seen joy in the        hall;    he I have not, who might wield sword
oððe        fægrie    faéted waége
or make        beautiful    this gilded flagon,
dryncfæt        déore·    duguð ellor séoc·
this precious drinking        vessel;    the veteran warriors are ill        elsewhere;
sceal se hearda        helm    hyrstedgolde
must the stern        helmet    adorned with gold
faétum        befeallen·    feormynd swefað
stripped of its        ornaments;    the burnishers slumbers,
þá ðe        beadogríman    býwan sceoldon·
they who        war-masks    ought to brighten;
gé swylce séo        herepád    sío æt hilde gebád
also so the army's coats of        mail,    which in battle endured
ofer borda        gebræc    bite írena
over the shattering of        shield-boards    the bite of iron,
brosnað æfter        beorne·    ne mæg byrnan hring
decay along with the        men;    byrnie's ring may not
æfter        wígfruman    wíde féran
with        war-fighter    fare widely,
hæleðum be        healfe·    næs hearpan wyn
alongside        heroes;    there was not harp's joy,
gomen        gléobéames    né gód hafoc
delight of glee-wood,    nor good hawk
geond sæl        swingeð    né se swifta mearh
soaring through the        hall,    nor swift horse
burhstede        béateð·    bealocwealm hafað
trampling the        courtyard;    baleful death has
fela        feorhcynna    forð onsended.'
many of my living        kin    sent forth.'
Swá        giómormód    giohðo maénde
Thus sad at        heart    in grief he bemoaned
án æfter        eallum·    unbliðe hwearf
one after        all,    unhappily passed
dæges ond        nihtes    oð ðæt déaðes wylm
days and        nights,    until the flood of Death
hrán æt        heortan.    Hordwynne fond
reached to his        heart.    Hoard-joy he found,
eald        úhtsceaða    opene standan
the old twilight-scather,    standing        open,
sé ðe        byrnende    biorgas séceð
he who,        burning,    seeks barrows,
nacod        níðdraca·    nihtes fléogeð
the naked malevolent        dragon;    he flies by night,
fýre        befangen·    hyne foldbúend
encircled in        fire;    him earth-dwellers
: : : : : : : : : : :        :nan.    Hé gesécean sceall
hearm on        hrúsan    þaér hé haéðen gold
harm in the        ground,    where he heathen gold
warað wintrum        fród·    ne byð him wihte ðý sél.
guards, wise in        winters;    he is not a bit better for        that.
Swá se        ðéodsceaða    þréo hund wintra
So the        people-scather    three hundred winters
héold on        hrúsan    hordærna sum
ruled in the        earth    of one of the hoard-halls,
éacencræftig     oð        ðæt hyne án ábealch
vastly        powerful,    until one angered him,
mon on        móde:    mandryhtne bær
a man in pride:    he bore to his liege-lord
faéted        waége·    frioðowaére bæd
the gold-adorned        cup,    begged peace-truce
hláford        sínne·    ðá wæs hord rásod,
from his        lord;    then was the hoard ransacked,
onboren béaga        hord,    béne getíðad
rings' hoard borne        off,    a boon was granted
féasceaftum        men·    fréa scéawode
to the wretched        man;    a lord examined
fíra        fyrngeweorc    forman síðe.
the ancient work of        men    for the first time.
Þá se wyrm        onwóc     wróht wæs geníwad
then the worm        awoke,     quarrel was renewed
stonc ðá æfter        stáne·    stearcheort onfand
he sniffed along the stone,    the harsh-hearted one found
féondes        fótlást·    hé tó forð gestóp
the foot-print of his foe;     he too far forward had        stepped
dyrnan        cræfte    dracan héafde néah.
in his stealthy        craft    near the dragon's head.
Swá mæg        unfaége    éaðe gedígan
wéan ond        wraécsíð    sé ðe waldendes
woe and hardship,    he        who the Ruler's
hyldo        gehealdeþ.    Hordweard sóhte
grace protects.    The hoard-ward sought
georne æfter        grunde·    wolde guman findan
eagerly along the        ground,    he wished to find the man,
þone þe him on        sweofote    sáre getéode·
the one who him in his        slumber    had sorely harmed;
hát ond        hréohmód    hlaéwum oft ymbehwearf
hot and        fierce-minded,    he often circled among the        mounds
ealne        útanweardne     né ðaér aénig mon
all round the        outside     not any man there
on þám        wéstenne    hwæðre hilde gefeh
in that        wilderness,    but he rejoiced in battle,
beadu        weorces     hwílum on beorh æthwearf·
of        battle-work     sometimes he turned back to the        barrow,
sincfæt        sóhte·    hé þaét sóna onfand·
sought the        treasure-cup;    he suddenly discovered,
ðæt hæfde gumena        sum    goldes gefandod
that a certain man had            disturbed the gold,
héahgestréona·    hordweard        onbád
the high        treasures;    the hoard-ward waited
earfoðlíce    oð        ðæt aéfen cwóm·
with great        difficulty,    until evening came;
wæs ðá        gebolgen      beorges hyrde·
then was        enraged    the keeper of the barrow,
wolde se        láða    líge forgyldan
he wished the        injury    to repay with flame,
drincfæt        dýre.    Þá wæs dæg sceacen
the dear        drinking-vessel.    Then the day was        departed
wyrme on        willan·    nó on wealle læg
to the joy of the        wyrm;    he did not lie within the wall,
bídan wolde    ac        mid baéle fór
(nor) wished to        wait,    but with bale-fire set forth,
fýre        gefýsed·    wæs se fruma egeslíc
infused with        flame;    this beginning was terrible
léodum on        lande    swá hyt lungre wearð
for the people in the        land,    as it soon was
on hyra        sincgifan    sáre geendod.
upon their treasure-giver     painfully        ended.