Þá wæs gesýne þæt se síð ne ðáh
Then it was seen that the venture did not benefit
XLII
þám ðe unrihte inne gehýdde
who he unrightly had hidden inside,
wræce under wealle· weard aér ofslóh
vengeance under the walls; this warden earlier slew
féara sumne· þá sío faéhð gewearð
one man of a few; then was the feud
gewrecen wráðlíce. Wundur hwár þonne
wrathfully avenged. It is a wonder where then
eorl ellenróf ende gefére
a man famed for courage should meet end
lífgesceafta þonne leng ne mæg
of his fated life, when he can no longer
mon mid his maégum meduseld búan·
one among his kinsmen, inhabit a mead-hall;
swá wæs Bíowulfe, þá hé biorges weard
thus it was for Beowulf, when he the barrow's ward
sóhte searoníðas: seolfa ne cúðe
sought treacherous quarrels: he himself did not know
þurh hwæt his worulde gedál weorðan sceolde.
through what his parting from this world must bring about.
Swá hit oð dómes dæg díope benemdon
Thus until judgement's day deeply declared
þéodnas maére þá ðæt þaér dydon·
the great princes, who put it there,
þæt se secg waére synnum scildig
that the man would be guilty of crimes,
hergum geheaðerod hellbendum fæst
banned from sacred places, in hell-bonds fast,
wommum gewítnad sé ðone wong strude·
reproached for his transgressions, he who plundered that place;
næs hé goldhwæte gearwor hæfde
he was not liberal with gold (nor) had he readily
ágendes ést aér gescéawod.
the kindness of a lord ever shown.
Wígláf maðelode Wíhstánes sunu:
Wiglaf spoke, the son of Weohstan,
'Oft sceall eorl monig ánes willan
'Often must many men, for the will of one,
wraéc ádréogan swá ús geworden is·
endure exile, as it has happened to us;
ne meahton wé gelaéran léofne þéoden
we could not convince the beloved prince,
ríces hyrde raéd aénigne·
the keeper of the kingdom, by any counsel,
þæt hé ne grétte goldweard þone·
that he not greet the gold-ward,
léte hyne licgean þaér hé longe wæs,
let him lie, where he long had been,
wícum wunian oð woruldende·
inhabiting his abodes until the world's end;
heoldon héahgesceap· hord ys gescéawod,
he held to his noble destiny; the hoard is exposed,
grimme gegongen· þæt gifeðe wæs
grimly gained; that was granted
tó swíð þé ðone þyder ontyhte.
too harshly which him impelled thither.
Ic wæs þaér inne ond þæt eall geondseh
I was there inside and looked over all of it,
recedes geatwa þá mé gerýmed wæs,
the trappings of the hall, when the way was cleared for me,
nealles swaéslíce síð álýfed
not at all sweetly was the errand allowed
inn under eorðweall· ic on ofoste geféng
inside the earthwall; I seized in haste
micle mid mundum mægenbyrðenne
much with my hands, a mighty burden
hordgestréona· hider út ætbær
of hoard-treasures, bore it out hither
cyninge mínum· cwico wæs þá géna
to my king; he was still alive then,
wís ond gewittig· worn eall gespræc
wise and knowing; he spoke much on many things,
gomol on gehðo ond éowic grétan hét·
old in his grief, and commanded me greet you all,
bæd þæt gé geworhton æfter wines daédum
bid that you build in accord of your friend's deeds
in baélstede beorh þone héän
in the cremation place a high barrow,
micelne ond maérne swá hé manna wæs
large and splendid, as he was of men
wígend weorðfullost wíde geond eorðan
a warrior most honoured thought this wide earth,
þenden hé burhwelan brúcan móste.
while he the prosperity of a city could enjoy.
Uton nú efstan óðre síðe
Let us now hasten another time
séon ond sécean on searogeþræc
to see and to seek in that heap of cunningly wrought things,
wundur under wealle· ic éow wísige
a wonder under the walls; I shall guide you,
þæt gé genóge néon scéawiað
so that you sufficient close-up will see
béagas ond brád gold· síe sío baér gearo
rings and broad gold; let the bier be ready,
aédre geæfned þonne wé út cymen
quickly prepared, when we come out,
ond þonne geferian fréan úserne
and then carry our lord,
léofne mannan þaér hé longe sceal
beloved man, where he must long
on ðæs waldendes waére geþolian.'
in the Ruler's protection endure.'
Hét ðá gebéodan byre Wíhstánes
He then commanded to direct, the son of Weohstan,
hæle hildedíor hæleða monegum
the battle-brave hero, many warriors,
boldágendra þæt híe baélwudu
house-holders, that they the pyre-wood
feorran feredon folcágende
to fetch from afar, folk-chieftains,
gódum tógénes: 'Nú sceal gléd fretan,
to the good man: 'Now must the fire devour,
weaxan wonna lég wigena strengel
the dim flame grow, the ruler of warriors,
þone ðe oft gebád ísernscúre
he who often endured shower of iron,
þonne straéla storm strengum gebaéded
when the storm of arrows, impelled by bow-strings,
scóc ofer scildweall· sceft nytte héold
shot over the shield-wall; shaft held true to task,
fæðergearwum fús· fláne fulléode.'
its feather-trappings eager, arrow-head followed.'
Húru se snotra sunu Wíhstánes
Indeed the wise son of Weohstan
ácígde of corðre cyniges þegnas
summoned from the troop of king's thanes,
syfone tósomne þá sélestan·
seven altogether, the best;
éode eahta sum under inwithróf
he went, one of eight, under the evil roof
hilderinc·sum on handa bær
one battle-man bore in his hands
aéledléoman sé ðe on orde géong.
a fire-brand, he who went in the fore-front.
Næs ðá on hlytme hwá þæt hord strude
It was not in a casting of lots, who would plunder that hoard,
syððan orwearde aénigne daél
when unprotected any part
secgas geségon on sele wunian
the men saw remaining in the hall,
laéne licgan· lýt aénig mearn
lying frail; little did anyone mourn
þæt hí ofostlíce út geferedon
that they quickly carried out
dýre máðmas· dracan éc scufun
precious treasures; the dragon too they shoved,
wyrm ofer weallclif· léton wég niman,
the wyrm over the cliff-wall, they let the waves take,
flód fæðmian frætwa hyrde·
the flood enfold, that keeper of baubles;
þæt wæs wundengold on waén hladen
that was braided gold loaded on the waggon,
aéghwæs unrím, æþelinge boren
of each kind countless, to the prince bore,
hárum hilde tó hrones næsse.
hoary grey from battle, to the whale's headland.