Ðá wæs        gegongen    guman unfródum
Then it        went    with the young man
XXXVIIII
earfoðlíce     þæt        hé on eorðan geseah
painfully,     that        he saw on the ground
þone        léofestan    lífes æt ende
the dearest        man    at the end of his life
bléate        gebaéran·    bona swylce læg
miserably        enduring;    the slayer also lay,
egeslíc        eorðdraca    ealdre beréafod
the terrible        earth-dragon     bereft of life,
bealwe        gebaéded·    béahhordum leng
balefully beaten        down;    the ring-hoard longer
wyrm        wóhbogen    wealdan ne móste
the wickedly coiled        wyrm    could not control,
ac him        írenna    ecga fornámon,
rather him        irons'     edges took off,
hearde        heaðoscearde    homera láfe
the hard,        battle-notched    leavings of hammers,
þæt se        wídfloga    wundum stille
so that the        wide-flier,    stilled by wounds,
hréas on        hrúsan    hordærne néah·
fell to the        ground    near the hoard-store;
nalles æfter        lyfte    lácende hwearf
not at all through the        air    flying turned
middelnihtum·     máðmaéhta        wlonc
in the middle of        nights,    proud of his prized possessions,
ansýn ýwde    ac hé        eorðan geféoll
manifested an        appearance,    but he fell to earth
for ðæs        hildfruman    hondgeweorce.
by the        battle-leader's    work of his own        hands.
Húru þæt on        lande    lýt manna ðáh
Indeed it on        land    few men succeeded,
mægenágendra            míne gefraége
possessors of        strength,    I have heard,
þéah ðe hé daéda        gehwæs    dyrstig waére·
though he in all        deeds    were daring;
þæt hé wið        attorsceaðan     oreðe geraésde
that he against the        poison-scourge's    breath rushed,
oððe        hringsele    hondum styrede
or its        ring-hall    stirred up with hands,
gif hé        wæccende    weard onfunde
if he a        watching      warden        found
búon on        beorge·    Bíowulfe wearð
living in the        barrow;    for Beowulf was
dryhtmáðma        daél    déaðe forgolden·
the noble treasures'        share,    repaid with death;
hæfde        aéghwæðre    ende geféred
each of them had     arrived at the end
laénan        lífes.    Næs ðá lang tó ðon
of his loaned        life.    It was not long to when
þæt ðá        hildlatan    holt ofgéfan
that the        battle-shirkers    gave up the forest,
týdre        tréowlogan    týne ætsomne
cowardly troth-breakers,    ten        together,
ðá ne dorston        aér    dareðum lácan
who had not dared        before    with javelins to fight
on hyra        mandryhtnes    miclan þearfe
in their        liege-lord's    great need
ac hý        scamiende    scyldas baéran
but they,        shamed,    bore shields,
gúðgewaédu     þaér        se gomela læg·
war-clothing,            to where the old man lay;
wlitan on        Wíláf·    hé gewérgad sæt
they looked at        Wiglaf;    he sat wearied,
féðecempa     fréan        eaxlum néah·
the        foot-soldier    near the shoulders of his lord;
wehte hyne        wætre·    him wiht ne spéow·
he tried to rouse him with water,            but it availed him not a bit;
ne meahte hé on        eorðan,    ðéah hé úðe wél
he could not on earth,     though he wished well,
on ðám        frumgáre    feorh gehealdan
in that first-spear    preserve life,
né ðæs        wealdendes    wiht oncirran:
nor the Ruler's            man        turn back:
wolde dóm        godes    daédum raédan
the judgement of God        would    rule the deeds
gumena        gehwylcum    swá hé nú gén dëð.
of all men,    as        it still does now.
Þá wæs æt ðám        geongan    grim andswaru
Then there was from that young        man    a grim answer
éðbegéte     þám ðe        aér his elne forléas·
easily got,    for        him who earlier had lost his courage;
Wígláf maðelode            Wéohstánes sunu
Wiglaf        spoke,    Weohstan's son,
secg        sárigferð    seah on unléofe:
a man sore at        heart    looked on the unloved men:
'Þæt, lá, mæg        secgan     sé ðe wyle sóð specan·
'That, indeed, may        say     he who wishes to speak the truth,
þæt se        mondryhten    sé éow ðá máðmas geaf
that the        liege-lord,    he who gave you treasures,
éoredgeatwe     þé        gé þaér on standað
cavalry-gear,    that you stand in        there
þonne hé on        ealubence    oft gesealde
when he on the        ale-bench    often gave
healsittendum    helm ond byrnan,
to        hall-sitters    helm and byrnie,
þéoden his        þegnum    swylce hé þrýdlícost
the chieftain to his        thanes    such as he the grandest
ówer feor oððe        néah    findan meahte
anywhere far or        near    was able to find
þæt hé génunga            gúðgewaédu
that he        completely    war-clothing
wráðe        forwurpe    ðá hyne wíg beget·
grievously threw        away,    when fighting befell him;
nealles        folccyning    fyrdgesteallum
not at all the        folk-king    his companions in arms
gylpan        þorfte·    hwæðre him god úðe
need to boast        about;    yet God granted him,
sigora        waldend    þæt hé hyne sylfne gewræc
victories'        Ruler,    that he avenged himself,
ána mid ecge    þá        him wæs elnes þearf.
one with a        blade,    when for him was need of        valour.
Ic him        lífwraðe    lýtle meahte
I him life-protection     little        could
ætgifan æt        gúðe    ond ongan swá þéah
provide in        war,    and yet began
ofer mín        gemet    maéges helpan·
beyond my measure    to aid my kinsman;
symle wæs þý        saémra    þonne ic sweorde drep
ever was it the weaker    when I struck with        sword,
ferhðgeníðlan            fýr unswíðor
the deadly        enemy,    fire less fiercely
wéoll of        gewitte·    fergendra tó lýt
surged from the        seat of intellect;    leaders too few
þrong ymbe        þéoden    þá hyne sío þrág becwóm.
thronged around the        chieftain,    when distress came to him.
Hú sceal        sincþego    ond swyrdgifu
How must        treasure-receipt    and sword-giving
eall        éðelwyn    éowrum cynne
all native        joy    for your kin,
lufen        álicgean!    Londrihtes mót
delight        cease!    Of        land-rights must
þaére        maégburge    monna aéghwylc
of your        clan    every man
ídel        hweorfan    syððan æðelingas
become        deprived,    when nobles
feorran        gefricgean    fléam éowerne
from afar        learn    of your flight,
dómléasan        daéd:    déað bið sélla
gloryless        dead:    death is better
eorla        gehwylcum    þonne edwítlíf.'
for all men    than        a life of dishonour.'