Heht ðá þæt heaðoweorc tó hagan bíodan
Then he commanded battle-result to be announced at the stronghold,
XL
úp ofer ecgclif þaér þæt eorlweorod
up over the cliff-edge, where that warrior-band
morgenlongne dæg módgiómor sæt
the morning-long day sat sad in spirit,
bordhæbbende béga on wénum:
shield-bearers, in expectation of two things:
endedógores ond eftcymes
the end of his days or the return
léofes monnes. Lýt swígode
of the dear man. On little was he silent
níwra spella sé ðe næs gerád
of the new tidings, he who rode the headland,
ac hé sóðlíce sægde ofer ealle:
but he truly said over all:
'Nú is wilgeofa Wedra léoda
'Now is the wish-giver of the Wederas' nation,
dryhten Géata déaðbedde fæst
the lord of the Geats unmoving on his death-bed,
wunað wælreste wyrmes daédum·
remaining in the repose of slaughter by the wyrm's deeds;
him on efn ligeð ealdorgewinna
beside him lies his life-contender
siexbennum séoc: sweorde ne meahte
sick with seax-wounds: he could not with his sword
on ðám áglaécean aénige þinga
on that fearsome being in any way
wunde gewyrcean· Wígláf siteð
inflict wounds; Wiglaf sits
ofer Bíowulfe byre Wíhstánes
over Beowulf, the son of Weohstan,
eorl ofer óðrum unlifigendum·
one earl over another unliving,
healdeð higemaéðum héafodwearde
he holds, weary in his mind, head-watch
léofes ond láðes. Nú ys léodum wén
over beloved and loathed. Now for the nation one expects
orleghwíle syððan undyrne
time of warfare when unsecret
Froncum ond Frýsum fyll cyninges
to the Franks and Frisians, the fall of the king,
wíde weorðeð· wæs sío wróht scepen
widely becomes; the quarrel was shaped
heard wið Húgas syððan Higelác cwóm
fierce against the Hugas, when Hygelac came
faran flotherge on Frésna land
faring with a fleet onto the Frisians' land
þaér hyne Hetware hilde gehnaégdon·
where him the Hetware attacked in battle,
elne geéodon mid ofermægene
it happened in courage with over-strength,
þæt se byrnwiga búgan sceolde·
that the mailed-warrior had to bow down;
féoll on féðan· nalles frætwe geaf
he fell among the foot-troop; not at all ornaments gave
ealdor dugoðe· ús wæs á syððan
the lord to his retinue; for us was ever after
Merewíoingas milts ungyfeðe.
the Merovingian (king's) kindness withheld.
Né ic te Swéoðéode sibbe oððe tréowe
I do not from the Swedes peace or truce
wihte ne wéne ac wæs wíde cúð
expect a bit, but it was widely known
þætte Ongenðío ealdre besnyðede
that Ongentheow of life deprived
Hæðcen Hréþling wið Hrefnawudu
Haethcyn Hrethel's son at Raven's Wood,
þá for onmédlan aérest gesóhton
when for arrogance first sought out
Géata léode Gúð-Scilfingas
the Geatish people the War-Scilfings
sóna him se fróda fæder Óhtheres
at once him the wise, old father of Ohthere,
eald ond egesfull hondslyht ágeaf·
ancient and terrible, returned onslaught by hand;
ábréot brimwísan· brýda herode·
he destroyed the sea-wise man, he honoured his wife,
gomela ióméowlan golde berofene
the old, wisened woman bereft of her gold,
Onelan módor ond Óhtheres
Onela's mother and Ohthere's
ond ðá folgode feorhgeníðlan
and then he followed those life-enemies,
oð ðæt hí oðéodon earfoðlíce
until they escaped with difficulty,
in Hrefnesholt hláfordléase·
into Raven's Wood, without a lord;
besæt ðá sinherge sweorda láfe
then he besieged the huge (sacred) grove, the survivors of swords
wundum wérge· wéan oft gehét
weary with wounds; he often threatened woes
earmre teohhe ondlonge niht·
to the wretched company in the length of the night;
cwæð: hé on mergenne méces ecgum
said: he in the morning by the edges of a maiche
gétan wolde, sum on galgtréowum
he would sacrifice one of them on the gallow-tree
fuglum tó gamene· frófor eft gelamp
as game for the birds; relief came back
sárigmódum somod aérdæge
to the sorrow-spirited ones together with early day,
syððan híe Hygeláces horn ond býman
when they Hygelac's horn and trumpet,
gealdor ongéaton þá se góda cóm,
and his battle-yell recognised, then the good man came,
léoda dugoðe on lást faran.
with the tribe's veteran warriors travelling on the path.