Béowulf maþelode bearn Ecgþéowes:
Beowulf spoke, the son of Edgetheow:
XXVII
'Nú wé saélíðend secgan wyllað
'Now we sea-farers wish to say
feorran cumene þæt wé fundiaþ
having come from afar, that we are anxious
Higelác sécan· waéron hér tela
to seek Hygelac; we here were well
willum bewenede· þú ús wél dohtest.
entertained in our desires; you have treated us well.
Gif ic þonne on eorþan ówihte mæg
If then on earth I can (do) anything
þínre módlufan máran tilian,
of your affections earn more,
gumena dryhten, ðonne ic gýt dyde,
lord of men, than I have done yet,
gúðgeweorca ic béo gearo sóna
with feats of arms, I am ready at once,
gif ic þæt gefricge ofer flóda begang
if I find it out over the flood's expanse,
þæt þec ymbsittend egesan þýwað
that you neighbouring-tribes oppress with terror,
swá þec hetende hwílum dydon
as enemies to you sometimes did,
ic ðé þúsenda þegna bringe
I to you a thousand thanes will bring,
hæleþa tó helpe. Ic on Higeláce wát,
heroes as help. I know of Hygelac,
Géata dryhten þéah ðe hé geong syÿ
the lord of the Geats, though he is young,
folces hyrde· þæt hé mec fremman wile
the keeper of the folk, that he would support me
weordum ond worcum þæt ic þé wél herige
with words and with deeds, so that I might honour you rightly
ond þé tó géoce gárholt bere
and to you in aid bring a forest of spears,
mægenes fultum þaér ðé bið manna þearf.
the support of strength, where you be needful of men.
Gif him þonne Hréþrínc tó hofum Géata
If him, on the other hand, Hrethric to the Geatish court
geþingeð þéodnes bearn hé mæg þaér fela
decides (to go), chieftain's son, he shall there be able many
fréonda findan· feorcýþðe béoð
friends to find; distant lands are
sélran gesóhte þaém þe him selfa déah.'
better sought by one who is powerful himself.'
Hróðgár maþelode him on andsware:
Hrothgar spoke to him in reply:
'Þé þá wordcwydas wigtig drihten
'To you these sayings of words the wise Lord
on sefan sende· ne hýrde ic snotorlícor
has sent into mind; I have not heard more intelligently
on swá geongum feore guman þingian·
at such young age man make a speech;
þú eart mægenes strang ond on móde fród
you are strong in power and wise in your heart,
wís wordcwida· wén ic talige
judicious word-speaker; I consider it likely
gif þæt gegangeð þæt ðe gár nymeð
if it happens, that from you the spear takes,
hild heorugrimme Hréþles eaferan,
a horrendous battle Hrethel's heir,
ádl oþðe íren ealdor ðínne
sickness or iron your ruler,
folces hyrde ond þú þín feorh hafast
the guardian of the folk, and you have your life,
þæt þe Saé-Géatas sélran næbben
that the Sea-Geats could not have better
tó gecéosenne cyning aénigne
by choosing any other king,
hordweard hæleþa gyf þú healdan wylt
hoard-ward of heroes, if you wish to rule
mága ríce· mé þín módsefa
your kinsman's kingdom. Your spirit and heart me
lícað leng swá wél, léofa Béowulf·
pleases so well the longer (I know them), dear Beowulf;
hafast þú geféred þæt þám folcum sceal
you have achieved that for the folk shall
Géata léodum ond Gár-Denum
the people of the Geats and the Spear-Danes
sib gemaénum ond sacu restan,
in mutual peace, and strife subside,
inwitníþas, þé híe aér drugon,
hostilities, which they endured before;
wesan þenden ic wealde wídan ríces
shall be, while I rule the wide kingdom,
máþmas gemaéne, manig óþerne
wealth in common, many an other
gódum gegréttan ofer ganotes bæð·
with good things will greet over the gannet's bath;
sceal hringnaca ofer heáþu bringan
the ring-prowed ship shall bring over the high seas
lác ond luftácen· ic þá léode wát
offerings and tokens of friendship; I know these nations
gé wið féond gé wið fréond fæste geworhte
both towards foe and towards friend firmly disposed,
aéghwæs untaéle ealde wísan.'
blameless in everything, in the ancient manner.'
Ðá gít him eorla hléo hine gesealde
Then again to him the protector of earls gave to him,
mago Healfdenes máþmas twelf·
the son of Half-Dane, twelve treasures;
hét inne mid þaém lácum léode swaése
he commanded him with these gifts his own dear nation
sécean on gesyntum, snúde eft cuman·
to seek in safety, to return quickly;
gecyste þá cyning æþelum gód,
kissed then, the king the upright noble,
þéoden Scyldinga ðegn betostan
the chieftain of the Scyldings, the best thane
ond be healse genam· hruron him téaras
and took him by the neck; tears fell from him,
blondenfeaxum· him wæs béga wén
from the silver and gold whiskers; in him were both thoughts
ealdum infródum, óþres swíðor·
old and deeply wise, the second stronger,
þæt híe seoððan geséon móston
that they afterwards might meet,
módige on meþle· wæs him se man tó þon léof
brave in a formal summit; the man was so dear to him
þæt hé þone bréostwylm forberan ne mehte
that he the welling of his breast could not hold back
ac him on hreþre hygebendum fæst
but him in his heart in firm bounds of thought
æfter déorum men dyrne langað
for the dear man a remote longing
beorn wið blóde. Him Béowulf þanan
burned in his blood. Him Beowulf thence,
gúðrinc goldwlanc græsmoldan træd
warrior proud with gold, trod the grass-mound,
since hrémig· saégenga bád
triumphing in treasure. The sea-goer awaited
ágedfréän sé þe on ancre rád·
its lord and owner, which rode at its anchor;
þá wæs on gange gifu Hróðgáres
later on the journey was the gift of Hrothgar
oft geæhted· þæt wæs án cyning,
often praised; that was one king,
aéghwæs orleahtre oþ þæt hine yldo benam
in everything blameless, until age deprived him
mægenes wynnum sé þe oft manegum scód.
of strength's delights, a thing which continually harms many.