Hróðgár maþelode helm Scyldinga:
Hrothgar spoke, the Helm of the Scyldings:
XX
'Ne frín þú æfter saélum· sorh is geníwod
'Do not you ask after pleasures; sorrow is renewed
Denigea léodum· déad is Æschere
for the Danish nation; Æschere is dead,
Yrmenláfes yldra bróþor
Yrmenlaf's elder brother,
mín rúnwita ond mín raédbora
my confident and my chief counsellor,
eaxlgestealla ðonne wé on orlege
shoulder-companion, when we in war
hafelan weredon þonne hniton féþan
protected the head, when clashed with foot-soldiers,
eoferas cnysedan· swylc eorl scolde
dashed boars (atop helmets); so ought a man
wesan aérgód swylc Æschere wæs.
be experienced and noble, as Æschere was.
Wearð him on Heorote tó handbanan
In Heorot for him was a hand-slayer,
wælgaést waéfre· ic ne wát hwæþer
restless death-spirit; I know not whether,
atol aése wlanc eftsíðas téah
glorying in the carcass, she undertook a return journey,
fylle gefraégnod· héo þá faéhðe wræc
contented by her feast; she avenged the feud
þe þú gystran niht Grendel cwealdest
in which you yester-night Grendel quelled
þurh haéstne hád heardum clammum
through violent means in harsh embrace,
forþan hé tó lange léode míne
because he for too long my people
wanode ond wyrde hé æt wíge gecrang
diminished and destroyed, he fell in the fight,
ealdres scyldig ond nú óþer cwóm
having forfeited his life, and now the other has come,
mihtig mánscaða· wolde hyre maég wrecan·
the mighty crime-wreaker, she wants to avenge her kinsman,
gé feor hafað faéhðe gestaéled
and has very far carried her feud,
þæs þe þincean mæg þegne monegum
as it must seem to many a thane,
sé þe æfter sincgyfan on sefan gréoteþ:
who for the treasure-giver weeps in his heart:
hreþerbealo hearde· nú séo hand ligeð
hard mind-grief! now the hand has fallen away,
sé þe éow wélhwylcra wilna dohte.
which in all of you had sustained wishes.
Ic þæt londbúend léode míne
I it, land-dwellers, my people,
seleraédende secgan hýrde
hall-counsellors have heard tell
þæt híe gesáwon swylce twégen
that they saw two such
micle mearcstapan móras healdan,
massive marchers of no-man's land haunting the moors,
ellorgaéstas· ðaéra óðer wæs
alien spirits; one of them was,
þæs þe híe gewislícost gewitan meahton
as they most certainly were able to discern,
idese onlícnæs· óðer earmsceapen
of the likeness of a woman; the other one wretchedly shaped
on weres wæstmum wraéclástas træd
in the form of a man trod in the tracks of an exile,
næfne hé wæs mára þonne aénig man óðer·
except he was larger than any other man;
þone on géardagum Grendel nemdon
in days of yore him 'Grendel' named
foldbúende· nó híe fæder cunnon·
the earth-dwellers; they did not know of his father,
hwæþer him aénig wæs aér ácenned
whether of them any were born previously
dyrnra gásta. Híe dýgel lond
of obscure spirits. They a secret land
warigeað wulfhleoþu windige næssas
inhabited, wolf-slopes, windy water-capes,
frécne fengelád ðaér fyrgenstréam
a dangerous passage over the fen-waters, where mountain-stream
under næssa genipu niþer gewíteð
under the darkness of the headlands descended downward,
flód under foldan· nis þæt feor heonon
the flood under the earth; it is not that far hence
mílgemearces þæt se mere standeð·
in mile-marks, that the mere stands;
ofer þaém hongiað hrímge bearwas·
over it hangs frost-covered groves,
wudu wyrtum fæst wæter oferhelmað·
tree held fast by its roots overshadows the water;
þaér mæg nihta gehwaém níðwundor séon
there one may every night a horrible marvel see:
fýr on flóde· nó þæs fród leofað
fire on the water; not even the wise of them lives,
gumena bearna þæt þone grund wite.
of men's sons, that knows the bottom.
Ðéah þe haéðstapa hundum geswenced
Though the heath-stepper harrassed by hounds,
heorot hornum trum holtwudu séce
the hart with strong horns, seeks the forest,
feorran geflýmed· aér hé feorh seleð
put to flight from far, first he will give up his life,
aldor on ófre aér hé in wille
existence on the shore, before he will (leap) in
hafelan helan· nis þæt héoru stów·
to hide his head; it is not a pleasant place;
þonon ýðgeblond úp ástígeð
thence a maelström of the waves rises up,
won tó wolcnum þonne wind styreþ
dark to the clouds, when the wind stirs
láð gewidru oð þæt lyft drysmaþ·
grievous storms, until the air grows dark,
roderas réotað. Nú is se raéd gelang
the skies weep. Now is the remedy dependent upon
eft æt þé ánum· eard gít ne const
you alone once again; you do not know the region yet,
frécne stówe ðaér þú findan miht
terrible place where you might find
felasinnigne secg· séc gif þú dyrre·
the much-sinning creature; seek if you dare;
ic þé þá faéhðe féo léanige
for the feud you I would reward with wealth,
ealdgestréonum swá ic aér dyde,
with old treasures, as I did before,
wundungolde gyf þú on weg cymest.'
with twisted-gold, if you come away.'