Wígláf wæs        háten     Wéoxstánes sunu
Wiglaf he was called,    son of Weohstan,
XXXVI
léoflíc        lindwiga    léod Scylfinga
noble        shield-fighter,    man        of the Scylfings,
maég        Ælfheres·    geseah his mondryhten
kinsman of        Ælfhere;    he saw his liege-lord
under        heregríman    hát þrówian·
under the        war-mask    suffering heat;
gemunde ðá ðá áre    þé hé        him aér forgeaf
he remembered then the        honour    that he had given him before,
wícstede        weligne    Waégmundinga,
lush        dwelling-place    of the Waegmundings,
folcrihta        gehwylc    swá his fæder áhte·
to each folk-rights,    as his father had        owned;
ne mihte ðá        forhabban·    hond rond geféng
then he could not hold        back,    his hand seized his round shield,
geolwe        linde·    gomelswyrd getéah·
yellow        lindenwood,    he drew his ancient sword;
þæt wæs mid        eldum    Éanmundes láf
it was among        men    the legacy of Eanmund,
suna        Óhtere·    þám æt sæcce wearð
son of        Ohthere;    of        him in battle was,
wræcca        wineléasum    Wéohstánes bana
of the friendless        exile,    Weohstan his slayer
méces ecgum    ond        his mágum ætbær
by maiche's edges,    and to his kinsman        he brought back
brúnfágne        helm    hringde byrnan
bright-gleaming        helm,    ringed byrnie,
ealdsweord        etonisc·    þæt him Onela forgeaf
an old ogrish        sword;    that to him Onela returned,
his        gædelinges    gúðgewaédu
his        kinsman's    war-garment,
fyrdsearo        fúslíc·    nó ymbe ðá faéhðe spræc
war-devised        clothing;    he did not speak of the feud,
þéah ðe hé his bróðor        bearn    ábredwade·
though he        his brother's son    had slain;
hé frætwe        gehéold    fela misséra
he held the treasures    for many seasons,
bill ond        byrnan    oð ðæt his byre mihte
bill and byrnie,    until his son could
eorlscipe        efnan    swá his aérfæder·
accomplish noble        deeds    like his old father;
geaf him ðá mid        Géatum     gúðgewaéda
then, among the Geats, he gave        him     war-clothing,
aéghwæs unrím    þá        hé of ealdre gewát
of all kinds, in countless        number,    then he went from life,
fród on        forðweg.    Þá wæs forma síð
wise, on the way        forth.    Then was the first time
geongan cempan            þæt hé gúðe raés
for the young        champion,    that he the rush of war
mid his        fréodryhtne    fremman sceolde·
with his noble        lord    had to perform;
ne gemealt him se        módsefa    né his mægenes láf
his spirited heart in him did not melt        away,    nor the remainder of his strength
gewác æt        wíge·    þa se wyrm onfand
fail in the        fight;    then the wyrm had discovered,
syððan híe        tógædre     gegán hæfdon.
when they        together    had come.
Wígláf        maðelode·    wordrihta fela
Wiglaf        spoke,    many proper words
sægde        gesíðum     him wæs sefa geómor :
he said to his        companions     his heart was sad in him :
'Ic ðæt maél        geman     þaér wé medu þégun
'I recall that        time,     where we partook of mead,
þonne wé        gehéton    ússum hláforde
when we        promised    to our lord
in bíorsele    ðé        ús ðás béagas geaf
in the        beer-hall,    he who gave us rings,
þæt wé him ðá        gúðgetawa    gyldan woldon
that we to him for the        war-gear    wished to repay,
gif him        þyslicu    þearf gelumpe,
if for him        such    a need arose,
helmas ond heard        sweord.    Ðé hé úsic on herge gecéas
with helmets and hard        swords.    Because of that he chose us from the        army
tó ðyssum        síðfate    sylfes willum·
for this        adventure    of his own desire;
onmunde úsic        maérða    ond mé þás máðmas geaf
he deemed us worthy of        renown,    and gave me these treasures,
þé hé úsic        gárwígend    góde tealde
because he us        spear-warriors    considered excellent,
hwate        helmberend    þéah ðe hláford ús
bold        helm-bearers,    though the lord for us
þis        ellenweorc    áná áðóhte
this valiant        work    intended alone
tó        gefremmanne,    folces hyrde,
to perform,    the        keeper of the folk,
forðán hé manna        maést     maérða gefremede
because he of men the        most    glories has achieved,
daéda        dollícra.    Nú is sé dæg cumen
the most audacious        deeds.    Now is the day come
þæt úre        mandryhten    mægenes behófað
that our        liege-lord    has need of strength
gódra        gúðrinca·    wutun gongan tó
of good        war-men;    let us go to,
helpan        hildfruman    þenden hyt sÿ
aid the        battle-leader,    while the heat lasts,
glédegesa        grim.    God wát on mec
the fierce        fire-terror.    God knows of me
þæt mé is micle        léofre     þæt mínne líchaman
that to me it is much more        agreeable,    that my body
mid mínne        goldgyfan    gléd fæðmie·
with my        gold-giver    the fire embraces;
ne þynceð mé        gerysne    þæt wé rondas beren
it does not seem proper to        me,    that we bear shields
eft tó        earde    nemne we aéror mægen
back to our        land,    unless we first can
fáne        gefyllan,    feorh ealgian
fell the        foe,    defend the life
Wedra        ðéodnes·    ic wát geare
of the chief of the        Wederas;    I know well,
þæt naéron        ealdgewyrht     þæt hé ána scyle
that his deeds of old are not        such,    that he alone should
Géata        duguðe    gnorn þrówian,
of the Geats'        retinue    sorrow suffer,
gesígan æt        sæcce·    úrum sceal sweord ond helm
to sink in        strife;    for the two        of us must sword and helm,
byrne ond        byrduscrúd    bám gemaéne.'
byrnie and rich shroud    both        share.'
Wód þá þurh þone        wælréc·    wígheafolan bær
Then he waded through the smoke of        slaughter,     bore his war-head
fréan on        fultum·    féa worda cwæð:
to the support of his        lord;    a few words he spoke:
'Léofa        Bíowulf,    laést eall tela
'Dear        Beowulf,    carry out all well,
swá ðú on        geoguðféore    geára gecwaéde
as you in        youth-life    long ago said,
þæt ðú ne        álaéte    be ðé lifigendum
that you would not        allow,    with you still living,
dóm        gedréosan·    scealt nú daédum róf,
glory to        fail;    you must now in bold deeds,
æðeling        anhýdig,    ealle mægene
a noble firm in        mind,    with all of your strength,
feorh        ealgian·    ic ðé fullaéstu.'
defend your life;            I shall support you.'
Æfter ðám        wordum    wyrm yrre cwóm
After those        words    the wrathful wyrm came,
atol        inwitgæst    óðre síðe
awful cruel        visitor    a second time,
fýrwylmum        fáh    fíonda níosian
with hostile, gleaming flood of        fire    to seek his foes
láðra        manna·    líg        ýðum for·
the hated        humans;    the flame came forth in waves,
born bord wið        rond·    byrne ne meahte
burned shield to the        boss;    the byrnie could not
geongum        gárwigan    géoce gefremman
to the young        spear-fighter    lend support
ac se maga        geonga    under his maéges scyld
but the young        man,    under his kinsman's shield
elne geéode    þá        his ágen wæs
courageously        advanced,    when his own was
glédum        forgrunden.    Þá gén gúðcyning
consumed by        fire.    Then again the war-king
miht        gemunde·    mægenstrengo slóh
remembered his        strength,    with mighty force struck
hildebille    þæt        hyt on heafolan stód
with his battle-bill,    so that it stood in        (the serpent's) head
níþe        genýded·    Nægling forbærst·
driven by        violence;    Naegling burst asunder,
geswác æt        sæcce    sweord Bíowulfes
failed in the        fight    Beowulf's sword
gomol ond        graégmaél·    him þæt gifeðe ne wæs
ancient and        silver-streaked;    it was not granted to him,
þæt him        írenna    ecge mihton
that for him        irons'    edges could
helpan æt        hilde:    wæs sío hond tó strong
help in        battle:    the hand was too strong,
sé ðe méca        gehwane    míne gefraége
that each one of the blades             I heard
swenge        ofersóhte    þonne hé tó sæcce bær
in stroke he        over-taxed;    when he bore to battle
waépen wundum        heard    næs him wihte ðé sél.
a weapon hardened by wounds,      it was not any better for him.
Þá wæs        þéodsceaða    þriddan síðe
Then the scourge of people            a third time,
frécne        fýrdraca    faéhða gemyndig·
the fierce fire-drake            enmity in mind,
raésde on ðone        rófan    þá him rúm ágeald
rushed at the brave        man,    when he        was yielded space,
hát ond        heaðogrim    heals ealne ymbeféng
hot and        battle-fierce,    (Beowulf's) whole neck he        clamped
biteran        bánum·    hé geblódegod wearð
between sharp        fangs;    he was drenched
sáwuldríore·     swát ýðum        wéoll.
in        life-blood;    gore gushed in waves.