Ðá gýt aéghwylcum             eorla drihten
Then, furthermore, to each one             of the earl's company
XVI
þára þe mid Béowulfe             brimléade teah
those with Beowulf             travelled the sea-path,
on þære medubence             máþðum gesealde
on the mead-bench             he gave treasures,
yrfeláfe      ond        þone aénne heht
inherited relics,             and the one man decreed
golde forgyldan             þone ðe Grendel aér
to requite in gold             whom Grendel first
máne ácwealde             swá hé hyra má wolde
in wickedness quelled,             as he would have more of them
nefne him wítig god             wyrd forstóde
except for them wise God             that fate had prevented,
ond ðæs mannes mód.             Metod eallum wéold
and this man's courage.      The        Measure of Fate controlled all
gumena cynnes,             swá hé nú gít déëð·
for mankind,             as he now still does;
forþan bið andgit             aéghwaér sélest
therefore understanding is             best everywhere,
ferhðes foreþanc·             fela sceal gebídan
the forethought of mind;             he must abide much
léofes ond láþes             sé þe longe hér
love and much hate             he who long here
on ðyssum windagum             worolde brúceð.
in these days of strife             would enjoy the world.
Þaér wæs sang ond swég             samod ætgædere
There was song and sound             at the same time all together
fore Healfdenes             hildewísan,
before Half-Dane's             battle-plotter,
gomenwudu gréted,             gid oft wrecen
the glee-wood plucked,      a lay often        recited
ðonne healgamen             Hróþgáres scop
when a hall-performance                   Hrothgar's bard
æfter medobence             maénan scolde:
before the mead-bench             was obliged to utter:
Finnes eaferum             ðá híe se faér begeat
concerning        Finn's heirs, with whom,      when disaster struck        them,
hæleð Healfdena·             Hnæf Scyldinga
the hero of Half-Danes,             Hnaef the Scylding,
in Fréswæle             feallan scolde.
on the Frisian battle-field             was fated to fall.
Né húru Hildeburh             herian þorfte
Truly, Hildeburh did not      have need to        praise
eotena tréowe·             unsynnum wearð
the good faith of the Eotens;      she was        guiltless,
beloren léofum             æt þám hildplegan
bereft of her dear ones:              in the war-play
bearnum ond bróðrum·             híe on gebyrd hruron
her son and brother;             they fell, in accorance with Fate,
gáre wunde·             þæt wæs geómuru ides.
wounded by spear;             that was a mournful woman.
Nalles hólinga             Hóces dohtor
Not without reason did             Hoc's daughter
meotodsceaft bemearn             syþðan morgen cóm
grieve over Fate's decree,             when the morning came,
ðá héo under swegle             geséon meahte
then she under the sky             could see
morþorbealo mága             þaér hé aér maéste héold
the baleful slaughter of kinsmen,             where before he had held the most
worolde wynne·             wíg ealle fornam
joy in the world,             war took all
Finnes þegnas             nemne féaum ánum
of Finn's thanes,             except a few alone,
þæt hé ne mehte             on þaém meðelstede
so that he could not             in that meeting-place
wíg Hengeste             wiht gefeohtan
the clash with Hengest      conclude at all,
né þá wéaláfe             wíge forþringan
nor the woeful remnant             by battle dislodge from their position,
þéodnes ðegne             ac hig him geþingo budon:
the prince's thane,             so they offered them settlement:
þæt híe him óðer flet             eal gerýmdon
that they for them the other dwelling             would completely clear,
healle ond héahsetl             þæt híe healfre geweald
hall and high seat,             that they would half of it control
wið eotena bearn             ágan móston
with the Eotens' sons      might have,
ond æt feohgyftum             Folcwaldan sunu
and at the giving of treasure             Folcwalden's son
dógra gehwylce             Dene weorþode·
each day      the        Danes would honour,
Hengestes héap             hringum wenede
Hengest's company             would revere with rings,
efne swá swíðe             sincgestréonum
with even as much             precious possesions
faéttan goldes             swá hé Frésena cyn
of ornate gold             exactly as he the Frisian kind
on béorsele             byldan wolde.
in the beer-hall             would wish to embolden.
Ðá híe getruwedon             on twá healfa
Then they pledged             on both sides
fæste frioðuwaére·             Fin Hengeste
firm compact of peace;             Finn to Hengest
elne unflitme             áðum benemde
with incontestable earnestness             proclaimed an oath
þæt hé þá wéaláfe             weotena dóme
that he the woeful remnant,             by sages' judgement,
árum héolde             þæt ðaér aénig mon
would hold in honour,             that there any man
wordum né worcum             waére ne braéce
by word nor by deed             would not break the treaty,
né þurh inwitsearo             aéfre gemaénden
nor in malicious artifice             ever complain,
ðéah híe hira béaggyfan             banan folgedon
though they their ring-giver's             killer followed,
ðéodenléase,             þá him swá geþearfod wæs·
leaderless,             and were thus forced by necessity;
gyf þonne Frýsna hwylc             frécnen spraéce
if then any Frisian             by audacious speech
ðæs morþorhétes             myndgiend waére
the murderous feud             were to remind (them),
þonne hit sweordes ecg             syððan scolde.
then it by sword's edge             must be thereafter.
Ád wæs geæfned             ond incge gold
The funeral fire was prepared,             and Ingui's gold,
áhæfen of horde·             Here-Scyldinga
raised from the hoard;             the War-Scyldings'
betst beadorinca             wæs on baél gearu·
best battle-man             was ready on the bier;
æt þaém áde wæs             éþgesýne
at the funeral-pyre was             easily seen
swátfáh syrce             swýn ealgylden
the blood-stained mail-shirt,             the        swine all-golden,
eofer írenheard             æþeling manig
the boar hard as iron,             the prince had many
wundum áwyrded·             sume on wæle crungon·
destroyed by wounds;             great men had fallen in slaughter;
hét ðá Hildeburh             æt Hnæfes áde
then Hildeburh ordered             at Hnaef's pier
hire selfre sunu             sweoloðe befæstan,
her own son             committed to the fire,
bánfatu bærnan             ond on baél dóön
the body-vessel burned,      and put on        the bier,
earme on eaxle·             ides gnornode·
the wretched woman at his shoulder,             the lady lamented,
geómrode giddum·             gúðrinc ástáh·
sorrowed with songs;             the warrior was laid out,
wand tó wolcnum             wælfýra maést
spiralled into the clouds             the greatest fire of the slain
hlynode for hláwe·             hafelan multon·
roared before the mound;             heads melted,
bengeato burston             ðonne blód ætspranc,
the wound-gates burst open,             then blood sprang out,
láðbite líces·             líg ealle forswealg,
from the hate-bites of the body;      the        blaze swallowed all up,
gaésta gífrost,             þára ðe þaér gúð fornam
the greediest guest              those who there were taken by battle
béga folces·             wæs hira blaéd scacen.
from both peoples;             their vigour was dispersed.