Béowulf maðelode bearn Ecgþéowes:
Beowulf spoke, the son of Edgetheow:
XXII
'Geþenc nú, se maéra maga Healfdenes
'Think now, glorious kinsman of Half-Dane,
snottra fengel· nú ic eom síðes fús·
wise chieftain, now I am eager for the adventure,
goldwine gumena, hwæt wit géo spraécon:
gold-friend of man, what we spoke of earlier:
gif ic æt þearfe þínre scolde
if I in employment of yours should
aldre linnan· þæt ðú mé á waére
be parted from life, that you for me ever would be,
forðgewitenum on fæder staéle·
having passed on, in the place of a father;
wes þú mundbora mínum magoþegnum
be you hand-bearer to my young retainers,
hondgesellum gif mec hild nime
hand-companions, if battle takes me,
swylce þú ðá mádmas, þé þú mé sealdest,
so too you the treasures, those which you gave me,
Hróðgár léofa, Higeláce onsend·
beloved Hrothgar, send on to Hygelac;
mæg þonne on þaém golde ongitan Géata dryhten,
he then will able to in the gold observe, the lord of the Geats,
geséon sunu Hraédles þonne hé on þæt sinc starað
to perceive, the son of Hrethel, when he on that treasures stares,
þæt ic gumcystum gódne funde
that I one of noble virtues, a good king, had found,
béaga bryttan bréac þonne móste.
dispenser of rings, enjoyed while I could.
Ond þú Hunferð laét ealde láfe
And let Unferth the old heirloom,
wraétlíc waégsweord wídcúðne man
the glorious wave-sword, (let) the widely-known man
heardecg habban· ic mé mid Hruntinge
have that hard-edged (sword); I for myself with Hrunting
dóm gewyrce oþðe mec déað nimeð.'
will gain glory, unless Death takes me.'
Æfter þaém wordum Weder-Géata léod
After these words the man of the Weder-Geats
efste mid elne· nalas andsware
hastened with courage; not in the least for a reply
bídan wolde· brimwylm onfeng
did he wish to await; the surging-lake enfolded
hilderince. Ðá wæs hwíl dæges,
the battle-warrior. Then it was a long part of a day,
aér hé þone grundwong ongytan mehte
ere he the bottom could perceive,
sóna þæt onfunde sé ðe flóda begong
at once she found it out,  she who the floods' expanse,
heorogífre behéold hund misséra
fiercely-ravenous, held a hundred half-years,
grim ond graédig þæt þaér gumena sum
wrathful and greedy  that there one of the humans
ælwihta eard ufan cunnode·
the realm of strange being explored from above;
gráp þá tógéanes· gúðrinc geféng
then she groped towards, seized the warrior
atolan clommum· nó þý aér in gescód
in terrible clasps; Not the sooner she crushed inside
hálan líce· hring útan ymbbearh
his hale body; the ring-mail gave him protection from without,
þæt héo þone fyrdhom ðurhfón ne mihte
that she the soldier-garment could not penetrate,
locene leoðosyrcan láþan fingrum.
the interlocked limb-coat, with her loathsome fingers.
Bær þá séo brimwylf þá héo tó botme cóm
Then the sea-wolf bore, when she had come to the bottom,
hringa þengel tó hofe sínum
the lord of those rings to her court,
swá hé ne mihte  nó hé þæs módig wæs
so he could not  no matter how brave he was
waépna gewealdan ac hine wundra þæs fela
wield his weapon, but him so many bizarre things
swecte on sunde· saédéor monig
smelled in the deep, many sea-beasts
hildetúxum heresyrcan bræc·
with battle-tusks tore at his army-mail,
éhton áglaécan. Ðá se eorl ongeat
the horrors attacked. Then the earl saw
þæt hé níðsele náthwylcum wæs
that he in a hall of hatred  I know not which  was,
þaér him naénig wæter wihte ne sceþede
where not any water him oppressed at all,
né him for hrófsele hrínan ne mehte
nor him, due to the the hall's roof, was not able to reach
faérgripe flódes· fýrléoht geseah,
the sudden onrush of the flood; he saw firelight,
blácne léoman beorhte scínan·
a pale light shining vividly;
ongeat þá se góda grundwyrgenne
then the good man saw the accursèd one of the deep,
merewíf mihtig· mægenraés forgeaf
the mighty mere-wife; he gave a powerful thrust
hildebille· hondswenge ne oftéah
to the battle-bill, did not withhold the swing of his hand,
þæt hire on hafelan hringmaél ágól
so that on her head the ring-marked sang out
graédig gúðléoð· ðá se gist onfand
a greedy war-song; then the guest discovered
þæt se beadoléoma bítan nolde,
that the battle-brand did not wish to bite,
aldre sceþðan ac séo ecg geswác
to crush life, rather the edge failed
ðéodne æt þearfe· ðolode aér fela
the noble in his need; it had endured already many
hondgemóta· helm oft gescær
hand-to-hand encounters, often split helm,
faéges fyrdhrægl· ðá wæs forma síð
the war-garments of the doomed; this was the first time
déorum mádme þæt his dóm álæg.
for the precious treasure that its glory failed.
Eft wæs anraéd, nalas elnes læt
Again was resolute, not at all slackening in courage,
maérða gemyndig maég Hýgláces
mindful of fame the kinsman of Hygelac
wearp ðá wundenmaél wraéttum gebunden
then he threw aside the twisting pattern (sword), adorned with ornaments,
yrre óretta þæt hit on eorðan læg
the angry warrior, so that it lay on the earth,
stíð ond stýlecg· strenge getrúwode,
firm and steel-edged; he trusted to strength,
mundgripe mægenes· swá sceal man doön
his hand-grip of might; so must a man do,
þonne hé æt gúðe gegán þenceð
when he in war intends to gain
longsumne lof· ná ymb his líf cearað.
long-lasting praise; he cares not for his life.
Geféng þá be eaxle  nalas for faéhðe mearn
Grabbed her then by the shoulder  not in the least regretting the feud
Gúð-Géata léod, Grendles módor·
the prince of the War-Geats, Grendel's mother;
brægd þá beadwe heard þá hé gebolgen wæs
the hard man of conflict then heaved, now that he was enraged,
feorhgeníðlan þæt héo on flet gebéah·
the deadly foe, so that she fell to the floor;
héo him eft hraþe handlean forgeald
she again him quickly gave hand-reward
grimman grápum ond him tógéanes féng·
with wrathful grips and clutched him against herself;
oferwearp þá wérigmód wigena strengest
then, weary in spirit, he stumbled, the strongest man,
féþecempa þæt hé on fylle wearð·
warrior on foot, so that he was in a fall;
ofsæt þá þone selegyst ond hyre seax getéah
then she bestrode the guest in her hall, and drew her seax,
brád ond brúnecg· wolde hire bearn wrecan
broad and bright-edged; she wished to avenge her son,
ángan eaferan· him on eaxle læg
only offspring; on his shoulder lay
bréostnet bróden; þæt gebearh féore
woven breast-net; it protected life,
wið ord ond wið ecge ingang forstód.
against point and against edge it withstood entry.
Hæfde ðá forsíðod sunu Ecgþéowes
Then he would have perished, the son of Edgetheow,
under gynne grund Géata cempa
under the yawning ground, the champion of the Geats,
nemne him heaðobyrne helpe gefremede
except that him the war-byrnie provided help,
herenet hearde  ond hálig god
firm army-net  and holy God
gewéold wígsigor· wítig drihten
controlled the war-victory; the wise Lord,
rodera raédend hit on ryht gescéd
the Ruler of the heavens, decided it rightly,
ýðelíce syþðan hé eft ástód.
easily, thereupon he stood up again.