Geseah ðá on searwum sigeéadig bil
He saw then among the arms a victory-blessed bill,
XXIII
ealdsweord eotenisc ecgum þýhtig
an old giantish sword with firm edges,
wigena weorðmynd· þæt wæs waépna cyst
an honour of warriors, it was the choicest weapon,
búton hit wæs máre ðonne aénig mon óðer
but it was more than any other man
tó beaduláce ætberan meahte
to battle-play could carry,
gód ond geatolíc gíganta geweorc·
good and stately, the work of giants;
hé geféng þá fetelhilt· freca Scyldinga
he seized then the ring-hilt, champion of the Scyldings
hréoh ond heorogrim hringmaél gebrægd
wild and furiously battle-fierce, he drew the ring-marked (sword)
aldres orwéna· yrringa slóh
without hope of life, angrily struck,
þæt hire wið halse heard grápode·
so that through her neck it clutched hard,
bánhringas bræc· bil eal ðurhwód
broke bone-rings; the bill passed entirely through
faégne flaéschoman· héo on flet gecrong·
the doomed cloak of flesh; she fell on the floor;
sweord wæs swátig· secg weorce gefeh.
the sword was bloody, the warrior rejoiced in his work.
Líxte se léoma· léoht inne stód
The gleam flashed, the light stood within,
efne swá of hefene hádre scíneð
even as from heaven shines brightly
rodores candel· hé æfter recede wlát·
the sky's candle; he looked about the hall;
hwearf þá be wealle· waépen hafenade
moved along the wall, weapon raised
heard be hiltum Higeláces ðegn
fierce with hilts, Hygelac's thane,
yrre ond anraéd· næs séo ecg fracod
angry and single-minded; nor was that edge useless
hilderince ac hé hraþe wolde
to the battle-man, but he quickly wished
Grendle forgyldan gúðraésa fela
to repay Grendel for the many war-raids
ðára þe hé geworhte tó West-Denum
which he had carried out on the West-Danes
oftor micle ðonne on aénne síð
much more often than on a single venture,
þonne hé Hróðgáres heorðgenéatas
when he Hrothgar's hearth-companions
slóh on sweofote· slaépende fraét
slaughter in their slumber, devoured in their sleep,
folces Denigea fýftýne men
of the folk of the Danes fifteen men,
ond óðer swylc út offerede
and other such had he carried out and off
láðlicu lác· hé him þæs léan forgeald
hideous haul; he paid him the reward of that,
réþe cempa tó ðæs þe hé on ræste geseah
the fierce fighter, in that he saw in repose
gúðwérigne Grendel licgan
war-weary Grendel lying,
aldorléasne swá him aér gescód
lifeless, as he had injured him earlier
hild æt Heorote  hrá wíde sprong
in the conflict at Heorot  the corpse burst wide open,
syþðan hé æfter déaðe drepe þrówade
when it after death suffered a blow,
heorosweng heardne  ond hine þá héafde becearf.
a hard sword-stroke  and then its head he cut off.
Sóna þæt gesáwon snottre ceorlas
Suddenly that saw the wise fellows,
þá ðe mid Hróðgáre on holm wliton·
who with Hrothgar looked at the lake,
þæt wæs ýðgeblond eal gemenged
that was turmoil of waves all stirred up
brim blóde fáh· blondenfeaxe
the water coloured with blood; with blended-hair,
gomele ymb gódne ongeador spraécon
aged, about the good man, together they spoke,
þæt hig þæs æðelinges eft ne wéndon·
that they that noble one did not expect again
þæt hé sigehréðig sécean cóme
that he, triumphing in victory, would come to seek
maérne þéoden· þá ðæs monige gewearð
the glorious ruler; then it many agreed,
þæt hine séo brimwylf ábreoten hæfde.
that the sea-wolf him had destroyed.
Ðá cóm nón dæges· næs ofgéafon
Then came then ninth hour of the day; they abandoned the cape,
hwate Scyldingas· gewát him hám þonon
the brave Scyldings; he went home hence,
goldwine gumena· gistas sécan
the gold-friend of men; the guests looked about
módes séoce ond on mere staredon·
sick at heart, and stared into the mere,
wíston, ond ne wéndon þæt híe heora winedrihten
wished, and did not expect, that they their lord and friend
selfne gesáwon. Þá þæt sweord ongan
himself would see. Then that sword began
æfter heaþoswáte hildegicelum
caused by the gore of battle in icycles of battle,
wígbil wanian· þæt wæs wundra sum
the war-bill to wane; that was a great wonder
þæt hit eal gemealt íse gelícost
that it all melted, so like ice,
ðonne forstes bend fæder onlaéteð·
when frost's bond the Father loosens,
onwindeð waélrápas sé geweald hafað
unwinds water-ropes, who has control
saéla ond maéla· þæt is sóð metod.
of times and seaons; that is the true Creator.
Ne nóm hé in þaém wícum Weder-Géata léod
He did not take into those dwelling, the leader of the Weder-Geats,
máðmaéhta má þéh hé þaér monige geseah
more treasures, though he there saw a great number,
búton þone hafelan ond þá hilt somod
but that head and the hilt as well
since fáge· sweord aér gemealt·
shining with ornament; the sword had already melted,
forbarn bródenmaél· wæs þæt blód tó þæs hát,
burned up the wavy-patterned (blade); that blood was so hot,
ættren ellorgaést sé þaér inne swealt.
the venomous foreign spirit who had perished there inside.
Sóna wæs on sunde sé þe aér æt sæcce gebád
Straightaway he was in the water, he who survived in strife,
wíghryre wráðra wæter úp þurhdéaf·
the enemies' fall in war; he dove up through the water,
waéron ýðgebland eal gefaélsod
the turmoil of waves was all cleared,
éacne eardas þá se ellorgást
the vast regions, where the alien ghosts
oflét lífdagas ond þás laénan gesceaft·
gave up their life-days and this borrowed world;
cóm þá to lande lidmanna helm
he came then to the land, the seafarer's leader,
swíðmód swymman· saéláce gefeah
swimming stout-hearted; he rejoiced in the sea-loot,
mægenbyrþenne, þára þe hé him mid hæfde.
the great burden, which he had with him.
Éodon him þá tógéanes· gode þancodon
They went towards him, thanked God,
ðrýðlíc þegna héap þéodnes gefégon
the mighty band of thanes, they rejoiced for their lord,
þæs þe hí hyne gesundne geséon móston·
that they him sound were able to see;
ðá wæs of þaém hróran helm ond byrne
then the vigorous man was from helm and byrnie
lungre álýsed  lagu drúsade,
quickly loosened  the water grew still,
wæter under wolcnum wældréore fág
the lake under the clouds, stained with the gore of death
férdon forð þonon féþelástum
they fared forth thence along foot-paths
ferhþum fægne· foldweg maéton
happy in their hearts, traversed the trail over the earth,
cúþe straéte· cyningbalde men
the familiar streets; the men, bold as kings,
from þaém holmclife hafelan baéron
from that lake-cliff bore the head
earfoðlíce heora aéghwæþrum
arduously, for all of them,
felamódigra  féower scoldon
full of spirit  four had to
on þaém wælstenge wærcum geferian
on the pole of the slain to carry with difficulty
tó þaém goldsele Grendles héafod
to the gold-hall Grendel's head
oþ ðæt semninga tó sele cómon
until presently they came to the hall,
frome fyrdhwate féowertýne
brave army-keen fourteen
Géata gongan gumdryhten mid·
of the Geats moving, with their lord of men,
módig on gemonge meodowongas træd.
proud in the throng, trod on the plain near the mead-hall.
Ðá cóm in gaän ealdor ðegna
Then came in marching the lord of the thanes,
daédcéne mon dóme gewurþad
the deed-bold man exalted by glory,
hæle hildedéor Hróðgár grétan·
the battle-brave hero, to greet Hrothgar;
þá wæs be feaxe on flet boren
then it was by the hair borne to the floor
Grendles héafod þaér guman druncon,
the head of Grendel, where men were drinking,
egeslíc for eorlum ond þaére idese mid,
dreadful for the earls, and the ladies with them,
wliteséon wraétlíc· weras onsáwon.
a wondrous spectacle; the men stared.