Gewát ðá néosian             syþðan niht becóm
He then went to visit and see              when night came
II
héän húses·             hú hit Hring-Dene
the high house             how it, the Ring-Danes
æfter béorþege             gebún hæfdon·
after the beer-feast,             had occupied;
fand þá ðaér inne             æþelinga gedriht
he found then therein             the nobles' company
swefan æfter symble·             sorge ne cúðon
slumbering after the feast;             they did not know sorrow,
wonsceaft wera·             wiht unhaélo
misery of men;             that damned creature,
grim ond graédig             gearo sóna wæs
grim and greedy,             soon was ready,
réoc ond réþe             ond on ræste genam
savage and cruel             and from their rest seized
þrítig þegna·             þanon eft gewát
thirty thanes;             thence back he went
húðe hrémig      tó        hám faran
proud in plunder             to his home, faring
mid þaére wælfylle             wíca néosan.
with the banquet of bodies             to seek his shelter.
Ðá wæs on úhtan             mid aérdæge
Then was in the dark of dawn             before the day
Grendles gúðcræft             gumum undyrne·
Grendel's war-might             revealed to the men;
þá wæs æfter wiste             wóp up áhafen
then it was after their feasting             they raised up lament
micel morgenswég.             Maére þéoden
in a great morning-cry.             The mighty chieftain,
æþeling aérgod             unblíðe sæt·
the prince, old and good,             sat in sorrow,
þolode ðrýðswýð             þegnsorge dréah
The great mighty one suffered,             anguish of thane-loss   oppressed him
syðþan híe þæs láðan             lást scéawedon,
when they the foe's             tracks beheld,
wergan gástes·             wæs þæt gewin tó strang
of the wicked ghoul;             that strife was too strong,
láð ond longsum.             Næs hit lengra fyrst
loathsome and lingering.             Nor was it a longer time
ac ymb áne niht             eft gefremede
but after a single night             again he perpetuated
morðbeala máre             ond nó mearn fore,
more brutal slaughter,             and it grieved him not,
faéhðe ond fyrene·             wæs tó fæst on þám.
violence and viciousness,             he was too entrenched in these.
Þá wæs éaðfynde             þé him elles hwaér
Then was it easily found,             one who would somewhere else,
gerúmlícor             ræste sóhte
further away,             seek rest:
bed æfter búrum             ðá him gebéacnod wæs
a bed among the bowers,             when it was made clear to him,
gesægd sóðlíce             sweotolan tácne
truly told,      by        an unmistakable token
healðegnes hete·             héold hyne syðþan
the enmity of the hall's occupier;             he held himself then
fyr ond fæstor             sé þaém féonde ætwand.
further and safer,             he who shunned that fiend.
Swá ríxode      ond        wið rihte wan
Thus he ruled             and challenged justice,
ána wið eallum             oð þæt ídel stód
one against all,             until empty stood
húsa sélest·             wæs séo hwíl micel,
that finest of houses;             the time was long
twelf wintra tíd             torn geþolode
the space of twelve winters              that bitter anguish endured
wine Scyldenda,             wéana gehwelcne
the        friend, the shielder,       every woe,
sídra sorga·             forðám secgum wearð
immense miseries;             therefore to men became
ylda bearnum             undyrne cúð,
to sons of men,             clearly known
gyddum geómore             þætte Grendel wan
in mournful ballads,             that Grendel had contended
hwíle wið Hróþgár·             heteníðas wæg
long against Hrothgar,             sustained fierce enmity,
fyrene ond faéhðe             fela misséra,
felony and feud,             for many seasons
singále sæce·             sibbe ne wolde
continual strife;             he did not want peace
wið manna hwone             mægenes Deniga,
with any man             of the Danish contingent,
feorhbealo feorran,             féa þingian
to desist in life-destruction,             to settle it with payment,
né þaér naénig witena             wénan þorfte
none of the counsellors             had any need to hope for
beorhtre bóte             tó banan folmum
noble recompense             from the slayer's hands,
ac se aéglaéca             éhtende wæs
but the wretch             was persecuting
deorc déaþscua             duguþe ond geogoþe
the dark death-shade              warriors old and young;
seomade ond syrede·             sinnihte héold
he lay in wait and set snares,             in the endless night he held
mistige móras·             men ne cunnon
the misty moors;             men do not know
hwyder helrúnan             hwyrftum scríþað.
where such hellish enigmas      slink in their        haunts.
Swá fela fyrena             féond mancynnes
Thus many offences             that foe of mankind,
atol ángengea             oft gefremede,
that terrible lone traveller,             often committed,
heardra hýnða·             Heorot eardode
hard humiliations;             he dwelt in Heorot,
sincfáge sel             sweartum nihtum
the richly-adorned hall,             in the black nights
nó hé þone gifstól             grétan móste,
by        no means he the gift-throne      was compelled to        approach respectfully,
máþðum for metode,             né his myne wisse
the        treasure, by the Maker,      nor did he feel love for        it
Þæt wæs wraéc micel             wine Scyldinga,
That was great misery             for the Friend of the Scyldings,
módes brecða.             Monig oft gesæt
a breaking of his spirit.             Many often sat
ríce tó rúne·             raéd eahtedon·
the mighty at counsel;             pondered a plan,
hwæt swíðferhðum             sélest waére
what by strong-minded men      would be best,
wið faérgryrum             tó gefremmanne·
against the sudden horror,             to do;
hwílum híe gehéton             æt hærgtrafum
sometimes they pledged             at holy temples
wígweorþunga·             wordum baédon
sacred honouring,             in words bid
þæt him gástbona             géoce gefremede
that them the demon-slayer      would offer succour
wið þéodþréaum·             swylc wæs þéaw hyra·
from the plight of the people;             such was their habit:
haéþenra hyht·             helle gemundon
the hope of heathens;             on hell they pondered
in módsefan·             metod híe ne cúþon
in the depths of their hearts;             the Creator they did not know,
daéda démend·             ne wiston híe drihten god
the Judge of deeds,             they were not aware of the Lord God,
né híe húru heofena helm             herian ne cúþon
nor yet they the Helm of the Heavens      were able to        honour,
wuldres waldend.             Wá bið þaém ðe sceal
Glory's Wielder.             Woe be to him who must,
þurh slíðne níð             sáwle bescúfan
through dire terror,             thrust his soul
in fýres fæþm,             frófre ne wénan,
into fire's embrace;             hope not for relief,
wihte gewendan·             wél bið þaém þe mót
or to change at all;             well be he who may
æfter déaðdæge             drihten sécean
after death-day             seek the Lord
ond tó fæder fæþmum             freoðo wilnian.
and in his Father's arms             yearn towards Nirvana.