Him ðá        gegiredan    Géata léode
Then for him        prepared     the people of the Geats
XLIII
ád on        eorðan    unwáclícne
a pyre on the        earth,     not trifling,
helmum        behongen    hildebordum
hung with        helmets,    with battle-shields,
beorhtum        byrnum    swá hé béna wæs·
with bright        byrnies,    as he had requested;
álegdon ðá        tómiddes     maérne þéoden
they laid then in the        midst    the famed chieftain,
hæleð        híofende    hláford léofne·
the lamenting        heroes,     their belovèd lord;
ongunnon þá on        beorge    baélfýra maést
then began on the        barrow     the greatest bale-fire,
wígend        weccan·    wuduréc ástáh
the warriors to        kindle;    wood-smoke arose,
sweart ofer        swioðole    swógende lég
swarthy over the        heat,     the roaring flame
wópe        bewunden     windblond gelæg
woven with        weeping     the tumult of winds lay still
oð þæt hé ðá        bánhús     gebrocen hæfde
until it the bone-house    had broken
hát on        hreðre·    higum unróte
hot at heart;            despairing in their hearts
módceare        maéndon    mondryhtnes cwealm·
they bemoaned their        grief,    their liege-lord's death;
swylce        giómorgyd    Géatisc ánméowle
so too a death-dirge            a solitary Geatish woman
Bíowulfe        brægd    bundenheorde
sang        sorgcearig·    saélðe geneahhe
she sang        sorrowful,     earnestly of fortune
þæt hío hyre        hearmdagas    hearde ondréde
that she for herself days of        harm    fiercely dreaded,
wælfylla        worn    werudes egesan
of multitude of        slaughter-feasts,    terror of troops,
hýðo ond        hæftnýd.    Heofon réce swealg·
rapine and        bondage.     Heaven swallowed the smoke;
geworhton        ðá    Wedra léode
then wrought    the        Wederas' people
hlaéo on hóe    sé        wæs héah ond brád
a barrow on the        hill,    it was high and broad,
waéglíðendum    wíde gesýne
for wave-farers     widely        visible,
ond        betimbredon    on týn dagum
and they        constructed    in ten days
beadurófes        bécn·    bronda láfe
the war-chief's        beacon,     the leavings of the fire,
wealle        beworhton    swá hyt weorðlícost
with a wall they        encircled,    as it most worthily
foresnotre        men    findan mihton·
the very wisest        men     could devise;
hí on beorg        dydon    bég ond siglu
they placed in the        barrow    rings and brooches,
eall swylce        hyrsta    swylce on horde aér
all such        trappings,    as before from the hoard
níðhédige        men    genumen hæfdon·
hostile men    had        taken away;
forléton eorla        gestréon     eorðan healdan
the treasure of heroes they        let    the earth hold,
gold on        gréote    þaér hit nú gén lifað
gold in the gritty        soil,     where it now still lives,
eldum swá        unnyt    swá hyt aérer wæs.
as useless to        men    as it was before.
Þá ymbe hlaéw        riodan,     hildedéore
Then around the mound        rode    the battle-brave
æþelinga        bearn    ealra twelfa·
sons of        nobles,    twelve in all,
woldon cearge        cwíðan    kyning maénan,
they wished to bewail their        sorrow,    to mourn their king,
wordgyd        wrecan    ond ymb wer sprecan·
to pronounce        elegy,    and speak about the man;
eahtodan        eorlscipe    ond his ellenweorc
they praised his heroic        deeds    and his works of courage,
duguðum        démdon.    Swá hit gedéfe bið
exalted his        majesty.     As it is fitting,
þæt mon his        winedryhten    wordum herge·
that one his friend and        lord    honours in words,
ferhðum        fréoge    þonne hé forð scile
cherish in one's        spirit,     when he must forth
of líchaman            laéded weorðan·
from his body    be        led;
swá        begnornodon    Géata léode
thus        bemourned    the people of the Geats
hláfordes        hryre,     heorðgenéatas:
their lord's        fall,    his hearth-companions:
cwaédon þæt hé        waére     wyruldcyning
they said that he was,             of all kings of the world,
manna        mildust    ond monðwaérust
the most generous of        men,    and the most gracious,
léodum        líðost    ond lofgeornost.
the most protective of his        people,    and the most eager for honour.