Hunferð maþelode Ecgláfes bearn
Unferth spoke, the son of Edgelaf,
VIII
þe æt fótum sæt fréan Scyldinga·
who sat at the feet of the lord of the Scyldings;
onband beadurúne  wæs him Béowulfes síð
he unbound battle-runes  for him was the venture of Beowulf,
módges merefaran micel æfþunca
brave seafarer's, a source of great displeasure,
forþon þe hé ne úþe þæt aénig óðer man
because he did not grant that any other man
aéfre maérða þon má middangeardes
ever glorious deeds the more on middle-earth
gehédde under heofenum þonne hé sylfa :
heeded under the heavens than he himself :
'Eart þú sé Béowulf sé þe wið Brecan wunne
'Are you the Beowulf, who contested against Breca
on sídne saé ymb sund flite?
on the broad sea, contended around the ocean-sound?
Ðaér git for wlence wada cunnedon
Where you for bravado tempted the waters
ond for dolgilpe on déop wæter
and for a foolish boast in deep sea
aldrum néþdon né inc aénig mon
risked your lives, you no man
né léof né láð beléan mihte
neither friend nor foe  could dissuade
sorhfullne síð þa git on sund réön·
from that sorrowful jaunt, when you rowed into the strait;
þaér git éagorstréam earmum þehton·
there you sea-currents in your arms embraced,
maéton merestraéta mundum brugdon·
traversed the ocean-roads, with hands wove,
glidon ofer gársecg· geofon ýþum
gliding over the sea; the ocean in waves
wéol wintrys wylm· git on wæteres aéht
welled, in winter's swells; you in the water's grasp
seofon niht swuncon· hé þé æt sunde oferflát·
toiled for seven nights; he got the better of you on the sea,
hæfde máre mægen. Þá hine on morgentíd
he had more might. Then he in the morning
on Heaþo-Raémes holm up ætbær·
on Heatho-Reams' shore was cast up by the sea;
ðonon hé gesóhte swaésne éðel,
thence he sought his own homeland,
léof his léodum, lond Brondinga
dear to his people, the land of the Brondings,
freoðoburh fægere þaér hé folc áhte
the fair citadel, he had folk there,
burh ond béagas· béot eal wið þé
boroughs and rings; the entire boast with you
sunu Béanstánes sóðe gelaéste.
the son of Beanstan truly fulfilled.
Ðonne wéne ic tó þé wyrsan geþingea
I expect then for you worse results,
ðéah þú heaðoraésa gehwaér dohte
though you in war-assaults everywhere prevailed,
grimre gúðe gif þú Grendles dearst
grim combat, if you for Grendel dare
nihtlongne fyrst néän bídan.'
the space of a night nearby wait.'
Béowulf maþelode bearn Ecgþéowes:
Beowulf spoke, the son of Edgetheow:
'Hwæt, þú worn fela, wine mín Hunferð,
'Listen, you a great deal  Unferth, my friend,
béore druncen ymb Brecan spraéce·
drunk on beer  have spoken about Breca,
sægdest from his síðe. Sóð ic talige
told of his journey. Truth I claim
þæt ic merestrengo máran áhte
that I sea-strength greater had,
earfeþo on ýþum ðonne aénig óþer man·
hardship on the waves, than any other man;
wit þæt gecwaédon cnihtwesende
we had it agreed, being lads,
ond gebéotedon  waéron bégen þá git
and vowed  being both then still
on geogoðféore  þæt wit on gársecg út
in the years of youth  that we out on the ocean
aldrum néðdon ond þæt geæfndon swá.
our lives would risk, and thus that we did.
Hæfdon swurd nacod þá wit on sund réön
We had naked swords when we rowed on the ocean-sound,
heard on handa: wit unc wið hronfixas
hard in our hands: we ourselves against whales
werian þóhton· nó hé wiht fram mé
planned to defend; not a whit from me was he
flódýþum feor fléotan meahte
on the sea-waves far able to float,
hraþor on holme· nó ic fram him wolde·
swifter on water, nor did I wish to part from him;
ðá wit ætsomne on saé waéron
then we together were on the sea,
fíf nihta fyrst oþ þæt unc flód tódráf
for the space of five nights, until the sea-waves drove us apart,
wado weallende wedera cealdost
the water welling, the coldest of weathers,
nípende niht ond norþanwind
the darkening night and the north wind
heaðogrim ondhwearf· hréo waéron ýþa·
fierce turned against us; wild were the waves;
wæs merefixa mód onhréred·
then was the sea-fishes' wrath roused;
þaér mé wið láðum lícsyrce mín
there me against foes my body-shirt
heard hondlocen helpe gefremede·
strong and hand-linked, did me help,
beadohrægl bróden on bréostum læg
my battle-garment braided lay on my breast,
golde gegyrwed· mé tó grunde téah
adorned with gold; to the bottom of the sea I was drawn
fáh féondscaða· fæste hæfde
by the hostile foe-scather, it held me fast,
grim on grápe· hwæþre mé gyfeþe wearð
cruel in grip; however, to it was granted
þæt ic áglaécan orde geraéhte
that I the monster reached with my point,
hildebille· heaþoraés fornam
with battle-bill; in the battle-rush I destroyed
mihtig meredéor þurh míne hand.
the mighty sea-beast with my hand.