Sé ðæs léodhryres léan gemunde
He for the prince's fall requital remembered
XXXIIII
uferan dógrum· Éadgilse wearð
in later days, to Eadgils he became
féasceaftum fréond· folce gestépte
a friend in his plight; with men he supported
ofer saé síde sunu Óhteres
over the wide sea the son of Ohtere,
wigum ond waépnum· hé gewræc syððan
with warriors and weapons; he had vengeance then
cealdum cearsiðum· cyning ealdre binéat:
in cold grief-bringing ventures, he deprived the king of his life:
swá hé níða gehwane genesen hæfde
so he each of the enmities had survived,
slíðra geslyhta, sunu Ecgðíowes,
dire conflicts, the son of Ecgetheow,
ellenweorca oð ðone ánne dæg
deeds of courage, until the one day,
þé hé wið þám wyrme gewegan sceolde.
when he with the serpent must struggle.
Gewát þá twelfa sum torne gebolgen
Then he went, one of twelve, swollen with anger,
dryhten Géata, dracan scéawian·
the lord of the Geats, to behold the dragon;
hæfde þá gefrúnen hwanan sío faéhð árás
he had heard then whence this feud arose,
bealoníð biorna: him tó bearme cwóm
wicked hostility for men: to his bosom came
máðþumfæt maére, þurh ðæs meldan hond·
the precious vessel, through the informer's hand;
sé wæs on ðám ðréate þreottéoða secg
he was in that group the thirteenth man,
sé ðæs orleges ór onstealde
he who this strife's origin brought about,
hæft hygegiómor· sceolde héan ðonon
the gloomy-minded captive; he was obliged, humbly, thence
wong wísian· hé ofer willan gíong
to lead the way to the place; he went against his will
tó ðæs ðe hé eorðsele ánne wisse
to where the earth-hall he alone knew,
hlaéw under hrúsan holmwylme néh
the cairn under the ground near the surging of the sea,
ýðgewinne· sé wæs innan full
the struggle of the waves; it was full inside
wraétta ond wíra· weard unhíore
of jewels and intricate metal-work; an unpleasant guard,
gearo gúðfreca goldmáðmas héold
ready, eager war-fighter held golden treasures
eald under eorðan· næs þæt ýðe céap
old under the earth; that was not an easy bargain,
tó gegangenne gumena aénigum.
to obtain for any man.
Gesæt ðá on næsse níðheard cyning·
Then on the headland sat the violence-hard king,
þenden haélo ábéad heorðgenéatum
while prosperity bid to his hearth-companions,
goldwine Géata· him wæs geómor sefa
the gold-friend of the Geats; in him his heart was sad,
waéfre ond wælfús, wyrd ungemete néah
restless and slaughter-eager, fate all too near
sé ðone gomelan grétan sceolde,
which the old man must greet,
sécean sáwle hord, sundur gedaélan
seeking the treasure of his soul, sever asunder
líf wið líce· nó þon lange wæs
life from limb; it was not for long then
feorh æþelinges flaésce bewunden.
the nobleman's life would be wound in his flesh.
Bíowulf maþelade bearn Ecgðéowes:
Beowulf spoke, the son of Edgetheow:
'Fela ic on giogoðe gúðraésa genæs
'In youth I many war-storms survived,
orleghwíla· ic þæt eall gemon·
in battle-times; I remember all of that;
ic wæs syfanwintre þá mec sinca baldor
I was seven-winters (old) when me the lord of treasure,
fréawine folca æt mínum fæder genam·
the lord and friend of the folk, took from my father;
héold mec ond hæfde Hréðel cyning·
held and had me King Hrethel,
geaf mé sinc ond symbel· sibbe gemunde·
gave me treasure and feast, recalled kinship;
næs ic him tó life láðra ówihte
I was not by him in life less in aught,
beorn in burgum þonne his bearna hwylc
a man in citadel, than each of his own sons,
Herebeald ond Hæðcyn oððe Hygelác mín.
Herebeald and Haethcyn or my Hygelac.
Wæs þám yldestan ungedéfelice
For the eldest was, unfittingly,
maéges daédum morþorbed strëd
by a kinsman's deeds a death-bed strewed,
syððan hyne Hæðcyn of hornbogan
when him Haethcyn from a horn-bow
his fréawine fláne geswencte·
his friend and lord struck down with an arrow,
miste mercelses ond his maég ofscét
missed his mark and his kinsman shot dead,
bróðor óðerne blódigan gáre·
the one brother the other with a bloody bolt;
þæt wæs feohléas gefeoht fyrenum gesyngad,
that was an irreparable fight, grieviously wronged,
hreðre hygeméðe· sceolde hwæðre swá þéah
heart-wearying in the breast; yet must though
æðeling unwrecen ealdres linnan.
the noble unavenged be parted from life.
Swá bið geómorlíc gomelum ceorle
In the same way it is tragic for an old man
tó gebídanne þæt his byre ríde
to abide that his son rides
giong on galgan: þonne hé gyd wrece,
young on the gallows: then he utters a dirge,
sárigne sang þonne his sunu hangað
a sorrowing song, that his son hangs
hrefne tó hróðre ond hé him helpan ne mæg
for the pleasure of the raven, and he can not him help,
eald ond infród aénige gefremman·
old and experienced, any provide;
symble bið gemyndgad morna gehwylce
ever is reminded each morning,
eaforan ellorsíð· óðres ne gýmeð
of the other-world journey of his son; another he heeds not
tó gebídanne burgum in innan
to wait for within the strongholds,
yrfeweardas þonne se án hafað
guardian of inheritance, when the one he has
þurh déaðes nýd daéda gefondad·
through Death's compulsion experienced deeds;
gesyhð sorhcearig on his suna búre
he sees, sad and sorrowful, in his son's dwelling
wínsele wéstne windge reste
a wine-hall wasted, a wind-swept resting place
réote berofene· rídend swefað
bereft of joy; the riders sleep,
hæleð in hoðman· nis þaér hearpan swég
heroes hidden in graves; there is not sound of harp,
gomen in geardum swylce ðaér iú waéron.
revelry in the courts, such as long ago there was.