Nolde eorla hléo aénige þinga
The protector of earls had no wish for any reason
XII
þone cwealmcuman cwicne forlaétan
the murderous guest to release alive,
né his lífdagas léoda aénigum
nor his life-days to any people
nytte tealde. Þær genehost brægd
counted as advantage. There many brandished
eorl Béowulfes ealde láfe·
warriors of Beowulf, old heirlooms,
wolde fréadrihtnes feorh ealgian
they wished prince-lord's life defend,
maéres þéodnes ðaér híe meahton swá·
the legendary leader's, if they could do so;
híe þæt ne wiston þá híe gewin drugon
they did not know that, when they joined the fray,
heardhicgende hildemecgas
the bold-minded battle-men,
ond on healfa gehwone héawan þóhton,
and on each side thought to heaw,
sáwle sécan: þone synscaðan
to seek the soul: that the sin-scather
aénig ofer eorþan írenna cyst
any on earth, of the choicest of irons,
gúðbilla nán grétan nolde
of war-bills, none, could not at all greet him
ac hé sigewaépnum forsworen hæfde
but he victory-weapons had forsworn,
ecga gehwylcre. Scolde his aldorgedál
every blade-edge. His life-severing was bound to
on ðaém dæge þysses lífes
on that day in this life
earmlíc wurðan ond se ellorgást
be wretched, and the alien-spirit
on féonda geweald feor síðian·
into the administration of fiends would journey far away;
ðá þæt onfunde sé þe fela aéror
then he found, he who before many,
módes myrðe manna cynne
miseries in his mind, on mankind
fyrene gefremede  he, fág wið god
atrocities committed  he, who fought with God
þæt him se líchoma laéstan nolde
that him his body-shell would not obey,
ac hine se módega maég Hygeláces
but him the daring kinsman of Hygelac
hæfde be honda· wæs gehwæþer óðrum
had by the hand; each was by the other
lifigende láð· lícsár gebád
loathed while living; body-pain he felt,
atol aéglaéca· him on eaxle wearð
the awful ogre; on his shoulder was
syndolh sweotol· seonowe onsprungon·
a great wound apparent, sinows sprang asunder,
burston bánlocan· Béowulfe wearð
bone-locks burst; to Beowulf was
gúðhréð gyfeþe· scolde Grendel þonan
war-glory given; thence Grendel had to
feorhséoc fléön under fenhleoðu,
flee sick unto death under the hills of the fen,
sécean wynléas wíc· wiste þé geornor
to seek his joyless abode; he knew it more surely
þæt his aldres wæs ende gegongen
that was his life's end arrived,
dógera dægrím. Denum eallum wearð
the day-count of his days. For the Danes were all,
æfter þám wælraése willa gelumpen:
after that slaughter-storm, wishes come to pass:
hæfde þá gefaélsod sé þe aér feorran cóm
he had then cleansed, he who had before come from afar,
snotor ond swýðferhð sele Hróðgáres,
shrewd and strong-minded, the hall of Hrothgar,
genered wið níðe· nihtweorce gefeh
rescued from ruin; in his night's work he rejoiced,
ellenmaérþum· hæfde Éast-Denum
in valour from great deeds; to the East-Danes had
Géatmecga léod gilp gelæsted·
the Geatmen's leader, his oath fulfilled;
swylce oncýþðe ealle gebétte
so too anguish all remedied,
inwidsorge þé híe aér drugon
grievous sorrow, that they had ere endured,
ond for þréanýdum þolian scoldon
and in hard distress had to suffer,
torn unlýtel· þæt wæs tácen sweotol
no small misery; that was a clear sign,
syþðan hildedéor hond álegde
when the battle-bold one the hand placed,
earm ond eaxle  þaér wæs eal geador
arm and shoulder  there was all together
Grendles grápe  under géapne hróf.
the grip of Grendel  under the gaping roof.