Straét wæs stánfáh·             stíg wísode
The street was paved with stones,             the path guided
V
gumum ætgædere·             gúðbyrne scán
the men together;             war-byrnie shone
heard hondlocen             hringíren scír
harsh, linked by hand,             ring-iron glittering,
song in searwum·             þá híe tó sele furðum
they sang in their arms,             as they to the hall straight
in hyra gryregeatwum             gangan cwómon·
in their grim gear             came marching;
setton saéméþe             síde scyldas
they set down, sea-weary,             their wide shields,
rondas regnhearde             wið þæs recedes weal·
the rims wondrous-hard             against the wall of the hall,
bugon þá tó bence·             byrnan hringdon
and bent down then to a bench;             corslets rang
gúðsearo gumena·             gáras stódon
the war-clothes of warriors;             spears stood,
saémanna searo             samod ætgædere
seamen's weapons,             all together,
æscholt ufan graég·             wæs se írenþréat
silvery above a grove of ash;             the iron-clad troop was
waépnum gewurþad·             þá ðaér wlonc hæleð
honoured in weapons;             then a proud noble
óretmecgas             æfter hæleþum frægn:
the elite soldiers             asked about the heroes:
'Hwanon ferigeað gé             faétte scyldas
'Whence ferry you             plated shields,
graége syrcan             ond grímhelmas
steel-hued shirts of mail             and masked-helms,
heresceafta héap?             Ic eom Hróðgáres
this host of army-shafts?             I am Hrothgar's
ár ond ombiht·             ne seah ic elþéodige
herald and officer;             I have not seen from a foreign land
þus manige men             módiglícran·
this many men             looking braver in spirit;
wén' ic þæt gé for wlenco             nalles for wraécsíðum
I expect that you from valour,             not from exile,
ac for higeþrymmum             Hróðgár sóhton.'
but from greatness of heart             have sought out Hrothgar.'
Him þá ellenróf             andswarode
Then him the renowned one             answered
wlanc Wedera léod             word æfter spræc
that proud prince of the Wedera nation       spoke thereafter        words,
heard under helme:             'Wé synt Higeláces
severe beneath his helmet:             'We are Hygelac's
béodgenéatas·             Béowulf is mín nama·
companions at table;             Beowulf  is my name;
wille ic ásecgan             sunu Healfdenes
I wish to proclaim to             the son of Half-Dane,
maérum þéodne             min aérende
that famed sovereign              my errand
aldre þínum             gif hé ús geunnan wile
to your lord,             if he wishes to grant us
þæt wé hine swá gódne             grétan móton.'
that we him, the virtuous one,             might greet.'
Wulfgár maþelode              þæt wæs Wendla léod·
Wulfgar began to speak              he was the Wendels' leader,
wæs his módsefa             manegum gecýðed
his courage was             well-known to many,
wíg ond wísdóm :             'Ic þæs wine Deniga
war-skill and wisdom :             'I this from friend of the Danes,
fréan Scildinga             frínan wille
lord of the Scyldings,             will inquire,
béaga bryttan·             swá þú béna eart·
from the giver of rings,              as you are petitioners
þéoden maérne             ymb þínne síð
from that famed sovereign             about your quest,
ond þé þá andsware             aédre gecýðan
and to you the answer             promptly make known
ðe mé se góda             ágifan þenceð.'
which to me the virtuous one             sees fit to give.'
Hwearf þá hrædlíce             þaér Hróðgár sæt
He turned then quickly             to where Hrothgar sat,
eald ond anhár             mid his eorla gedriht·
old and very grey,             amid his company of earls;
éode ellenróf             þæt hé for eaxlum gestód
he strode grandly             so that he stood by the shoulders
Deniga fréän:             cúþe hé duguðe þéaw·
of the Danes' lord:             he knew the custom of veteran-warriors;
Wulfgár maðelode             tó his winedrihtne:
Wulfgar made this speech             to his friend and lord:
'Hér syndon geferede             feorran cumene
'Here have ventured,             come from far away,
ofer geofenes begang             Géata léode·
over the expanse of the sea,             men of the Geats;
þone yldestan             óretmecgas
the eldest one             of these elite warriors
Béowulf nemnað·             hý bénan synt
is called Beowulf;             they are asking
þæt híe, þéoden min,             wið þé móton
that they, my lord,             with you might
wordum wrixlan·             nó ðú him wearne getéoh
exchange words;             give them not refusal
ðínra gegncwida,             glædman Hróðgár·
from your answers,             gracious Hrothgar;
hý on wíggetáwum             wyrðe þinceað
they by their war-gear             seem worthy
eorla geæhtlan·             húru se aldor déah
of the esteem of nobles;             indeed, the prince is powerful,
sé þaém heaðorincum             hider wísade.'
who the warriors             led hither.'