Sigon þá tó slaépe·             sum sáre angeald
They sank then into sleep;             one paid sorely
XVIIII
æfenræste      swá        him ful oft gelamp
for his evening rest,             as had quite often happened,
siþðan goldsele             Grendel warode·
when the gold-hall             Grendel warded,
unriht æfnde             oþ þæt ende becwóm,
inflict wrong             until the end came,
swylt æfter synnum.             Þæt gesýne wearþ
death for crimes.             That became manifest,
wídcúþ werum             þætte wrecend þá gýt
widely known by men,             that an avenger still
lifde æfter láþum             lange þráge
lived after the misfortunes,             for a long time
æfter gúðceare             Grendles módor
after the war-trouble,             Grendel's mother,
ides áglaécwíf             yrmþe gemunde
lady troll-wife,      remembered        misery,
sé þe wæteregesan             wunian scolde
she who the dreadful water             had to inhabit,
cealde stréamas            siþðan camp him wearð
the cold currents,             after strife arose through him,
tó ecgbanan             ángan bréþer
a sword-slayer to             an only brother,
fæderenmaége·             hé þá fág gewát
father's kin;             he went then stained,
morþre gemearcod             mandréam fléön·
marked by the murder,             fled human pleasures,
wésten warode.             Þanon wóc fela
lived in the wilds.             Then awoke many
geósceaftgásta·             wæs þaéra Grendel sum,
fated spirits;             Grendel was one of these,
heorowearh hetelíc·             sé æt Heorote fand
the hateful sword-outlaw,             who found at Heorot
wæccendne wer             wíges bidan·
a watching man             biding for battle;
þaér him áglaéca             ætgráepe wearð·
there with him the troll             came at close grips;
hwæþre hé gemunde             mægenes strenge
yet he remembered      the great        strength,
gimfæste gife             ðe him god sealde
generous gift,             which God gave him,
ond him tó anwaldan             áre gelýfde
and he on the One-Ruler's             favour relied,
frófre ond fultum·             ðý hé þone féond ofercwóm·
comfort and support;             by this he overcame the fiend,
gehnaégde helle gást·             þá hé héan gewát
subdued the spirit of hell;             then wretched he went,
dréame bedaéled             déaþwíc séön,
deprived of joy,             to see his place of death,
mancynnes féond.             Ond his módor þá gýt
that foe of mankind.             And his mother even now,
gífre ond galgmód             gegán wolde
greedy and gloomy-hearted             wished to go forth,
sorhfulne síð,             sunu déoð wrecan·
a sorrowful journey,             to avenge her son's death;
cóm þá to Heorote             ðaér Hring-Dene
she came then to Heorot,             where the Ring-Danes
geond þæt sæld swaéfun·             þá ðaér sóna wearð
slept throught the hall;             then there at once came about
edhwyrft eorlum             siþðan inne fealh
the earl's reversal of fortune,             when inside passed
Grendles módor·             wæs se gryre laéssa
Grendel's mother;             the horror was less
efne swá micle             swá bið mægþa cræft
by even so much,             as is maid's strength,
wíggryre wífes             bewaépned men
the war-violence of woman              from an armed man,
þonne heoru bunden             hamere geþuren
when adorned blade,             by hammer forged,
sweord swáte fáh             swín ofer helme
sword stained with blood              the boar-crest
ecgum dyhttig             andweard scireð.
by edges firm,             the opposing (helmet) is sheared.
Þá wæs on healle             heardecg togen
Then in the hall was drawn a        hard-edged
sweord ofer setlum,             sídrand manig
sword above the seats,             many a broad bossed-shield
hafen handa fæst·             helm ne gemunde
held fast in hand;             helmet was not heeded,
byrnan síde      þá        hine se bróga angeat·
(nor) broad byrnie,             when the horror perceived him;
héo wæs on ofste·             wolde út þanon,
she was in haste,             wanted out of there,
féore beorgan             þá héo onfunden wæs·
to protect her life,             when she was discovered;
hraðe héo æþelinga             ánne hæfde
quickly she a noble             one had
fæste befangen·             þá héo tó fenne gang·
seized tightly,             then she went to the fen;
sé wæs Hróþgáre             hæleþa léofost
he was to Hrothgar             the best-loved hero
on gesíðes hád             be saém twéonum
in the retinue's rank             between the two seas
ríce randwiga             þone ðe héo on ræste ábréat
mighty shield-warrior,             whom she ripped from his rest,
blaédfæstne beorn              næs Béowulf ðaér
the glorious man              Beowulf was not there,
ac wæs óþer in             aér geteohhod
but was in the other lodging             assigned earlier
æfter máþðumgife             maérum Géate
after the treasure-giving             to the mighty Geat
hréam wearð in Heorote·             héo under heolfre genam
a cry was in Heorot;             she took from its gore
cúþe folme·             cearu wæs geníwod,
a well-known arm;             sorrow was renewed,
geworden in wícun·             ne wæs þæt gewrixle til
it returned to their dwellings;             that exchange was not good,
þæt híe on bá healfa             bicgan scoldon
which they on both sides             were obliged to pay for
fréonda féorum·             þá wæs fród cyning
with the lives of friends;             then was the wise king,
hár hilderinc             on hréonmóde
the grey battle-man,             in a troubled spirit,
syðþan hé aldorþegn             unlyfigendne
when he the lordly thane             unliving,
þone déorestan             déadne wisse.
the dearest one,             knew was dead.
Hraþe wæs tó búre             Béowulf fetod
Quickly to the bower was             Beowulf fetched
sigoréadig secg·             samod aérdæge
the victorious warrior;             at day-break
éode eorla sum             æþele cempa
the notable earl went              noble champion
self mid gesíðum             þaér se snotera bád
himself with his companions             where the        wise one awaited
hwæþre him Alfwalda             aéfre wille
whether for him the Ruler of Elves      ever would        wish,
æfter wéaspelle             wyrpe gefremman·
after the news of woe,             to bring about a change for the better;
gang ðá æfter flóre             fyrdwyrðe man
then over the floor went             the war-worthy man
mid his handscale              healwudu dynede
with his crowd of companions              the wood of the hall resounded
þæt hé þone wísan             wordum hnægde
he the wise (king)             humbled with words:
fréan Ingwina·             frægn gif him waére
the lord of the Ingwins              asked if it had been for him,
æfter néodlaðu             niht getaése.
according to his hopes,      a pleasing        night.