Ðá ic snúde gefrægn sunu Wíhstánes
Then I heard swiftly the son of Weohstan,
XXXVIII
æfter wordcwydum wundum dryhtne
after the word-speech the wounded lord,
hýran heaðosíocum, hringnet beran
listened to the battle-sick one, bore a net of rings,
brogdne beadusercean under beorges hróf.
woven battle-shirt under the barrow's roof.
Geseah ðá sigehréðig þá hé bí sesse géong
He saw then victorious, when he went by the seat,
magoþegnmódig máððumsigla fealo,
the spirited young thane, many precious jewels,
gold glitinian grunde getenge
glittering gold close to the ground,
wundur on wealle ond þæs wyrmes denn
wonders on the wall, and the wyrm's den,
ealdes úhtflogan, orcas stondan
the old twilight-flier, beakers standing,
fyrnmanna fatu feormendléase
the vessels of men of old lacking a burnisher,
hyrstum behrorene· þaér wæs helm monig
stripped of adornments; there was a multitude of helms
eald ond ómig, earmbéaga fela
old and rusty, many arm-rings
searwum gesaéled  sinc éaðe mæg
cleverly fastened  treasure easily may,
gold on grunde gumcynnes gehwone
gold in the ground, any one of mankind
oferhígian hýde sé ðe wylle
overpower, hide he who will
swylce hé siomian geseah segn eallgylden
also he saw hanging a standard all-golden
héah ofer horde, hondwundra maést
high over the hoard, the greatest of hand-wrought wonders,
gelocen leoðocræftum· of ðám léoman stód
linked with skill of hands; from it light issued,
þæt hé þone grundwong ongitan meahte,
so that he on the ground could perceive,
wraéte giondwlítan· næs ðæs wyrmes þaér
look over the ornament; there was not of the wyrm
onsýn aénig ac hyne ecg fornam.
any appearance, for him the blade-edge took.
Ðá ic on hlaéwe gefrægn hord réafian
Then I heard in the mound the hoard plundered,
eald enta geweorc ánne mannan,
old work of giants, one man,
him on bearm hlódon bunan ond discas
him on his bosom loaded goblets and plates
sylfes dóme segn éac genóm
of his own judgement he also took the banner,
béacna beorhtost· bill aér gescód
the brightest beacon; the bill had already wounded
ecg wæs íren  ealdhláfordes
the edge was iron  of that old lord
þám ðára máðma mundbora wæs
him who the treasures' protector was
longe hwíle· lígegesan wæg
for a long while; the fire-terror had endured
hátne for horde hioroweallende
hot for sake of the hoard, fiercely welling up
middelnihtum oð þæt hé morðre swealt.
in the middle of nights until he died in violence.
Ár wæs on ofoste eftsíðes georn
The messenger was in haste, eager for return,
frætwum gefyrðred· hyne fyrwet bræc
urged on by treasures; curiosity burst in him,
hwæðer collenferð cwicne gemétte
whether bold-hearted he would meet alive
in ðám wongstede Wedra þéoden
in that place, the chief of the Wederas
ellensíocne þaér hé hine aér forlét·
ill in strength, where he had left him earlier;
hé ðá mid þám máðmum maérne þíoden
he then with that treasures to the glorious chieftain,
dryhten sínne dríorigne fand
his lord, found bleeding,
ealdres æt ende· hé hine eft ongon
of life at an end; he again began on him
wæteres weorpan oð þæt wordes ord
to sprinkle water, until the word's point
bréosthord þurhbræc
broke through the breast-hoard,
gomel on giogoðe gold scéawode:
the old one on the youth saw gold:
'Ic ðára frætwa fréan ealles ðanc
'I, for these riches, to the Lord of All, thanks
wuldurcyninge wordum secge
to the Glory-King say by words,
écum dryhtne þé ic hér on starie
to the eternal Lord, which I look on here,
þæs ðe ic móste mínum léodum
that I was able for my people
aér swyltdæge swylc gestrýnan
before my death-day to gain such riches,
nú ic on máðma hord minne bebohte
now I for the hoard of treasures have paid with my
fróde feorhlege fremmað géna
old span of life. Tend still
léoda þearfe· ne mæg ic hér leng wesan·
the need of the nation. I cannot be here longer;
hátað heaðomaére hlaéw gewyrcean
order war-famed men to construct a mound
beorhtne æfter baéle æt brimes nósan·
bright after the fire, at the ocean's cape;
sé scel tó gemyndum mínum léodum
it shall to remind my people
héah hlífian on hrones næsse
tower high on headland of whales,
þæt hit saélíðend syððan hátan
so that it sea-farers then will name
Bíowulfes Biorh ðá ðe brentingas
Beowulf's Barrow, those who ships
ofer flóda genipu feorran drífað.'
over the seas' mists drive from afar.'
Dyde him of healse hring gyldenne
Took him from his neck the golden ring,
þíoden þrísthýdig· þegne gesealde
the valiant chief, to the thane gave,
geongum gárwigan goldfáhne helm
to the young spear-warrior, gold-adorned helm,
béah ond byrnan· hét hyne brúcan well:
ring and byrnie, told him to use them well:
'Þú eart endeláf ússes cynnes
'You are the last remainder of our race,
Waégmundinga· ealle wyrd forswéop
of the Waegmundings; Fate has swept off all
míne mágas tó metodsceafte
of my kinsmen into destined death,
eorlas on elne· ic him æfter sceal.'
earls in their strength; I must go after them.'
Þæt wæs þám gomelan gingæste word
That was for the old man the final word
bréostgehygdum aér hé baél cure
of the thoughts of his breast, ere he chose funeral fire,
háte heaðowylmas· him of hwæðre gewát
hot furious seething; yet from him went
sáwol sécean sóðfæstra dóm.
his soul to seek truth-fast judgement.