Oð þæt him on        innan    oferhygda daél
Until within        him    pride's portion
XXVI
weaxeð ond        wrídað    þonne se weard swefeð
grows and        flourishes    then the warder sleeps,
sáwele        hyrde·    bið se slaép tó fæst,
the soul's        keeper;    the sleep is too sound,
bisgum        gebunden,    bona swíðe néah
bound with        troubles,    the killer is very near,
sá þe of        flánbogan    fyrenum scéoteð·
he who from his        shaft-bow    foully fires;
þonne bið on        hreþre    under helm drepen
then it is in the        heart    struck beneath the helm
biteran        straéle     him bebeorgan ne con
by the bitter        dart     he cannot protect himself
wóm        wundorbebodum    wergan gástes·
from the perversity of strange        biddings    of the wicked spirit;
þinceð him tó        lýtel     þæt hé tó lange héold·
it seems to him too        little    what he rules too long;
gýtsað        gromhýdig·    nallas on gylp seleð
cruel-mindedly        covets,    he in arrogance never gives
faédde        béagas    ond hé þá forðgesceaft
golden        rings,    and he then the future
forgyteð ond        forgýmeð    þæs þe him aér god sealde,
forgets and        disregards,    that which God gave him before,
wuldres        waldend,    weorðmynda daél·
glory's Ruler,    a        share of honour·
hit on        endestæf    eft gelimpeð
it in the        end    finally comes to pass
þæt se        líchoma    laéne gedréoseð·
that the        body,    lent, fails;
faége        gefealleð·    féhð óþer tó
fated to death, it        falls;    another body takes up,
sé þe        unmurnlíce    mádmas daéleþ
who without        regret    shares out treasure,
eorles        aérgestréon·    egesan ne gýmeð.
the earl's ancient        wealth,    and he heeds not fear.
Bebeorh þé ðone        bealoníð,    Beowulf léofa
Guard yourself against this wicked        strife,    beloved Beowulf,
secg        betosta,    ond þé þæt sélre gecéos
finest man,    and        for yourself choose the better,
éce        raédas·    oferhýda ne gým,
the eternal        gains;    do not pay heed to pride,
maére        cempa·    nú is þínes mægnes blaéd
renowned        champion;    now is the glory of your strength
áne        hwíle·    eft sóna bið
for a        while;    presently in turn will be
þæt þec ádl oððe        ecg     eafoþes getwaéfeð
that you sickness or        edge    will part from strength,
oððe fýres        feng    oððe flódes wylm
or grasp of        fire,    or surge of flood,
oððe gripe        méces    oððe gáres fliht
or bite of        blade,    or flight of spear,
oððe atol        yldo·    oððe éagena bearhtm
or repulsive        old-age;    or the brightness of the eyes
forsiteð ond        forsworceð·    semninga bið
weakens and        dims;    very soon will be
þæt ðec,        dryhtguma,    déað oferswýðeð.
that you,        warrior,    Death overpowers.
Swá ic        Hring-Dena    hund misséra
So I the        Ring-Danes     a        hundred seasons
wéold under        wolcnum    ond hig wigge beléac
have ruled under the        skies    and in war sheltered them,
manigum        maégþa    geond þysne middangeard
from many tribes            throughout this middle-earth,
æscum ond        ecgum    þæt ic mé aénigne
from ash-shafts and        sword-edges,    so        that I for myself any,
under swegles        begong    gesacan ne tealde.
under the expanse of the        heavens,    adversary I did not        account.
Hwæt, mé þæs on        éþle    edwendan cwóm,
Listen, to me in the homeland for        that    a reversal came,
gyrn æfter        gomene    seoþðan Grendel wearð
sorrow after        joy,    since Grendel became
ealdgewinna    ingenga min
an old        contender,    invader of mine,
ic þaére sócne            singáles wæg
I from that        persecution    endured continually
módceare        micle·    þæs sig metode þanc
great sorrow of        spirit;    thanks be for that to the Measurer of        Fate,
écean        dryhtne    þæs ðe ic on aldre gebád
eternal        Lord,    from that I survived alive,
þæt ic on þone hafelan            heorodréorigne
so that I on the        head    sword-bloodied
ofer eald        gewin    éagum starige!
after ancient strife            could gaze with my eyes!
Gá nú tó        setle·     symbelwynne dréoh
Go now to the        bench,    join in the pleasure-banquet,
wíggeweorþad·    unc sceal worn        fela
honoured by your        battle;    we must very many
máþma        gemaénra    siþðan morgen bið.'
treasures share between        us    when it is morning.'
Géat wæs        glædmód·     géong sóna tó
The Geat was        glad-hearted,    went straightaway to
setles        néosan    swá se snottra heht·
seek the        bench,    as the wise one had commanded;
þá wæs eft swá        aér     ellenrófum
then it was again as        before    for bold warriors,
fletsittendum    fægere gereorded
for those sitting in the        hall    they prepared a fine feast
níowan        stefne·    nihthelm geswearc
once again;    the        helm of night darkened,
deorc ofer        dryhtgumum·    duguð eal árás·
dark over the company of        warriors;    the veterans all arose;
wolde        blondenfeax    beddes néosan,
the blended-haired one       wishes    to seek his bed,
gamela        Scylding·    Géat unigmetes wél
the aged        Scylding;    the Geat exceedingly much,
rófne        randwigan    restan lyste·
valiant        shield-warrior,    desired rest;
sóna him        seleþegn    síðes wérgum
at once him the        hall-thane    the weary journeyer
feorrancundum    orð wísade
from afar    guided        forth,
sé for        andrysnum    ealle beweotede
who for        courtesy    looked after everything
þegnes        þearfe    swylce þý dógore
of the hero's        needs,    such as in those days
heaþolíðende    habban scoldon·
warrior-sailors    were obliged to        have;
reste hine þá        rúmheort·     reced hlíuade
rested him then, the large-hearted        man;    the hall towered
géap ond        goldfáh·    gæst inne swæf
vaulted and        gold-adorned;    the guest slept inside
oþ þæt hrefn        blaca    heofones wynne
until the black        raven,    the        joy of the sky
blíðheort        bodode.    Ðá cóm beorht scacan
declared        glad-heartedly.    Then came bright        hurrying,
scaþan ónetton·
fighters hastening;
waéron        æþelingas    eft tó léodum
the nobles        were    back to their people
fúse tó        farenne·    wolde feor þanon
eager to        fare;    he wished far thence,
cuma        collenferhð    céoles néosan.
the high-spirited        visitor,    to seek his ship.
Heht þá se        hearda    Hrunting beran
He then directed the tough        man    to wear Hrunting
sunu        Ecgláfes·    heht his sweord niman
the son of        Edgelaf,    bid him take his sword,
léoflíc        íren·    sægde him þæs léanes        þanc·
beloved        iron;    said thanks to him for the loan,
cwæð: hé þone        gúðwine     gódne tealde
quoth: he the        war-friend    marked well,
wígcræftigne·     nales wordum        lóg
skilled in        war;    he did not in words blame
méces        ecge·    þæt wæs módig secg.
the maiche's edge;    he was a proud        man.
Ond þá        síðfrome,    searwum gearwe
And then, eager to be        going,    ready in arms,
wígend        waéron    éode weorð Denum
were the warriors,            the one honoured by the Danes went,
æþeling tó        yppan    þaér se óþer wæs
noble to the high        seat,    where the other was,
hæle        hildedéor    Hróðgár grétte.
the battle-bold        hero    greeted Hrothgar.