Him wæs ful boren ond fréondlaþu
The full cup was brought to him, and a friendly invitation
XVIII
wordum bewægned ond wundengold
proffered in words, and twisted gold
éstum geéawed: earmréade twá
kindly offered: two arm-ornaments,
hrægl ond hringas, healsbéaga maést
robe and rings, the largest necklace
þára þe ic on foldan gefrægen hæbbe·
of those which I on earth have heard of;
naénigne ic under swegle sélran hýrde
none under the sky I have heard of better
hordmádmum hæleþa syþðan Háma ætwæg
from hoard-treasures of heroes, since Hama carried off
tó herebyrhtan byrig Brósinga mene
to the battle-bright stronghold the Brosings' necklet,
sigle ond sincfæt· searoníðas fealh
jewel and precious setting; he fled the cunning enmity
Eormenríces· gecéas écne raéd·
of Eormenric, chose eternal benefit;
þone hring hæfde Higelác Géata
That ring had Hygelac of the Geats,
nefa Swertinges nýhstan síðe
grandson of Swerting, on his last adventure,
siðþan hé under segne sinc ealgode·
when under the banner he defended riches,
wælréaf werede· hyne wyrd fornam
warded slaughter-spoils; him Fate took away,
syþðan hé for wlenco wéan áhsode
after he from pride sought misery,
faéhðe tó Frýsum· hé þá frætwe wæg
feud with the Frisians; he then wore the ornament,
eorclanstánas ofer ýða ful
the mysterious stone over the waves' cup,
ríce þéoden· hé under rande gecranc.
the mighty prince; he fell under the rimmed-shield.
Gehwearf þá in Francna fæþm feorh cyninges
Passed then into the Franks' grasp the body of the king,
bréostgewaédu ond se béah somod·
mail-coat and the ring together;
wyrsan wígfrecan wæl réafeden
lesser warrior rifled the corpses
æfter gúðsceare· Géata léode
after the slaughter of battle; the people of the Geats
hréawíc héoldon. Heal swége onféng·
filled the field of corpses. The hall resounded with noise;
Wealhðéo maþelode· héo fore þaém werede spræc:
Wealhtheow spoke; she spoke before the retinue:
'Brúc ðisses béages, Béowulf léofa
'Make use of this ring, belovèd Beowulf,
hyse, mid haéle ond þisses hrægles néot
young man, with good fortune, and take benefit from this corslet,
þéod gestreona ond geþéoh tela·
the wealth of a nation, and prosper well,
cen þec mid cræfte ond þyssum cnyhtum wes
prove yourself with strength, and to these lads be
lára líðe· ic þé þæs léan geman·
gentle in teaching; I shall remember you for this requital;
hafast þú geféred þæt ðé feor ond néah
you have brought it about that you far and near
ealne wídeferhþ weras ehtigað
always and forever men will praise,
efne swá síde swá saé bebúgeð,
even as widely as the sea surrounds
windgeard, weallas· wes þenden þú lifige,
the home of the wind, walls; be while you live,
æþeling, éadig· ic þé an tela
prince, happy; I wish thee well,
sincgestréona· béo þú suna mínum
and rich in treasure; be you to my sons
daédum gedéfe, dréamhealdende·
indulgent in deeds, possessing joy;
hér is aéghwylc eorl óþrum getrýwe
here is each of the men true to the others
módes milde mandrihtne hléo·
generous in mind, in the protetion of their liege-lord;
þegnas syndon geþwaére þéod ealgearo
the thanes are united, the people alert,
druncne dryhtguman dóð swá ic bidde.'
the warrior-retinue cheered by drink do as I bid.'
Éode þá tó setle· þaér wæs symbla cyst·
She went then to her seat; there was the finest feast,
druncon wín weras· wyrd ne cúþon
the men drank wine; they did not know their fate,
geósceaft grimme swá hit ágangen wearð
horrific destiny, as it had happened
eorla manegum syþðan aéfen cwóm
to many heroes, after evening came,
ond him Hróþgár gewát tó hofe sínum
and Hrothgar went to his quarters,
ríce tó ræste reced weardode
the ruler to rest, the hall guarded
unrím eorla swá híe oft aér dydon
countless earls, as they often had done before,
bencþelu beredon· hit geondbraéded wearð
they cleared away the benches from the floor; over it was spread
beddum ond bolstrum· béorscealca sum
bedding and bolsters; one of the beer-drinkers,
fús ond faége fletræste gebéag·
eager and doomed, lay down in his hall-couch;
setton him tó héafdon hilderandas
they set at their heads battle-bossed shields,
bordwudu beorhtan· þaér on bence wæs
bright linden-wood; there on the bench was
ofer æþelinge ýþgeséne
over each nobleman easily seen
heaþostéapa helm hringed byrne
a battle-steep helm, ringed byrnie,
þrecwudu þrymlíc· wæs þéaw hyra
(and) glorious mighty shaft; their custom was
þæt híe oft waéron an wíg gearwe
that they were often ready for a battle
gé æt hám gé on herge gé gehwæþer þára
both at home and out harrying, and either of these,
efne swylce maéla swylce hira mandryhtne
for just such times as for their liege-lord
þearf gesaélde· wæs séo þéod tilu.
the need arose; they were a good platoon.