Ðá ic æt þearfe        gefrægn     þéodcyninges
I heard that then at the        need    of the folk-king
XXXVII
andlongne        eorl    ellen cýðan
the nobleman        alongside    displayed courage,
cræft ond        cénðu    swá him gecynde wæs·
strength and        boldness,    as was natural to him;
ne hédde hé þæs        heafolan    ac sío hand gebarn
he did not heed (the dragon's)        head,    though the hand was burned
módiges        mannes    þaér hé his mægenes healp
of the spirited        man,    there he his strength helped,
þæt he þone        níðgæst     nioðor hwéne slóh,
that he the        hostile outsider    struck somewhat lower,
secg on        searwum    þæt ðæt sweord gedéaf
the warrior in his        war-gear,    so that the sword sank in
fáh ond        faéted    þæt ðæt fýr ongon
gleaming and        golden    so that the fire began
sweðrian        syððan.    Þá gén sylf cyning
to weaken after        that.    Then again the king himself
gewéold his        gewitte·    wællseaxe gebraéd
gathered his        wits,    drew a slaughter-seax
biter ond        beaduscearp    þæt hé on byrnan wæg·
bitter and        battle-sharp,    that he wore on his byrnie;
forwrát Wedra        helm    wyrm on middan.
The Helm of the Wederas cut        through    the wyrm in the middle.
Féond        gefyldan     ferh ellen wræc
The foe they        felled     their courage driving out life
ond hí hyne þá        bégen    ábroten hæfdon,
and then the both of them        him    had destroyed,
sibæðelingas·    swylc sceolde secg        wesan
the noble        kinsmen;    so ought a man to be,
þegn æt        ðearfe.    Þæt ðám þéodne wæs
a thane in        need.    That was for the chieftain
síðas        sigehwíle    sylfes daédum,
the last time of        victory    by his own deeds,
worlde        geweorces.    Ðá sío wund ongon
in the world of        action.    Then the wound began,
þé him se        eorðdraca    aér geworhte
which him the        earth-dragon    had caused earlier,
swelan ond        swellan·    hé þæt sóna onfand·
to swelter and to        swell;    he soon discovered that,
þæt him on        bréostum     bealoníð wéoll
it him in the        breast    welled with deadly evil,
attor on        innan.    Ðá se æðeling gíong
poison        inside.    Then the noble went,
þæt hé bí        wealle     wíshycgende
so that he by the        wall    wise in thought
gesæt on        sesse·    seah on enta geweorc·
sat on a        seat;    he looked on the giants' work
hú ðá        stánbogan    stapulum fæste
how the stone-arches            on firm pillars
éce        eorðreced    innan healden.
the eternal        earth-hall    supported within.
Hyne þá mid        handa    heorodréorigne
Then with his        hands,    sword-bloody,
þéoden        maérne    þegn ungemete till
the renowned        chieftain,    the immensely good thane
winedryhten        his    wætere gelafede
his friend and        lord    washed with water,
hilde sædne    ond        his helm onspéon·
weary of        battle,    and unfastened his helm;
Bíowulf        maþelode·    hé ofer benne spræc,
Beowulf        spoke;    he spoke despite his injury,
wunde        wælbléate     wisse hé gearwe
the slaughter-wretched        wound     he readily knew
þæt hé        dæghwíla    gedrogen hæfde
that he the length of his        days    had fulfilled,
eorðan        wynne·    ðá wæs eall sceacen
joy of        earth;    then was all departed
dógorgerímes,     déað ungemete        néah :
his number of        days,    death exceedingly near
'Nú ic suna        mínum    syllan wolde
'Now I to my        son    I would have wished to give
gúðgewaédu     þaér        mé gifeðe swá
war-garments,            if it had been granted to me such that
aénig        yrfeweard    æfter wurde
any guardian of inheritance    would be        after
líce        gelenge·    ic ðás léode héold
this body        remaining;    I ruled the people
fíftig        wintra·    næs sé folccyning
fifty        winters;    there was not a folk-king
ymbesittendra    aénig ðára
of my        neighbours     of any of them
þé mec        gúðwinum    grétan dorste,
who me with war-friends     dared to        greet,
egesan        ðéön·    ic on earde bád
to threaten with        terror;    I on earth awaited
maélgesceafta·     héold mín        tela·
destiny,    ruled        my own well,
ne sóhte        searoníðas    né mé swór fela
did not seek cunning        hostility,    nor swore me many
áða on        unriht·    ic ðæs ealles mæg
oaths        unjustly;    I all of it can,
feorhbennum        séoc    geféan habban
sick with        mortal-injuries,    have rejoicing,
forðám mé wítan ne        ðearf     Waldend fíra
because he will not need to reproach        me,    the Ruler of men,
morðorbealo        mága    þonne mín sceaceð
for dire murder of        kin,    when departs my
líf of        líce.    Nú ðú lungre geong
life from        body.    Now go you quickly
hord        scéawian    under hárne stán,
to examine the        hoard    under the hoary grey stone,
Wígláf léofa,    nú        se wyrm ligeð,
dear Wiglaf,    now        the wyrm lies dead,
swefeð sáre        wund    since beréafod
sleeping sorely        wounded,    deprived of treasure
bío nú on        ofoste    þæt ic aérwelan
be now in        haste,    that I the ancient wealth,
goldaéht        ongite·    gearo scéawige
the possession of gold might        perceive,    readily behold
swegle        searogimmas    þæt ic ðý séft mæge
sparkling cleverly-cut        gems,    so that I can the more pleasantly
æfter        máððumwelan    mín álaétan
for        treasure-wealth    leave my
líf ond        léodscipe    þone ic longe héold.'
life and        nation,    that long I ruled.'