Wæs sío        swátswaðu    Swóna ond Géata
The bloody swathe            of the Swedes and Geats,
XLI
wælraés        weora    wíde gesýne·
the slaughter-rush of        men    was widely seen;
hú ðá folc mid        him    faéhðe tówehton·
how the folk between        them     awoke a feud;
gewát him ðá se        góda    mid his gædelingum
then the good man        went    with his fellow kinsmen,
fród        felageómor    fæsten sécean·
old and wise, greated        saddened,    to seek a citadel;
eorl        Ongenþío    ufor oncirde·
the warrior        Ongentheow    retreated higher up,
hæfde        Higeláces    hilde gefrúnen
he had of        Hygelac's    battle-skill heard,
wlonces        wígcræft·    wiðres ne trúwode·
the proud man's        war-craft;    he did not trust his resistance,
þæt hé        saémannum    onsacan mihte,
that he the        sea-men    could oppose,
heaðolíðendum            hord forstandan
against battle        travellers    defend the hoard,
bearn ond        brýde·    béah eft þonan
children and        women;    he fell back thence
eald under        eorðweall·    þá wæs aéht boden
old behind the        earth-wall;    then pursuit was offered
Swéona        léodum·    segn Higeláces
to the Swedish        nation,    the standards of Hygelac
freoðowong        þone    forð oferéodon
that place of refuge            forth overran,
syððan        Hréðlingas     tó hagan þrungon.
when the        Hrethelings    pressed forward into that        entrenchment.
Þaér wearð        Ongenðíow    ecgum sweordan
There was        Ongentheow    by edges of swords,
blondenfexa    on        bid wrecen
the        grizzle-haired    was compelled to pause,
þæt se        þéodcyning    ðafian sceolde
so that the        tribe-king    had to submit
Eafores ánne        dóm·    hyne yrringa
to the sole judgement of Eofor;    him wrathfully
Wulf        Wonréðing    waépne geraéhte
Wulf, Wonred's son,    reached with        his weapon,
þæt him for        swenge    swát aédrum sprong
so that from him by the        blow    blood in streams sprang
forð under        fexe·    næs hé forht swá ðéh
forth beneath his        hair;    he was not frightened though,
gomela        Scilfing    ac forgeald hraðe
the aged        Scilfing,    but quickly repaid
wyrsan wrixle            wælhlem þone
with a more terrible        response    for that slaughter-stroke,
syððan        ðéodcyning    þyder oncirde·
when the        tribe-king    turned thither;
ne meahte se        snella    sunu Wonrédes
he could not, the brave            son of Wonred,
ealdum        ceorle    hondslyht giofan
to the old        fellow    offer onslaught by hand,
ac hé him on        héafde    helm aér gescer
rather he        him on his head    had sheared his helm,
þæt he blode        fah    bugan sceolde·
so that he,        blood-stained,    had to bow down;
féoll on        foldan·    næs hé faége þá gít
he fell on the        field;    he was not doomed yet,
ac hé hyne        gewyrpte    þéah ðe him wund hrine·
but he recovered        himself,    though the wound touched him;
lét se        hearda    Higeláces þegn
Let he,        the hard    thane of Hygelac,
bráde méce    þá        his bróðor læg
broad maiche,    when his brother lay        dead,
ealdsweord        eotonisc    entiscne helm
the old ogrish        sword,    the giantish helm
brecan ofer        bordweal·    ðá gebéah cyning
break over the        shield-wall;    then the king bowed down,
folces        hyrde·    wæs in feorh dropen.
the shepherd of the        folk,    was struck to        his life.
Ðá waéron        monige     þé his maég wriðon·
Then there were        many,    who bandaged his        kinsman,
ricone        áraérdon    ðá him gerýmed wearð
they quickly raised him        up,    when room was made for them,
þæt híe        wælstówe    wealdan móston·
so that they the place of        slaughter    were able to control;
þenden        réafode    rinc óðerne·
then plunder    the        one man the other,
nam on        Ongenðío    írenbyrnan
he took from        Ongentheow    his iron byrnie,
heard swyrd        hilted    ond his helm somod·
his hard hilted        sword,    and his helmet too;
háres        hyrste    Higeláce bær·
the hoary one's        armour    he bore to Hygelac;
hé ðám frætwum        féng    ond him fægre gehét
he took the treasures    and fairly pledged to him
léana mid        léodum    ond gelaéste swá·
rewards among the        people,    and did so;
geald þone        gúðraés    Géata dryhten
he paid for the        war-onslaught,    the lord of the Geats,
Hréðles        eafora    þá hé tó hám becóm
Hrethel's        heir,    when he returned home,
Iofore ond        Wulfe    mid ofermáðmum·
to Eofor and        Wulf    with an abundance of treasure;
sealde hiora        gehwæðrum    hund þúsenda
he gave them        both    a hundred thousand worth of
landes ond locenra        béaga     ne ðorfte him ðá léan oðwítan
land and interlocked        rings     he needed not the gifts scorn,
mon on middangearde      syððan híe ðá maérða geslógon
(any) man on middle-earth,      since they gained those glories in fighting
ond ðá Iofore        forgeaf    ángan dohtor
and then to Eofor he        gave    his only daughter,
hámweorðunge    hyldo tó wedde.
a honour to the        home,    as pledge of friendship.
Þæt ys sío        faéhðo     ond se féondscipe
That is the        feud     and the enmity,
wælníð wera    ðæs        ðe ic wéan hafo
the slaughterous hate of        men,    for which I have woe,
þé ús séceað tó            Swéona léoda
they shall attack        us,    the Swedish nation,
syððan híe        gefricgeað    fréan úserne
when they        learn    our lord
ealdorléasne            þone ðe aér gehéold
is lifeless,     he who formerly        preserved
wið        hettendum    hord ond ríce
against        despisers    our hoard and kingdom,
æfter hæleða        hryre,    hwate Scildingas·
after fall of        heroes,    bold Scyldings,
folcréd        fremede    oððe furður gén
supported the welfare of the        folk,    or moreover
eorlscipe        efnde.    Mé is ofost betost
accomplished noble        deeds.    For me haste is best,
þæt wé        þéodcyning     þaér scéawian
that we the        people-king    look upon there,
ond þone        gebringan    þé ús béagas geaf
and that one        bring,    he who gave us rings,
on        ádfære·    ne scel ánes hwæt
on a journey to the        pyre;    nor must a part only
meltan mid þám        módigan    ac þaér is máðma hord
melt with that great-spirited        one,    but there is the treasure's hoard,
gold        unríme    grimme gecéapod
gold        uncounted,    bitterly purchased,
ond nú æt        síðestan    sylfes féore
and now at        last    with his own life
béagas        gebohte:    þá sceall brond fretan,
bought the        rings:    then the blaze must devour,
aéled        þeccean,    nalles eorl wegan
the fire        cover,    no man shall wear
máððum tó        gemyndum    né mægð scýne
these treasures in        remembrance,    no pretty girl
habban on        healse    hringweorðunge
shall have on her        neck    ring-adornment,
ac sceal        geómormód    golde beréafod
but must,        sad-hearted,    bereft of gold,
oft nalles        aéne    elland tredan
often, not        once,    tread in alien land,
nú se        herewísa    hleahtor álegde
now the        cohort-leader    has laid aside laughter
gamen ond        gléodréam.    Forðon sceall gár wesan
pleasure and        merriment.    Therefore must be spears
monig        morgenceald    mundum bewunden,
many, morning-cold,    grasped in palms,
hæfen on        handa,    nalles hearpan swég
raised in        hands,    not at all the sound of harp
wígend        weccean    ac se wonna hrefn
to wake the        warrior,    but the black raven,
fús ofer        faégum    fela reordian,
eager over the        doomed,    speaking many things,
earne secgan    hú        him æt aéte spéow
telling the        eagle,    how he succeeded in eating,
þenden hé wið        wulf    wæl réafode.'
when he with the        wolf    despoiled the slain.'
Swá se secg        hwata    secggende wæs
So the bold        men    was teller
láðra        spella·    hé ne léag fela
of hateful        tidings;    he did not lie much
wyrda né        worda.    Weorod eall árás·
in deeds or in        words.    The troop all arose;
éodon        unblíðe    under earna næs
they went unhappily            under the eagle's headland,
wollentéare    wundur        scéawian·
with welling        tears,    to gaze upon the wonder;
fundon ðá on        sande    sáwulléasne
they found then on the        sand,     soulless,
hlimbed        healdan    þone þe him hringas geaf
ruling over his bed of        rest,    the who gave them rings
aérran        maélum·    þá wæs endedæg
in earlier        times;    then it was the end-day
gódum        gegongen    þæt se gúðcyning
come for good        men,    that the war-king,
Wedra        þéoden    wundordéaðe swealt.
the Wederas'        chieftain,    died a wondrous death.
AÉr hí þaér        geségan    syllícran wiht
First they saw        there    a rarer creature,
wyrm on        wonge    wiðerræhtes þaér
the wyrm on the        ground    just opposite there,
láðne        licgean:    wæs se légdraca
the loathsome one lying        dead:    the fire-drake was
grimlíc        gryregiest    glédum beswaéled·
a grim gruesome        guest    burnt by flames;
sé wæs        fíftiges    fótgemearces
it was        fifty    foot-measures
lang on        legere·    lyftwynne héold
long as it        lay;    in air-joy it had ruled
nihtes        hwílum·    nyðer eft gewát
the times of the        night,    down again had gone
dennes        níosian·    wæs ðá déaðe        fæst·
to seek its        den;    it was then still in death,
hæfde        eorðscrafa    ende genyttod.
it had of        earth-caverns    enjoyed its end.
Him big        stódan    bunan ond orcas·
They stood by        him     goblets and beakers,
discas lágon    ond        dýre swyrd
lay plates    and        precious swords,
ómige        þurhetone    swá híe wið eorðan fæðm
eaten through by        rust,    as if they had in the embrace of the        earth
þúsend        wintra    þaér eardodon·
a thousand        winters    remained there;
þonne wæs þæt        yrfe     éacencræftig,
then was that              legacy     of exceedingly powerful,
iúmonna        gold    galdre bewunden
gold of men of        yore,    encompassed by an incantation,
þæt ðám        hringsele    hrínan ne móste
that the        ring-hall    could not touch
gumena        aénig    nefne god sylfa
any man,    unless        God himself,
sigora        sóðcyning    sealde þám ðe hé wolde
victories'        Truth-king    allowed he who He wished
hé is manna        gehyld      hord openian·
He is man's        protector     to open the hoard,
efne swá hwylcum        manna    swá him gemet ðúhte.
even so to every        man    as it seemed fitting to Him.