Him se yldesta             andswarode·
He the eldest             answered,
IIII
werodes wísa             wordhord onléac:
the crew's captain,             he unlocked his word-hoard:
'Wé synt gumcynnes             Géata léode
'We are of the tribe             of the Geat people
ond Higeláces             heorðgenéatas·
and Hygelac's             hearth-companions;
wæs mín fæder             folcum gecýþed
my father was             known to the folk,
æþele ordfruma             Ecgþéow háten·
a noble vanguard-warrior,             called Edgetheow,
gebád wintra worn             aér hé on weg hwurfe
who saw many winters             ere he passed away,
gamol of geardum·             hine gearwe geman
old, from our courtyards;             he is readily recalled
witena wélhwylc             wíde geond eorþan.
by each one of the wise             widely throughout the world.
Wé þurh holdne hige             hláford þínne
We, by resolute resolve,             your lord,
sunu Healfdenes             sécean cwómon
the son of Half-Dane             have come to seek,
léodgebyrgean·             wes þú ús lárena gód·
that protector of the people;             be you a good guide to us;
habbað wé tó þaém maéran             micel aérende
we have, to that grand one,             a great errand
Deniga fréän·             ne sceal þaér dyrne sum
to the Danish lord;             there shouldn't some secret
wesan þæs ic wéne.             Þú wást gif hit is
be of this, I think.             You know if it is
swá wé sóþlíce             secgan hýrdon
as we truly             have heard said,
þæt mid Scyldingum             sceaðona ic nát hwylc
that amongst the Scyldings,             some enemy, I know not what,
déogol daédhata             deorcum nihtum
a furtive despoiler,             in dark nights,
éaweð þurh egsan             uncúðne níð
sickeningly reveals             unknown enmity,
hýnðu ond hráfyl.             Ic þæs Hróðgár mæg
suffering and slaughter.             I can on this matter, to Hrothgar,
þurh rúmne sefan             raéd gelaéran·
from a spacious spirit,             give counsel,
hú hé fród ond gód,             féond oferswýðeþ
how he, wise and good,             overcome the fiend
gyf him edwendan             aéfre scolde
if for him a change             ever should,
bealuwa bisigu             bót eft cuman
from this suffering of miseries             to remedy, come after
ond þá cearwylmas             cólran wurðaþ
and his hot wellings of melancholic        care      grow cooler;
oððe á syþðan             earfoðþráge
or else ever after,             a time of torment,
þréanýd þolað             þenden þaér wunað
horrible hardship he will endure,             so long as there remains,
on héahstede             húsa sélest.'
in its high place,             that        best of houses.
Weard maþelode             ðaér on wicge sæt
The guard made a speech,             sitting there on his horse,
ombeht unforht:             'AÉghwæþres sceal
the unhesistating officer:             'He will  every
scearp scyldwiga             gescád witan
sharp shield-warrior              know the distinction
worda ond worca             sé þe wél þenceð.
between words and works,             he who reasons rightly.
Ic þæt gehýre·             þæt þis is hold weorod
I hear it,             that this is a legion loyal
fréan Scyldinga·             gewítaþ forð beran
to the lord of the Scyldings;             go forth bearing
waépen ond gewaédu·             ic éow wísige·
weapons and armour;             I shall guide you;
swylce ic maguþegnas             míne háte
likewise, I  the kin-thanes             of mine will order,
wið féonda gehwone             flotan éowerne
against any foes             your vessel,
níwtyrwydne             nacan on sande
newly tarred,             ship on the sand
árum healdan             oþ ðæt eft byreð
to guard in honour,             until it bears back,
ofer lagustréamas             léofne mannan
over the sea-streams,             the dear man,
wudu wundenhals             tó Wedermearce·
the swoop-necked wood        to Wedermark;
gódfremmendra             swylcum gifeþe bið
those who perform noble deeds              to such as these it shall be granted
þæt þone hilderaés             hál gedígeð.'
that the battle-rush             he survive in one piece.'
Gewiton him þá féran              flota stille bád·
Then they went faring              the boat at rest awaited,
seomode on sole             sidfaéþmed scip
it rode on the sand             the broad-bosomed ship,
on ancre fæst              eoforlíc scionon
on anchor fast              boar-figures shone
ofer hléorberan             gehroden golde·
atop        cheekguards      adorned with gold;
fáh ond fýrheard             ferhwearde héold·
glittering and fire-hard;             life-guard they held;
gúþmód grummon·             guman ónetton·
war-spirits raised;             the men hastened,
sigon ætsomne             oþ þæt hý sæltimbred
marched forward together,             until they the timbered hall,
geatolíc ond goldfáh             ongyton mihton·
glorious and gold-trimmed,             were able to glimpse;
þæt wæs foremaérost             foldbúendum
that was the foremost              for earth-dwellers
receda under roderum             on þaém se ríca bád·
of halls under the heavens,             in it the ruler dwelt;
líxte se léoma             ofer landa fela.
its light glimmered             over many lands.
Him þá hildedéor             hof módigra
Then to them the fierce fellow      to that court of        great men
torht getaéhte             þæt híe him tó mihton
glorious  he lead,             that they to it could
gegnum gangan·             gúðbeorna sum
go directly;             the worthy warrior
wicg gewende·             word æfter cwæð:
turned his horse,             thereupon spoke words:
'Maél is mé tó féran.             Fæder alwalda
'Time it is for me to go.             The Father all-ruling,
mid árstafum             éowic gehealde
with grace      may        He hold you
síða gesunde!             Ic tó saé wille
sound on your sojourns!             I will to the sea,
wið wráð werod             wearde healdan.'
against brutal dacoits             keep watch.'