Ðá cóm of móre under misthleoþum
Then came from the moor under the misty cliffs
XI
Grendel gongan· godes yrre bær·
Grendel walking, God's wrath he bore;
mynte se mánscaða manna cynnes
the vile ravager meant from mankind
sumne besyrwan in sele þám héan·
a sample
wód under wolcnum tó þæs þe hé wínreced
he waded under the clouds until he the wine-hall,
goldsele gumena gearwost wisse
the gold-hall of men  mostly-certainly saw,
faéttum fáhne· ne wæs þæt forma síð
shining gold; it was not the first time
þæt hé Hróþgáres hám gesóhte·
that he Hrothgar's home had sought;
naéfre hé on aldordagum aér ne siþðan
he never in the days of his life, ere nor after,
heardran haéle healðegnas fand.
harder luck or hall-thanes found.
Cóm þá to recede rinc síðian
He came then to the hall the fighter journeying,
dréamum bedaéled· duru sóna onarn
cut-off from merriment; the door soon rushed open,
fýrbendum fæst syþðan hé hire folmum æthrán
firm with fire-forged bands, when he tapped it with his hands
onbraéd þá bealohýdig ðá hé gebolgen wæs,
plotting evil then he tore open, now that he was enraged,
recedes múþan· raþe æfter þon
the mouth of the building; straight after that
on fágne flór féond treddode·
on the tessellated floor the fiend treaded,
éode yrremód· him of éagum stód
advanced angrily; from his eyes issued,
ligge gelícost léoht unfaéger·
most like a flame, a distorted light;
geseah hé in recede rinca manige
he saw in the hall many warriors
swefan sibbegedriht samod ætgædere
a sleeping company of kinsmen gathered together
magorinca héap. Þá his mód áhlóg:
a great host of warriors. Then his heart laughed:
mynte þæt hé gedaélde aér þon dæg cwóme
he intended to deprive, ere the day came,
atol áglaéca ánra gehwylces
the cruel beast, from each one
líf wið líce þá him álumpen wæs
life from body, now had befallen him
wistfylle wén. Ne wæs þæt wyrd þá gén
a hope of a full feast. It was not his fate again
þæt hé má móste manna cynnes
that he might more of mankind
ðicgean ofer þá niht· þrýðswýð behéold
partake of after that night; the mighty man beheld,
maég Higeláces hú se mánscaða
the kinsman of Hygelac, how the cruel killer
under faérgripum gefaran wolde.
by means of a sudden attack wished to proceed.
Né þæt se áglaéca yldan þóhte
That the monster did not think to delay,
ac hé geféng hraðe forman síðe
but he quickly grasped, at the first occasion,
slaépendne rinc slát unwearnum·
a sleeping warrior, rended without restraint,
bát bánlocan· blód édrum dranc·
bit into the bone-locks, from the veins drank blood,
synsnaédum swealh· sóna hæfde
swallowed great chunks; soon he had
unlyfigendes ealgefeormod
the unliving one all devoured,
fét ond folma· forð néar ætstóp·
feet and hands; nearer he stepped forth,
nam þá mid handa higeþíhtigne
taking then with his hands a stout-hearted
rinc on ræste· raéhte ongéan
warrior from his rest, reached towards him
féond mid folme· hé onféng hraþe
the foe with his palm; quickly he grasped
inwitþancum ond wið earm gesæt.
the malice thoughts and clamped down on the arm.
Sóna þæt onfunde fyrena hyrde·
At once he found, the shepherd of atrocities,
þæt hé ne métte middangeardes
that he had not met in middle-earth,
eorþan scéatta on elran men
in the expanse of the world, in another man
mundgripe máran· hé on móde wearð
a greater hand-grip; he in his heart grew
forht on ferhðe· nó þý aér fram meahte·
fearing for life; none the sooner could he away;
hyge wæs him hinfús· wolde on heolster fléon,
eager-to-go-hence was the thought in him, he wanted to flee into the darkness,
sécan déofla gedræg· ne wæs his drohtoð þaér
to seek the devils' concourse; his situation there was not
swylce hé on ealderdagum aér gemétte.
like he in the days of his life ever had met.
Gemunde þá se góda maég Higeláces
The good man then recalled, the kinsman of Hygelac,
aéfenspraéce· uplang ástód
his evening-speech; upright he stood
ond him fæste wiðféng· fingras burston·
and laid hold of him tight; fingers burst;
eoten wæs útweard· eorl furþur stóp.
the troll was striving to move outward, the earl stepped forward.
Mynte se maéra hwaér hé meahte swá
The infamous one meant, anywhere he so was able,
wídre gewindan ond on weg þanon
farther escape and away thence
fléon on fenhopu· wiste his fingra geweald
flee to his secret places in the fen; he knew his fingers' control
on grames grápum· þæt he wæs géocorsíð
in his enemy's grip, that was a bitter journey he
þæt sé hearmscaþa to Heorute átéah.
that the harm-warrior had taken to Heorot.
Dryhtsele dynede· Denum eallum wearð
The noble hall broke into a din; the Danes all were,
ceasterbúendum cénra gehwylcum
the citadel-dwellers  each of the bold,
eorlum ealuscerwen· yrre waéron bégen
earls in the flood of bitter drink; enraged were both
réþe renweardas· reced hlynsode.
fierce hall-wards; the hall resounded.
Þá wæs wundor micel þæt se wínsele
Then it was a great wonder that the wine-hall
wiðhæfde heaþodéorum· þæt hé on hrúsan ne féol
withstood the war-fighters, that it did not fall to the ground,
faéger foldbold ac hé þæs fæste wæs
the fair mansion but it so firm was
innan ond útan írenbendum
inside and out with iron-bands
searoþoncum besmiþod· þaér fram sylle ábéag
skilfully smithed; there from the floor broke away
medubenc monig míne gefraége
many mead-benches, I heard,
golde geregnad þaér þá graman wunnon·
adorned with gold, where the enemies struggled;
þæs ne wéndon aér witan Scyldinga·
it was not thought before, by the sages of the Scyldings,
þæt hit á mid gemete manna aénig
that it ever by means any men
betlíc ond bánfág tóbrecan meahte,
splendid and bone-adorned, could break it up,
listum tólúcan nymþe líges fæþm
cleverly cleave asunder, not unless fire's embrace
swulge on swaþule. Swég up ástág
swallowed it in inferno. Sound ascended up,
níwe geneahhe· Norð-Denum stód
new, nearby: the North-Danes stood
atelíc egesa ánra gehwylcum
in ghastly horror, in each one of
þára þe of wealle wóp gehýrdon,
them who from the wall weeping heard,
gryreléoð galan godes andsacan
terrible screaming, God's adversary,
sigeléasne sang, sár wánigean
a victoryless song, bewailing his wound,
helle hæfton· héold hine fæste
Hel's prisoner; he held him fast,
sé þe manna wæs mægene strengest
he who was of men in might strongest
on þaém dæge þysses lífes.
on that day in this life.