Swá mec gelóme             láðgetéonan
Thus me often             hateful attackers
VIIII
þréatedon þearle·             ic him þénode
pressed sorely;             I served them
déoran sweorde             swá hit gedéfe wæs·
with my dear sword,             as it was fitting;
næs híe ðaére fylle             geféan hæfdon
they the feast did not             have rejoicing,
mánfordaédlan             þæt híe mé þégon·
those perpetrators of crime,             that they partook of me,
symbel ymbsaéton             saégrunde néah
sitting round a banquet             near the sea-bed
ac on mergenne             mécum wunde
but in the morning             by maiche-swords wounded,
be ýðláfe      uppe        laégon
along what is left by the waves             up they lay
sweordum áswefede             þæt syðþan ná
put to sleep by swords,             so that never since
ymb brontne ford             brimlíðende
on the high waterway             sea-travellers
láde ne letton.             Léoht éastan cóm
way did not hinder.             Light came from the east,
beorht béacen godes·             brimu swaþredon
bright beacon of God,             the sea became still,
þæt ic saénæssas             geséon mihte
so that I the headlands             was able to see,
windige weallas.             Wyrd oft nereð
windswept walls.             Fate often spares
unfaégne eorl             þonne his ellen déah.
the hero not fated to die             when his courage endures.
Hwæþere mé gesaélde             þæt ic mid sweorde ofslóh
However it was my good fortune             that I with my sword slew
niceras nigene·             nó ic on niht gefrægn
nine of the nicors;      I have not heard by        night
under heofones hwealf             heardran feohtan
under heaven's vault             of a more grievous fight,
né on égstréamum             earmran mannon·
nor on the water-streams      of a more wretched        man;
hwaþere ic fára feng             féore gedígde
yet I the foes' grasp             survived with my life,
siþes wérig·             ðá mec saé oþbær
weary from my venture;             then the sea bore me off
flód æfter faroðe             on Finna land
flood following current             onto the land of the Lapps,
wudu weallendu.             Nó ic wiht fram þé
the tossing boat.             Not a whit of thee
swylcra searoníða             secgan hýrde
in such strife of conflict             have I heard told,
billa brógan·             Breca naéfre gít
of bill-blade terror;      Breca never        yet
æt heaðoláce             né gehwæþer incer
at battle-play,             nor either of you,
swá déorlíce             daéd gefremede
so boldly             performed a deed
fágum sweordum              nó ic þæs gylpe
with bright swords              I do not boast of this
þéah ðú þínum bróðrum             tó banan wurde
nevertheless, you your brothers'             killer were,
héafodmaégum·             þæs þú in helle scealt
near relatives;             for that you must with Hel
werhðo dreogan             þéah þín wit duge·
suffer torment,             though your mind is strong;
secge ic þé to sóðe,             sunu Ecgláfes,
I say to you in truth,             son of Edgelaf,
þæt naéfre Grendel swá fela             gryra gefremede
that Grendel would have never so many             atrocities committed,
atol aéglaéca             ealdre þínum,
that terrible demon              to your leader,
hýnðo on Heorote             gif þín hige waére
humiliation on Heorot,             if your heart were,
sefa swá searogrim             swá þú self talast
and your spirit so battle-fierce             as you yourself tell
ac hé hafað onfunden             þæt hé þá faéhðe ne þearf
but he has found             that the fight he needs not,
atole ecgþræce             éower léode
that terrible storm of sword-edges             of your nation,
swíðe onsittan             Sige-Scyldinga·
greatly to dread,             of the Victory-Scyldings;
nymeð nýdbáde·             naénegum árað
he takes a forced toll,             spares none
léode Deniga             ac hé lust wigeð·
of the Danish people,             but he carries on his delight,
swefeð ond sendeþ·             secce ne wéneþ
slaying and despatching,             he does not expect contest
tó Gár-Denum.             Ac ic him Géata sceal
from the Spear-Danes.             But I shall him the Geats'
eafoð ond ellen             ungeára nú
might and courage,             before long now,
gúþe gebéodan·             gaéþ eft, sé þe mót
offer in war;             a man will be able to go back,
tó medo módig             siþþan morgenléoht
to mead bravely,             when the morning-light
ofer ylda bearn             óþres dógores
over the sons of men             of another day,
sunne sweglwered             súþan scíneð.'
the sun clad in radiance,             shines from the south.'
Þá wæs on sálum             sinces brytta
Then was joyful             the        dispenser of treasures,
gamolfeax ond gúðróf             géoce gelýfde
with wizened hair and brave in battle             for support he trusted
brego Beorht-Dena             gehýrde on Béowulfe
the lord of the Bright-Danes             heard in Beowulf
folces hyrde             fæstraédne geþóht·
the guardian of the folk,             firmly-resolved intent;
ðaér wæs hæleþa hleahtor·             hlyn swynsode·
There was the laughter of heroes,             the noise made melody,
word waéron wynsume.             Éode Wealhþéow forð
words were joyful.             Wealhtheow came forth,
cwén Hróðgáres             cynna gemyndig
Hrothgar's queen,             mindful of etiquette,
grétte goldhroden             guman on healle
greeted, gold-adorned,             the men in the hall
ond þá fréolíc wíf             ful gesealde
and then the noble lady             gave out full cups,
aérest Éast-Dena             éþelwearde·
first to the East-Danes             homeland-guardian,
bæd hine blíðne             æt þaére béorþege
bade him be blithe             at the partaking of beer,
léodum léofne·             hé on lust geþeah
beloved by the people;             he took in delight
symbel ond seleful             sigeróf kyning·
feast-food and hall-cup,             the victorious king;
ymb-éode þá             ides Helminga
then she went among them,             the lady of the Helmings,
duguþe ond geogoþe             daél aéghwylcne·
to veteran and youth             a portion to each,
sincfato sealde             oþ þæt saél álamp
gave rich cups,             until the time came
þæt hío Béowulfe,             béaghroden cwén
that she to Beowulf,             the ring-adorned queen,
móde geþungen             medoful ætbær·
blossoming in spirit,             carried a mead-cup;
grétte Géata léod·             gode þancode
she greeted the Geatish prince,             thanked God,
wísfæst wordum             þæs ðe hire se willa gelamp
wise in her words,             for that her wish was to be fulfilled,
þæt héo on aénigne             eorl gelýfde
that she in any             noble man could count on
fyrena frófre.             Hé þæt ful geþeah
relief from wickedness.             He took that full-cup,
wælréow wiga             æt Wealhþéön
the slaughter-fierce warrior             from Wealhtheow,
ond þá gyddode             gúþe gefýsed·
and then spoke solemnly,             made eager for war;
Béowulf maþelode             bearn Ecgþéowes:
Beowulf spoke,             the son of Edgetheow:
'Ic þæt hogode·             þá ic on holm gestáh·
'I resolved that,             when I mounted the water,
saébát gesæt             mid mínra secga gedriht·
sat down in the sea-boat             amid my company of warriors,
þaét ic ánunga             éowra léoda
that I forthwith             your people's
willan geworhte             oþðe on wæl crunge
will would work,             or fall in slaughter,
féondgrápum fæst·             ic gefremman sceal
fast in the fiend's grasp;             I must perform
eorlíc ellen             oþðe endedæg
this daring act of courage             or the last day
on þisse meoduhealle             mínne gebídan.'
in this mead-hall             of mine await.'
Ðám wífe þá word             wél lícodon
The woman these words             liked well,
gilpcwide Géates·             éode goldhroden
the vow-speech of the Geat;             went gold-adorned,
fréolicu folccwén             tó hire fréan sittan.
the noble queen of the folk,             to sit by her lord.
Þá wæs eft swá aér             inne on healle
Then were again, as before,             in the hall,
þrýðword sprecen,             ðéod on saélum,
bold words spoken,             the people full of joy,
sigefolca swég             oþ þæt semninga
victory-folk's clamour              until presently
sunu Healfdenes             sécean wolde
the son of Half-Dane             wished to seek
aéfenræste·             wiste þaém áhlaécan
evening-rest;             he knew that the ogre
tó þaém héahsele             hilde geþinged
for the high hall             had plotted an attack,
siððan híe sunnan léoht             geséon meahton
ever since when they the sun's light             could see;
oþðe nípende             niht ofer ealle
and darkening             night all over,
scaduhelma gesceapu             scríðan cwóman
shadow-helm's shapes             came slithering,
wan under wolcnum.             Werod eall árás·
black beneath the skies.             The troop all arose;
gegrétte þá guma             guman óþerne
greeted then the man             the other man,
Hróðgár Béowulf             ond him haél ábéad
Hrothgar Beowulf,             and bid him health,
wínærnes geweald             ond þæt word ácwæð:
the wine-hall's ruler,             and spoke these words:
'Naéfre ic aénegum men             aér álýfde·
'I never to any man             before entrusted,
siþðan ic hond ond rond             hebban mihte·
since I hand and shield             was able to raise,
ðrýþærn Dena             búton þé nú ðá·
this strong-hall of the Danes,             save to thee now;
hafa nú ond geheald             húsa sélest·
have now and hold             this best of houses,
gemyne maérþo·             mægenellen cýð·
focus on glory,             show great valour,
waca wið wráþum·             ne bið þé wilna gád
keep watch against the enemy;             there shall be no dearth of your desires
gif þú þæt ellenweorc             aldre gedígest.'
if this courage-work you             survive with your life.'