Ðá wæs on morgen             míne gefraége
Then was in the morning,             as I heard tell,
XIII
ymb þá gifhealle             gúðrinc monig
about the gift-hall             many warriors,
férdon folctogan             feorran ond néän
folk-chiefs arrived             from far and near
geond wídwegas             wundor scéawian
across wide regions             to behold the wonder,
láþes lástas·             nó his lífgedál
the foe's foot-prints;             his parting from life did not
sárlíc þúhte             secga aénegum
seem mournful             to any man
þára þe tírléases             trode scéawode·
of those who the gloryless foe's             track observed,
hú hé wérigmód             on weg þanon
how he weary             away thence,
níða ofercumen             on nicera mere
vanquished by violence,             to the nicors' mere
faége ond geflýmed             feorhlástas bær.
doomed and driven back             left        behind life-trails.
Ðaér wæs on blóde             brim weallende,
There with blood was             the water seething,
atol ýða geswing             eal gemenged
terrible swirling of swells             all mingled
háton heolfre             heorodréore wéol·
with boiling gore,             with sword-blood it welled,
déaðfaége déog             siððan dréama léas
doomed to die he        hid himself,      then, bereft of pleasure,
in fenfreoðo             feorh álegde
in his fen-refuge             he laid down his life,
haéþene sáwle·             þaér him hel onféng.
his heathen soul;             there Hel embraced him.
Þanon eft gewiton             ealdgesíðas
Thence returned             old companions,
swylce geong manig             of gomenwáþe
also many young,             from the sport-chase,
fram mere módge             méarum rídan
from the mere full-spirited,             riding horses,
beornas on blancum·             ðaér wæs Béowulfes
warriors on fair        steeds,      there was Beowulf's
maérðo maéned·             monig oft gecwæð
glory proclaimed;             many often said
þætte súð né norð             be saém twéonum
that neither south nor north             between the seas
ofer eormengrund             óþer naénig
over the whole vast earth,             no other
under swegles begong             sélra naére
under the sky's expanse             was ne'er better
rondhæbbendra,             ríces wyrðra·
shield-bearer,             of a worthier kingdom;
né híe húru winedrihten             wiht ne lógon
nor, however, the friend and lord,             did they blame at all,
glædne Hróðgár             ac þæt wæs gód cyning.
gracious Hrothgar,             for he was a good king.
Hwílum heaþorófe             hléapan léton
At times the brave warriors             let leap,
on geflit faran             fealwe méaras
in a contest raced             fallow horses,
ðaér him foldwegas             fægere þúhton
where to them the earth-roads             seemed suitable,
cystum cúðe.             Hwílum cyninges þegn
and known to be the best.             At times the king's thane,
guma gilphlæden             gidda gemyndig
a man laden with fine speech,             remembering songs,
sé ðe ealfela             ealdgesegena
he who very many             of ancient traditions
worn gemunde             word óþer fand
recalled scores,             found new words
sóðe gebunden·             secg eft ongan
bound in truth;             the man then began
síð Béowulfes             snyttrum styrian
Beowulf's exploit             skilfully to recite,
ond on spéd wrecan             spel geráde,
and artfully utter             an adept tale,
wordum wrixlan·             wélhwylc gecwæð
varying his words;             he spoke of almost everything
þæt hé fram Sigemunde             secgan hyrde
that he of Sigmund                   had heard said,
ellendaédum:             uncúþes fela
of his deeds of glory:             many uncanny things,
Wælsinges gewin             wíde síðas
the striving of Wael's son,      his great        journeys;
þára þe gumena bearn             gearwe ne wiston
those things of which the childen of        men      by no means knew,
faéhðe ond fyrena             búton Fitela mid hine,
feuds and feats of arms,             only Fitela with him,
þonne hé swulces hwæt             secgan wolde
then he of such matters             was wont to speak of,
éäm his nefan             swá híe á waéron
uncle to his nephew,             as they always were
æt níða gehwám             nýdgesteallan·
in every conflict             comrades in need;
hæfdon ealfela             eotena cynnes
they had a great many             of the giantkind
sweordum gesaéged·             Sigemunde gesprong
laid low with swords;             for Sigmund arose,
æfter déaðdæge             dóm unlýtel
after the day of his death,             no little fame,
syþðan wíges heard             wyrm ácwealde
since the fierce warrior             had quelled the great serpent,
hordes hyrde·             hé under hárne stán
the keeper of a hoard;             beneath the hoary grey stone he,
æþelinges bearn             ána genéðde
the prince's son,             alone ventured
frécne daéde             ne waés him Fitela mid·
a dangerous deed,             Fitela was not with him;
hwæþre him gesaélde             ðæt þæt swurd þurhwód
however it was granted him             that the sword pierced
wraétlícne wyrm             þæt hit on wealle ætstód
the wondrous wyrm,             so that it stood fixed in the wall,
dryhtlíc íren·             draca morðre swealt·
the noble iron;             the dragon perished in the slaughter;
hæfde áglaéca             elne gegongen
the fearsome one had             ensured by courage
þæt hé béahhordes             brúcan móste
that he the ring-hoard             might possess
selfes dóme·             saébát gehléod·
at his own choosing;             he loaded the sea-boat,
bær on bearm scipes             beorhte frætwa
bore in the bosom of his ship             the gleaming treasures,
Wælses eafera              wyrm hát gemealt
Wael's son              the wyrm in its heat melted
sé wæs wreccena             wíde maérost
he was of adventurers             the most widely famed
ofer werþéode             wígendra hléo
among nations,             the warriors' protector,
ellendaédum              hé þæs aér onðáh
for deeds of valour              he had prospered by this
siððan Heremódes             hild sweðrode,
since Heremod's      skirmishing had        abated,
earfoð ond ellen·             he mid eotenum wearð
affliction and spirit;             he among the Etins was
on féonda geweald             forð forlácen
into enemy hands             given up,
snúde forsended·             hine sorhwylmas
quickly despatched;             the surgings of sorrow him
lemede tó lange·             hé his léodum wearð
hindered too long;             he to his people became,
eallum æþellingum             tó aldorceare·
to all of the nobles,             a great mortal sorrow;
swylce oft bemearn             aérran maélum
moreover they often mourned,             for in earlier times,
swíðferhþes síð             snotor ceorl monig
the departure of the stouted-hearted        king,      many learnèd sages
sé þe him bealwa             tó bóte gelýfde
who to him for miseries'             remedy had trusted and believed
þæt þæt ðéodnes bearn             geþéon scolde,
that that prince's son             must prosper,
fæderæþelum onfón,             folc gehealdan
take up his father's rank,             rule the folk,
hord ond hléoburh             hæleþa ríce
their treasury and citadel,             the heroes' kingdom,
éðel Scyldinga·             hé þaér eallum wearð
homeland of the Scyldings;             he by all became,
maég Higeláces             manna cynne
the kinsman of Hygelac,             by mankind,
fréondum gefægra·             hine fyren onwód.
more esteemed;             wickedness undid him.
Hwílum flítende             fealwe straéte
Now and then racing,             dusky streets
méarum maéton.             Ðá waés morgenléoht
on their mounts they traversed.             Then was the morning light
scofen ond scynded·             éode scealc monig
hurried and hastened;             many retainers went
swíðhicgende             tó sele þám héan
determined      to        the high hall
searowundor séon·             swylce self cyning
to see the strange wonder;             the king himself too
of brýdbúre             béahhorda weard
from his wife's bower,             the ward of the ring-hoard,
tryddode tírfæst             getrume micle
stepped out splendid             with his great troop,
cystum gecýþed             ond his cwén mid him
famed for his excellence,             and his queen with him,
medostigge mæt             mægþa hóse.
passed down the meadhall-path,             accompanied by maidens.