Hróðgár maþelode helm Scyldinga:
Hrothgar spoke,  the Helm of the Scyldings :
VI
'Ic hine cúðe cnihtwesende·
'I knew him when he was a youth;
wæs his ealdfæder Ecgþéo háten
his old father was called Ecgtheow,
ðaém tó hám forgeaf Hréþel Géata
to whom gave into his home Hrethel of the Geats
ángan dohtor· is his eaforan nú
his only daughter; now his heir is
heard hér cumen· sóhte holdne wine.
come here bravely, seeking a steadfast friend.
Ðonne sægdon þæt saélíþende
Further, it has been said by sea-farers,
þá ðe gifsceattas Géata fyredon
they who our gifts of coins ferried for the Geats
þyder tó þance· þæt hé þrítiges
thither in thanks, that he thirty
manna mægencræft on his mundgripe
men's strength in the grip of his hand,
heaþoróf hæbbe· hine hálig god
renowned in war, has; him holy God,
for árstafum ús onsende
in benevolence, has sent to us,
tó West-Denum· þæs ic wén hæbbe·
to the West-Danes, of this I have hope,
wið Grendles gryre· ic þaém gódan sceal
against Grendel's terror; I the good man must
for his módþræce mádmas béodan.
for his great daring offer precious treasures.
Béo ðú on ofeste· hát in gáän
Be you in haste, order to come in
séon sibbegedriht samod ætgædere·
to see me the noble band of kinsmen all together;
gesaga him éac wordum þæt híe sint wilcuman
Say to them also in words, that they are welcome
Deniga léodum.'
to the Danish land.'
Word inne ábéad:
A word from within announced:
'Éow hét secgan sigedrihten mín
'To you I am commanded to say by my valorous lord,
aldor Éast-Dena þæt hé éower æþelu can
the leader of the East Danes, that he knows your noble history,
ond gé him syndon ofer saéwylmas
and you are to him, over sea-swells,
heardhicgende hider wilcuman·
bold in thought  welcome hither;
nú gé móton gangan in éowrum gúðgeatáwum
now you may enter in your war-gear,
under heregríman Hróðgár geseon·
under visored-helmets, to see Hrothgar;
laétað hildebord hér onbidan,
let battle-boards here await,
wuduwælsceaftas, worda geþinges.'
and wooden slaughter-shafts, the result of words.'
Árás þá se ríca, ymb hine rinc manig
Then the mighty one arose, about him many warriors,
þrýðlíc þegna héap· sume þaér bidon·
the glorious troop of thanes; some waited there,
heaðoréaf héoldon swá him se hearda bebéad·
guarding the gear of war as the hardy leader bade;
snyredon ætsomne· þá secg wísode
they hurried together; the hero led the way for them
under Heorotes hróf·
under Heorot's roof,
heard under helme þæt hé on héoðe gestód.
severe under his helmet, until he stood in the hall.
Béowulf maðelode  on him byrne scán
Beowulf spoke  on him a mail-coat gleamed,
searonet seowed smiþes orþancum :
a net of armour woven by smith's skilful art :
'Wæs þú, Hróðgár, hál. Ic eom Higeláces
'Be you, Hrothgar, whole. I am Hygelace's
maég ond magoðegn· hæbbe ic maérða fela
kinsman and retainer; I have many great labours
ongunnen on geogoþe· mé wearð Grendles þing
undertaken in my youth; Grendel's enterprises have to me become,
on mínre éþeltyrf undyrne cúð:
on my native soil, clearly known:
secgað saélíðend þæt þæs sele stande
it is said by sea-farers that in this hall stands,
reced sélesta rinca gehwylcum
the best of buildings  for each and every man,
ídel ond unnyt siððan aéfenléoht
idle and useless, after evening-light
under heofenes hádor beholen weorþeð.
under the firmament of heaven goes to hide.
Þá mé þæt gelaérdon léode míne
Then I was advised that, by my people,
þá sélestan snotere ceorlas,
the best ones, the clever chaps,
þéoden Hróðgár, þæt ic þé sóhte
sovereign Hrothgar, that it were thee I should seek,
for þan híe mægenes cræft míne cúþon·
for that they the force of the strength of mine knew;
selfe ofersáwon ðá ic of searwum cwóm
themselves had looked on, when I returned from battle,
fáh from féondum þaér ic fífe geband·
stained with the blood of foes, where I bound five,
ýðde eotena cyn ond on ýðum slóg
destroyed ogrish kin, and amid the waves slew
niceras nihtes· nearoþearfe dréah·
nicors by night; I weathered distress in many a tight corner,
wræc Wedera níð  wéan áhsodon
avenged injury done the Wederas  they sought woe
forgrand gramum ond nú wið Grendel sceal
the foes I crushed, and now against Grendel I am bound,
wið þám áglaécan ána gehégan
with that terrible creature, alone, to settle
ðing wið þyrse. Ic þé nú ðá,
the affair with the troll. I now then you,
brego Beorht-Dena, biddan wille,
prince of the Bright-Danes, want to request,
eodor Scyldinga, ánre béne:
O protector of the Scyldings, one boon:
þæt ðú mé ne forwyrne, wígendra hléo
that you not refuse me, O shield of warriors,
fréowine folca, nú ic þus feorran cóm·
liege and comrade of the folk, now that I have come thus far;
þæt ic móte ána, mínra eorla gedryht
that I might alone, with my company of nobles
ond þes hearda héap, Heorot faélsian·
and this hardy horde of warriors, cleanse Heorot;
hæbbe ic éac ge-áhsod þæt sé aéglaéca
I have also heard that the evil creature
for his wonhýdum waépna ne recceð·
in his recklessness heeds not weapons;
ic þæt þonne forhicge  swá mé Higelác síe
then I it scorn  so that for me Hygelac may be
mín mondrihten módes blíðe
my liege-lord blithe in his heart
þæt ic sweord bere oþðe sídne scyld
that I bear a sword or broad shield,
geolorand tó gúþe ac ic mid grápe sceal
yellow-rim to war, but I with my grip shall
fón wið féonde ond ymb feorh sacan,
fight with this fiend and over life strive,
láð wið láþum· ðaér gelýfan sceal
enemy against enemy; there must trust in
dryhtnes dóme sé þe hine déað nimeð·
the judgement of the Lord, whichever one that Death takes;
wén' ic þæt hé wille gif hé wealdan mót
I expect that he will wish, if he can compass it,
in þaém gúðsele Géotena léode
in the war-hall, the Geatish people
etan unforhte swá hé oft dyde,
to devour fearlessly, as he often did,
mægenhréð manna. Ná þú mínne þearft
the force of glorious warriors. You will have no need for my
hafalan hýdan ac hé mé habban wile
head to shroud, but rather he will have me
déore fahne gif mec déað nimeð
fiercely stained with gore, if me Death takes,
byreð blódig wæl· byrgean þenceð·
he will bear my bloody corpse; he aims to bite,
eteð ángenga unmurnlíce·
the lone prowler eats unmournfully,
mearcað mórhopu· nó ðú ymb mínes ne þearft
marking the limits of his moor enclosures; nor will you for the needs of my
líces feorme leng sorgian.
body's funeral-provisions have any further concern.
Onsend Higeláce gif mec hild nime
Send to Hygelac, if I am taken by battle,
beaduscrúda betst þæt míne bréost wereð,
the best of battle-shrouds, the one that protects my breast,
hrægla sélest· þæt is Hraédlan láf
choicest of garments; that is Hrethel's relic,
Wélandes geweorc. Gaéð á wyrd swá hío scel.'
Wayland's work. Fate goes always as She must.'