Oð ðæt híe forlaéddan tó ðám lindplegan
Until they had led to disaster in the shield-play
XXX
swaése gesíðas ond hyra sylfra feorh.
their dear companions and their own lives.
Þonne cwið æt béore sé ðe béahgesyhð
Then speaks at the beer-drinking, he who sees a ring-precious object,
eald æscwiga sé ðe eall geman
the old ash-warrior, he who remembers all
gárcwealm gumena  him bið grim sefa
the spear-death of men  in him is a fierce heart
onginneð géomormód geongum cempan
he begins sad-spirited in a young champion,
þurh hreðra gehygd higes cunnian,
by the musing of his heart, to tempt his mind,
wígbealu weccean ond þæt word ácwyð:
to awaken war-horror, and speaks these words:
"Meaht ðú, mín wine, méce gecnáwan
"Can you, my friend, recognise that maiche,
þone þín fæder tó gefeohte bær
which your father bore into the fight,
under heregríman hindeman síðe,
under his army-mask on the last campaign,
dýre íren, þaér hyne Dene slógon·
precious iron, there the Danes slew him,
wéoldon wælstówe syððan wiðergyld læg
controlled the slaying-field, when retribution failed,
æfter hæleþa hryre hwate Scyldungas?
after the heroes' fall, the fierce Scyldings?
Nú hér þára banena byre náthwylces
Now here of those slayers the son of one or other of them,
frætwum hrémig on flet gaëð·
exultant in trappings, goes across the floor,
morðres gylpeð ond þone máðþum byreð
boasts of murder, and wears the treasure
þone þe ðú mid rihte raédan sceoldest."
which you by right ought to possess."
Manað swá ond myndgað maéla gehwylce
Thus he incites and reminds every time
sárum wordum oð ðæt saél cymeð
with grievous words, until that time comes
þæt se faémnan þegn fore fæder daédum
that the woman's thane for his father's deeds
æfter billes bite blódfág swefeð
from the bite of a bill-blade sleeps, stained in blood,
ealdres scyldig· him se óðer þonan
having forfeited life; him the other thence
losað lifigende· con him land geare.
escapes alive, the land is readily known to him.
Þonne bíoð brocene on bá healfe
Then are broken on both sides
áðsweorð eorla· syððan Ingelde
the sworn oaths of earls; then in Ingeld
weallað wælníðas ond him wíflufan
murderous hate will well up and in him the love of woman
æfter cearwælmum cólran weorðað·
surges of grief will become cooler;
þý ic Heaðo-Beardna hyldo ne telge
Therefore I the Heathobards' loyalty do not consider,
dryhtsibbe daél Denum unfaécne,
the alliance's portion, for the Danes untreacherous,
fréondscipe fæstne. Ic sceal forð sprecan
enduring friendship. I ought speak further
gén ymbe Grendel þæt ðú geare cunne,
again about Grendel, that you may readily know,
sinces brytta, tó hwan syððan wearð
giver of treasure, what then happened,
hondraés hæleða syððan heofones gim
the hand-fight of heroes when heaven's gem
glád ofer grundas gaést yrre cwóm
had glided over the earth, the ireful guest came,
eatol aéfengrom úser néosan
terrible, fierce in the evening to visit us,
ðaér wé gesunde sæl weardodon
where we, unharmed, warded the hall,
þaér wæs Hondsciö hilde onsaége
where was for Hondscio a sinking battle
feorhbealu faégum· hé fyrmest læg
deadly evil for the doomed man; he fell first,
gyrded cempa· him Grendel wearð
the girded champion; for him Grendel was,
maérum maguþegne tó múðbonan·
the famed thane of distinction, a slayer by mouth,
léofes mannes líc eall forswealg·
the belovèd man's body swallowed up completely;
nó ðý aér út ðá gén ídelhende
not the sooner out yet empty-handed,
bona blódigtóð bealewa gemyndig
the slayer bloody-toothed, wickedness in mind,
of ðám goldsele gongan wolde
from the gold-hall did he wish to go
ac hé mægnes róf mín costode·
but he, famed for his strength, tested me,
grápode gearofolm· glóf hangode
gripped with an eager hand; a pouch hung down
síd ond syllíc searobendum fæst
spacious and strange, with cleverly-wrought clasps held fast,
sío wæs orðoncum eall gegyrwed
it was cunningly all devised
déofles cræftum ond dracan fellum·
with devil's crafts and dragon's skins;
hé mec þaér on innan unsynnigne
he me there inside, guiltless,
díor daédfruma gedón wolde
the daring instigator wished to stuff,
manigra sumne· hyt ne mihte swá
as one of many; he could not do so,
syððan ic on yrre upprihte ástód.
since I in anger stood erect.
Tó lang ys tó reccenne hú ic ðám léodsceaðan
It is too long to recount how I the scourge of the people
yfla gehwylces hondléan forgeald
for each of his evils paid in hand-requital
þaér ic, þéoden mín, þíne léode
where I, my lord, your people
weorðode weorcum· he on weg losade
honoured by acts; he escaped away
lýtle hwíle lífwynna bréac·
for a little while, enjoyed the joy of life;
hwæþre him sío swíðre swaðe weardade
yet from him the right, a vestige, remained behind
hand on Hiorte ond hé héan ðonan
hand in Heorot, and he wretched thence,
módes geómor meregrund geféoll.
gloomy in his heart, sank into the depths of the mere.
Mé þone wælraés wine Scildunga
To me for the bloody battle the Friend of the Scyldings
faéttan golde fela léanode
with objects of plated gold in plenty rewarded,
manegum máðmum syððan mergen cóm
many treasures, when morning came,
ond wé tó symble geseten hæfdon
and we to the feast had sat down
þaér wæs gidd ond gléo: gomela Scilding
where was song and glee: old Scylding
felafricgende feorran rehte·
who has heard tell of many things, from long ago narrated;
hwílum hildedéor hearpan wynne
at times this battle-daring one the harp for pleasure
gomelwudu grétte· hwílum gyd áwræc
the old-wood played; sometimes recited a song,
sóð ond sárlíc· hwílum syllíc spell
true and tragic; sometimes strange tales
rehte æfter rihte rúmheort cyning·
he related rightly, the open-hearted king;
hwílum eft ongan eldo gebunden
at times he began again, bound in his age,
gomel gúðwiga gioguðe cwíðan
the ancient war-soldier, to mourn for his youth,
hildestrengo· hreðer inne wéoll
his battle-strength; his heart welled inside,
þonne hé wintrum fród, worn gemunde.
when he, wise in winter, recalled many things.
Swá wé þaér inne andlangne dæg
So we there inside a whole long day
níode náman oð ðæt niht becwóm
took pleasure, until came night
óðer tó yldum· Þá wæs eft hraðe
another to men; then was again swiftly
gearo gyrnwræce Grendeles módor
ready for grief-revenge Grendel's mother,
síðode sorhfull· sunu déað fornam,
she journeyed full of sorrow; Death had taken her son,
wíghete Wedra· wíf unhýre
the war-hate of the Wederas; the horrible woman
hyre bearn gewræc· beorn ácwealde
avenged her child, killed a warrior
ellenlíce· þaér wæs Æschere
savagely; there was from Æschere,
fródan fyrnwitan feorh úðgenge.
the old, wise lore-counsellor, life departed.
Nóðer hý hine ne móston syððan mergen cwóm
Nor could they him, when morning came,
déaðwérigne Denia léode
weary of death the Danish people
bronde forbærnan né on baél hladan
cremate in fire, nor lay on the funeral bale,
léofne mannan· hío þæt líc ætbær
the beloved man; she had carried off the corpse
féondes fæðme under firgenstréam·
in fiend's embrace beneath the mountain stream;
þæt wæs Hróðgáre hréowa tornost
that was for Hrothgar the most bitter grief
þára þe léodfruman lange begéate.
which the ruler of the people long had received.
Þá se ðéoden mec ðíne lífe
Then me the chieftain, by your life,
healsode hréohmód þæt ic on holma geþring
implored with troubled mind, that I in the waters' tumult
eorlscipe efnde· ealdre genéðde·
perform a noble act, risk life,
maérðo fremede· hé mé méde gehét.
accomplish glory; he promised me rewards.
Ic ðá ðæs wælmes þé is wíde cúð
Then I the welling waters', as is widely known,
grimme gryrelícne grundhyrde fond·
wrathful ghastly guard of the deep found;
þaér unc hwíle wæs hand gemaéne·
there a while we were sharing a hand;
holm heolfre wéoll ond ic héafde becearf
the water welled with gore, and I cut off the head
in ðám grundsele Grendeles módor
in that deep-hall of Grendel's mother
éacnum ecgum· unsófte þonan
with mighty edges, not easily thence
feorh oðferede· næs ic faége þá gýt
I carried off my life; I was not doomed yet
ac mé eorla hléo eft gesealde
but to me the protector of heroes again gave
máðma menigeo maga Healfdenes.'
many treasures, the kinsman of Half-Dane.'